shifted out of safe places, and it will increase young people in their
contact with police and the criminal justice system.
We know that setting
young people up in this kind of way does not have good outcomes for them
or for anybody. We urge that this committee
looks seriously at the
NZBORA report on this bill, which sets out unjustifiable
limits on the rights of freedom
of expression and movement, and that should be taken seriously.
In closing, we think it would be useful to look at a couple of situations that
have been put out as justifying this bill.
The
visitors from overseas who are put off our city centers because
of begging, or the restaurant owner who's been told that people don't want to
visit their restaurant because rough sleepers make them feel
uncomfortable. This bill would actually not address those
issues. People will be shifted onto somewhere else,
and even the police aren't really sure where, which is likely to cause the same
problem for some other
retailer somewhere else down the road.
And all the while, there is no improvement to access to safe and affordable
housing and wraparound services to actually help deal with the underlying issues.
And given that those issues are in their complex,
we understand that, but given that there doesn't seem to be a real plan
for those underlying issues, there are potentially going to be new people
sleeping rough in these locations, and the cycle continues.
Those are all our remarks on our submissions, and we're happy to answer any
questions.
Fantastic. Thank you, Karen. And I just want to check, Rupert, did you have
anything further you wanted to add on to what Karen has said?
Oh, kia ora, Tom. No, she's summarized it all perfectly.
I'm just here to help answer questions if necessary. Thanks.
Superb. Thank you very much. I'll just have a look now.
We've got a question from Jamie Arbockle.
Morning. I'm just interested in your take on the
police's existing powers, if you could possibly comment
on those. And just also through
community law centers, whether you actually get
shopkeepers actually in issues with
begging and stuff that have actually come to law center for advice as
well. So I'm just interested in those two issues.
Yeah. So it's our understanding and our experience that the police do have
powers to
punish or to ... Where there's somebody who's doing something that
is making someone feel threatened, intimidating behavior, that kind of
action on the street is already punishable by the police.
It already can be a summary offense, and the cops already have
powers to deal with that. And where appropriate,
sometimes they do, and they sometimes use that power inappropriately already.
So that's a problem that we sometimes see,
and we have a concern about with this
summary offense. The other thing is that we are the question.
I've not seen that in Dunedin personally, so it's not an experience that
we have where shopkeepers have come in for advice about that in Dunedin.
So that's all I can say to that effect.
Fantastic. And just see if any other members have questions.
Doesn't appear. Oh, Dr. Lawrence Sunan.
Good. Thank you, Chair.
Yeah, so I just want to pick up on one of the things you mentioned earlier in
terms of that this will actually not address the issues that we're
seeing now.
Would you be able to elaborate on why
it won't address, the bill address the issue,
and what then would be, from a CLCA perspective, some of
the solutions to address this in a potentially
win-win scenario?
I can take that a little bit, potentially.
So the problem is people struggling with
homelessness or housing instability.
I think we can all agree on that is the
broad problem that we're seeing, and it leads to all sorts of issues.
One of those issues is that people are sometimes sleeping in or making other people
feel uncomfortable in public places, and that's one of the particular issues of
many, including a great deal of interaction with
poor health and substance abuse and all sorts of other things that are associated
with this. So
this just asks people to move from one spot to another, which
is, in our view, not really a very effective method of dealing with this
problem. It's a seriously wicked problem, as I'm sure you're aware,
and so solutions are difficult. And we definitely understand
that we've seen in our experience that access to housing is
one of the key ways to support people out of this system,
or the cycle of issues that people are experiencing.
Housing first approaches,
and easier access to emergency housing, that kind of thing.
That's what we see as being an appropriate response, an effective response.
Increased declines for emergency housing.
In our experience, it seems to have led to an increased number of people living
rough, and so an increased number of the issues that we've seen.
But emergency housing isn't the only solution, because what you really need is
longer term solutions as well.
It's a tough one. I'm sorry we don't have any golden bullets for
this committee, but that's our view.
Yeah. Yeah, I don't have anything to add to that. Thank you, Rupert.
And one final question from Rima Nakle.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. Good morning. Thanks for being with us.
Look, I respect what you're saying in many regards, because we all know the
issues with respect to homelessness are quite profound.
And-
And complex. But this law doesn't aim to
address those issues.
Mm.
This law, if I may say, is more of
an immediate response to, as the examples, Karen, you mentioned
earlier, restaurant owners who in my electorate told me,
or in South Auckland told me, that people are not attending their
restaurant because of the
people-
Mm
... out the front, which come with their issues, of course.
And so what do we say to these restaurant owners that are losing
the ability to pay for their kids, to
do what they need to do, pay for their mortgage because they're losing patrons?
Mm.
Because rough sleepers, with all their problems, are out in
front of their restaurants in South Auckland.
Yeah, I appreciate that.
And I know that as an MP for an electorate,
those issues are really top of mind and important.
And I think
this bill will move that problem down the road to somebody else.
And this bill,
it won't, and then they might come
back. They might
be replaced by other people. Our
view is that this will just be a cycle of
homeless and rough sleepers coming in and out and moving
around.
I just don't think that you can say to this restauranteur, "This is
an approach. This is something that will help or that will
fix this problem."
In that
it is about a balancing act of all of those things.
But no, I don't think that there's a simple fix, and I don't think that this bill
does it either.
Okay. Thank you very much, Karen and Rupert, for joining us this morning, and
for your written and oral submission. Thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Okay, members, our next submission is from Community Housing Aotearoa, and we've
got Paul who will be joining us.
Morning, Paul. Thank you for joining us this morning.
We've got you down for a 10-minute submission.
We have read your submission, and if you can just leave a few minutes at the end
for questions. Over to you.
Thank you so much, Mr. Chairman and committee.
Really appreciate the opportunity to talk with you this morning.
My name's Paul Gilbert, Chief Executive of Community Housing
Aotearoa, and we are a charitable incorporated
society. We have 107
full members across the country. To be a full member of our organization, you need
to be a provider of housing services.
So across the country, think of city missions, think of
Habitat for Humanities, providing everything from frontline
outreach services all the way through to home ownership products.
And we walk alongside Te Matawai, the independent Maori voice for housing in New
Zealand. So just to give you a sense of the scale, our members have
26,000 homes that they look after across the country.
So we've got pretty good data and a pretty good
understanding of what's occurring from actually Stewart
Island to north of Kaitaia, and everywhere in between.
I'm addressing the Move On legislation today.
And fundamentally, I think the question that I want to ask the
committee to consider as we go through this
conversation is move on to where?
And I'll get into some detail around
what sits underneath that. But I think it's important that I begin by
asserting all New Zealanders' human right to housing,
and the importance of that. And I'm going to quote
Desmond Tutu, because a lot of the submissions I've been watching
over the past few days,
and the tone and content of the drafted legislation
as-
Looks like we might have lost Paul.
I'll just see if the committee staff are able to either get him back.
Ah, here he is.
Sorry.
Welcome back, Paul. You're all good.
Thank you. Apologies. Technology dropped out just briefly.
I'm going to quote Desmond Tutu because a lot of the stuff that we are
doing seems to be addressing symptoms rather than root
causes. And I think we need to start thinking more systematically as a nation
and planning longer term and delivering longer term solutions rather
than dealing with the symptoms. So that's that quote of
his, "There comes a point we've got to stop pulling people out of the river.
We've got to go upstream and start figuring out why they are falling in
in the first place." And so
fundamentally, we reject the criminalization of homelessness.
It is the core of our submission.
We reject the characterization of rough sleeping as
criminal.
And we are asking you to consider
throwing out the bill in its entirety.
Or as a backstop, if that is not your
recommendation, to at least remove the clauses relating to
begging and rough sleeping, and I'll give some reasons for that.
As you and people all over the country may have noticed,
homelessness continues to increase in Aotearoa.
And the profile of homelessness appears to be changing, with
more people becoming homeless for the first time.
So that's alongside the entrenched and repeat homelessness that's occurring.
And so one of the things that we're asking you to think about is, well,
why is that? And fundamentally what we have noticed
is that it's a lack of available supply and a lack of
options for people to move into. I think a more
concerning trend that we've noticed, though, over the years is
not just the changing profile of homelessness, where there are increasing numbers
of youth,
pregnant moms, particularly women.
We have a very odd profile of homelessness in New Zealand, with over 50% of
our new homeless being women.
Pacific peoples,
young people in their 20s, and particularly a growing cohort of older adults
And so
where are they coming from? Well,
actually, the state and the agencies of the state, and the
behaviors of the state are one of the largest causes of homelessness.
And what I'm talking about there is people being discharged from hospitals who
are deeply sick into homelessness with no
preparation or accommodation, people being released from
prison into homelessness. So one of the things we're going to ask you
to consider as a committee, as part of your deliberations around this legislation
is, well, if we are, as the state, acting on behalf of our
taxpayers and our citizens, actually creating the homelessness,
maybe we should talk amongst ourselves and coordinate our services a little bit
better so that we're not one of the main drivers and causes
of the homelessness that we're seeing on the streets.
I think on the optimistic side, what I wanted to say to you is there's
a lot of things that we're doing that are working really well.
And so Housing First is a good example of that.
There are many programs and products where we are coordinating.
And I say we, the community housing sector, iwi, hapū,
community groups, faith groups, are coordinating with the
agencies of the Crown, and the Crown agencies are coordinating with each
other to get better outcomes. So we know that there are solutions available to
us, and we know what works, and it's things like
low-barrier drop-in hubs, housing with support,
rough sleeper navigation, and assertive outreach services.
So I think I'll close there and open up to
some questions, but just really implore you please to
throw this piece of legislation out.
It's not a criminal matter, it's a housing matter.
Let's do what works instead.
Thank you, Paul. Thank you very much. We've got a question from Dr Laurence Sunam.
Thank you, Chair. Thank you for your submission, Paul.
You answered one of my questions, but my other question is, in your experience
and data, how many people are coming to you
that have been rejected or were deemed
ineligible to apply for emergency housing?
And-
Yeah, that-- Yeah.
Oh yeah, you go with that question first.
I do have a second-
Yeah. So look, that is a
system issue, denial of service and the constraint of
access, as you will have noted from the data.
The government target to reduce emergency housing down to 800 has
occurred
three or four years ahead of schedule,
and is clearly a driver of what we're seeing on our streets,
as people don't have an alternative
place to go. That's the place of last resort.
And just a second question, which is
on--
I'm assuming that there is capacity issues currently in terms of the services
that you provide, and there are wait lists. We've heard that from Housing First.
What
is the increase in the wait list now for some of the things
that... Yeah.
Well,
we've had to resort,
Laurence, to collecting our own data now,
effectively. Because if you think of the
MSD-administered Social Housing Register, it's an
extraordinarily inaccurate and blunt instrument, which effectively
tells you very little about the quantity of persistent unmet housing need in
the system. All it really tells you is that somebody's managed to navigate their
way into an MSD office and has managed to get their name on a list
that is held by MSD. What we are seeing,
by the way, our 26,000 homes across the country, they
are all full of people.
So it's not as if we have spare vacant capacity in our system
to accommodate rough sleepers. Fundamental issue is that we have a
lack of affordable and social housing in New Zealand, and until we
address that root cause,
I'm afraid things are going to continue to get worse, not better.
Thank you.
Okay. Thanks, Laurence. Any other questions?
Doesn't appear to be the case. Thank you, Paul.
Really appreciate you joining us this morning.
Thank you for the work you're doing as a select committee. Really appreciate it.
Thank you.
All right, members, we're coming to Just Speak now.
We've got Katie and Charles, who are both going to be joining us.
And I can see Katie is there and Charles is just coming online, which is
great. We have read your submission. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
If you can just leave some time at the end for some questions as well, we'd really
appreciate that. But over to you.
See, call Katie Perkins talking about call Charles Harvey turn up,
and we are board members of the kaupapa Just Speak.
We also speak to you as a former police officer and criminal barrister.
Thank you for the opportunity to present today.
Offences Move On Orders Amendment Bill, and request that it be
rejected.
Being at the heart of our justice system by advocating for a public justice sector
that prioritizes prevention and healing and legislation-
I might just stop you just for a moment, Katie. Sorry.
Your connection just seems to be dropping a little bit in and out, so we catch some
of your first words and then don't catch the rest of your sentence, and I would
hate for that to be your submission.
So
we can't hear you now.
I can see you are talking but can't hear you.
Is that any better?
That is heaps better.
Whoa, okay.
Much better.
All right.
Thank you. Carry on.
So Just Speak's mission is to put social wellbeing at the heart of our justice
system by advocating for a public justice sector that prioritizes prevention
and healing and legislation and policy which is based on good evidence.
We've spent some time reflecting on what this bill is really about.
On the surface, it is framed as a response to disorder and concerns about public
spaces. But underneath that, we think it raises a much bigger question
about who we are as a country and how we choose to respond to people who
are struggling. Because legislation does more than create powers, it
reflects values. It communicates what we believe our obligations are to one
another. And what concerns us most about this bill is the way it encourages us to
think about people experiencing homelessness and vulnerability.
When we see someone sleeping rough, begging, or obviously struggling, we have
two choices. We can ask what support they need, or we can
ask how to make them less visible. This bill chooses visibility as the
problem. It focuses on moving people elsewhere rather than addressing the
circumstances that brought them there in the first place.
It risks normalizing the idea that when people are in difficult
circumstances, our responsibility is not to stand alongside them, but simply
to move them on. That if hardship makes us uncomfortable, it is the
person experiencing that hardship who should be required to move.
We do not believe that reflects the best of Aotearoa.
We want to be clear that homelessness is complex.
Some people experiencing homelessness will engage with support services
immediately, others will not. There are many reasons for that: a lack of
trust, previous negative experiences, mental health challenges,
addiction, past interactions with state agencies, or simply
exercising their own autonomy and making a choice we may not understand.
The right to make decisions about your own life does not disappear when you become
homeless. People retain their dignity, their autonomy, and
their mana regardless of their housing circumstances.
And where support is being declined, we think our response
should be curiosity rather than punishment.
We should be asking why someone would prefer remaining on the street to engaging
with available services. What has happened that trust has broken down to that
point?
What can we do differently, and what barriers exist?
Because those questions lead us towards solutions, move on orders
do not. Homelessness is a social issue, not a criminal
behavior issue. There is nothing inherently criminal about being homeless.
What this bill does is change that, and that reflects on us as a nation
about how we view and care for our most vulnerable.
Thank you, Katie. Kia ora koutou. I did have a few tech issues, so if you can't
hear me, please let me know. Members,
where JustSpeak really falls on this is that we ask the committee to look at what
the evidence tells us then about what does work.
And we do know that stable housing works, adequate income support works,
wraparound mental health services, addiction treatment, recovery services,
and long-term relationship-based support, we know works.
These are approaches that have consistently delivered positive outcomes for our
most vulnerable.
By contrast, the evidence shows that criminalization of
homelessness does not solve homelessness.
Overseas experience and studies demonstrate that.
If you had a chance to read our written submissions, a recent American study that
we've cited there says that move on orders and citations
fail to reduce urban disorder, but create instead a spatial
churn in which homeless people circulate between neighborhoods and police
jurisdictions rather than leaving public space.
And the authors of that study found that these types of approaches actually
reproduce homelessness.
Studies examining move on powers and criminalization of homelessness have found
that people are not removed, they're simply displaced from one location to another.
And so the underlying homelessness remains, the poverty that's caused that remains,
and the underlying social issues also remain.
The only thing that does change is where those people are seen within our society.
And so that brings me to where our real concern is about this
bill, and that is the criminalization of homelessness.
And a person sleeping rough, of course, is not
committing homelessness, they're experiencing it.
And
should this bill be passed, all it does, in our view, is create another pathway
into the justice system for individuals whose primary issue
is issues of poverty, of housing insecurity, trauma,
addiction, and disconnection.
And we know that contact with the justice system itself can be harmful for people.
Further research that we've cited shows that the early
engagement with the justice system increases the likelihood of
re-offending and can steer people away from pro-social pathways and
opportunities. And once people become involved with the justice system, it becomes
harder to secure employment, housing,
and their lifestyle becomes unstable.
And so for people who are already struggling, this can be another barrier that they
carry for years.
There are also some practical concerns that JustSpeak has.
The
offenses under this amendment
carry a maximum penalty of three months imprisonment.
And we know that once someone enters the criminal justice system, the consequences
can extend far beyond the statutory maximum penalty.
So for example, those who we see regularly before the courts with long conviction
histories and with difficulties with being granted bail
are at risk of having remands in custody longer than the statutory maximum that
they'd receive for offenses under the act.
So that process itself can become a punishment, and it all stems from
legislation that's directed at people whose underlying issue is that they have
nowhere else to go. And so JustSpeak also wants to
acknowledge the impact that this bill would have on young people.
The bill extends these powers,
orders to be imposed on people as young as 14.
Manaaki Rangatahi: Responding to youth homelessness in Aotearoa New Zealand, a
recent published Maori-led homelessness research paper, speaks about
rangatahi as taonga, deserving protection, dignity, connection,
and care. And we think that principle is important because it extends
beyond rangatahi, because people experiencing homelessness are not
problems that need to be managed. They're people with mana, with dignity,
and they're members of our community.
And so finally,
again, from a practical perspective, we note that, and I think the submission has
been made to this committee earlier in this week, is that the
issues that this bill is seeking to address can already be adequately
addressed under the Summary Offenses Act.
So issues of disorderly conduct, violence, intimidation,
blocking public ways
are already addressed within the Summary Offences Act.
And so the proposed Section 8A in the bill
only really goes to extend criminalization to paragraphs
E and F, which involve the conduct of begging and rough sleeping, which
are hallmarks of homelessness. So in our submission, that this bill,
all it does is extend the criminal liability scope
to include
homeless, well, symptoms of homelessness.
So then the question really is, how do we deal with harmful behavior?
And we suggest that that can already be dealt with under the Summary Offences Act.
So whether homelessness itself should be a trigger for police
intervention, and the criminal justice involvement, we say
that shouldn't be the case.
So we say that as a values question,
how do we deal with our most vulnerable?
Do we offer a hand up or do we encourage people to simply move somewhere else so
that we can't see them?
And so with those values of dignity, care, respect, and upholding
people's mana, we say that the committee should reject this bill in its
entirety, and we're grateful for the opportunity to speak to you today.
Fantastic. Thank you, Charles, and thank you, Katie.
We do have a question from Dr. Duncan Webb.
Kia ora, thank you for that. Look, I'm particularly
interested in what an appropriate response might be,
not so much in terms of prevention,
because we all want to do that. But there's been some suggestion
that these are tools that the police need, and you've got some police
experience there. If you're dealing with people that are
creating a little bit of a public nuisance but perhaps not
committing an offense, what might an appropriate policing
response look like?
Thank you for the question. Well, I think
it may be practically that the police are the first to have that
contact. And I think you're right that those sort of, I guess,
gray areas between sort of genuine
pro-social public behavior and conduct that would otherwise be criminal.
The gray zone in the middle is
the hardest to deal with. And you're right, the police are practically likely to be
the first ones to engage with those individuals.
There's essentially a triage and referral approach.
Those people need to then be engaged with other social support,
and ultimately have somewhere else to go.
And I appreciate that that type of conduct in public spaces can be
difficult, and can be unsettling for some people.
But our concern with the bill is that
more of that gray zone is now shifting towards the criminalization.
And
it does come down to a resourcing of
agencies being able to intervene at that point to assist these people.
I mean, if they engage in conduct that
may not be pro-social, but not criminal and just generally disruptive,
there's likely to be further social,
mental health, physical issues going on that need to be addressed.
The police are not the ones adequately
resourced or trained to deal with that, and so it is a referral and
triage approach that Justice Access would be the appropriate
pathway there.
Fantastic. Thank you both for joining us this morning.
We really do appreciate your time. Thank you.
Tena koutou.
All right, members, we're going to have Frank
Lawton.
For
some reason, that seems to be a regular occurrence where I get kicked off.
Must have been something I've said. We're going to have Frank Lawton.
Back up yet?
Hey, Frank.
Frank.
Nice to see you. We've got you down for five minutes, Frank.
We've read your submission, and if you can just leave some time at the end for some
questions, please.
Yeah. All good.
Yeah, so my name is Frank Lawton. I'm submitting to oppose the bill
as a member of the public.
People have talked about a lot of different
critiques of this bill, but I'm just going to focus on
one, which is the remark that it's unnecessary.
So I hosted an opportunity
for members of my church to submit on this bill.
Of course, followers of Jesus are interested in how the poor and the vulnerable are
treated in our society. In the following week, an older
member of my church pulled me aside for a chat.
He told me why he felt he couldn't honestly submit sort of either
way on the bill, either for or against it.
Him and his wife own a building in town that rents out
space to a few small businesses, and numerous times at different
hours of the evening, he's had to hop in his
ute and drive himself there to deal with sometimes erratic rough
sleepers so that his renters can close up the building for the night.
Sometimes they felt intimidated or just uncomfortable, and they sort of
occupied that in-between space
in that building or sometimes the entranceway.
And because he's someone who's trying to be a
Christian, follow Jesus, he makes an effort to talk with these people
and connect them to housing or support services so that they could be safe or
comfortable for the night without inhabiting or
obstructing his business or their ability to close it up.
But sadly, they sometimes refuse to leave, or they respond with
aggression, and he's had to call the police, and he remarked to me
that
the police being able to come in and have some ability to deal with this
situation made all of the difference.
They had excellent communication skills,
abilities to deescalate, and they had a greater power than he did to connect these
people to other support
Networks, and to move them on
in that way. And so he told me that whilst he sort of is in principle
concerned about increasing police power or increasing the
types of behaviors that are able to be criminalized,
his experience speaks to the fact that something needs to be done.
And he thinks maybe this bill could be it.
But ironically, I think that his story perfectly explains why this
particular bill does not need to happen.
Under the Trespass Act, of course, 1980, police already have the right to arrest
somebody for inhabiting a business,
and if the rough sleepers were immediately outside the building's entranceway,
many New Zealand councils have public places bylaws that
specifically prohibit obstructing entrances and doorways or access
points to premises from public land.
Also, my friend's primary gratitude to the police was for
their communication and networking abilities above anything else,
which they of course always have the right to do already without this move
on orders legislation. They can always come and talk and refer people on.
So to me, his story showed that the value that police can offer in situations like
this, and of course, not every one of his examples is relevant to this
bill. A few cases they were trespassing.
But the police
offer value in these sorts of situations already, not primarily through their
ability to arrest or fine, and that's not always the
first thing they do. They're excellent in this country at
de-escalation and referring. There's also already laws
when there's erratic behaviors. Other people have said when there's
aggressive or unsettling behavior, or people
are actually obstructing a business entranceway or in a business, there are
already laws in place.
And if something needs to be done, if there's a gap there, I think the gap
isn't the presence of
homeless people in a space where they can be seen.
I think the gap is when they're sort of, like a lot of
councils have bylaws about, it's when they are actually right
outside a business or a private entranceway, and they're obstructing people's
access there. So, it seems to
me that
this law doesn't add anything, any capacities,
or any opportunity that is missing in terms of
situations where rough sleepers are actually
causing any kind of inconvenience or difficulty for
people. And sometimes there may be gaps there, but
councils can address that. Or the bill could change.
It could be not about being in a public space.
It could be about when people are obstructing entranceways
or within a certain distance of entranceways.
So yeah, I oppose this bill because it's unnecessary.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Frank. That's our full five minutes.
So we do really appreciate you joining us-
No problem, mate
... this morning, and for your written submission as well. So thank you.
Sure.
All right. We're going to have a submission now from
Business New Zealand. Let's have a look.
From Retail New Zealand, I'm sorry, from Carolyn and Ben.
There they are. Fantastic. Thank you both for joining us this morning.
We have read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, so over to you.
Kia ora. Thank you very much. I know that most of you have met Ben and I before, so
we won't go into too many long introductions. Carolyn and Ben.
Look, I know you've read our submission, and I think you've heard from a lot of
people, and there's been some very similar feedback from a lot of
submitters. I guess, from our perspective, it's a really complex sort
of space. And so,
there's a couple of things that we really wanted to talk about.
We acknowledge that retailers want to be able to undertake their
business in a safe environment and have a
central business district that is engaging and welcoming for
all members of our community. And one of the things that makes
retail great is that it is somewhere where people like to
come and engage and work in. From time to time, when there is
disruptive and disorderly behavior outside stores, that causes members of the
community and public to be uncertain about going
into those areas. So we acknowledge that there are issues that need
to be addressed around actually resolving issues when they
occur. Our concern with this bill, the way it's worded, is
there's a number of things. Firstly, the fact that you're moving
someone on
can be a breaker for disruptive
behavior when it occurs, and that is needed from time to
time. The challenge is, of course, if that person
potentially is a rough sleeper,
or is homeless, so they have nowhere else to go, and maybe the behavior is
caused by potentially an addiction or mental health issues,
they are going to move on
perhaps from Queen Street into K Road and cause the same
behavior again because the underlying issues aren't resolved.
And then from K Road, they may be moved on, and they may go to Newmarket.
And then from there, they'll then move on, and they'll go to Parnell, and then
they'll be back in front of Queen Street.
And so the issue for Retail NZ is that we support retailers across the Motu,
and when you move someone on without the right support, that is
undertaking behaviors because of their situation,
whether it's health or an addiction, then that will continue to
occur in front of another retailer.
So it's kind of complicated from that perspective in the first instance.
So, we really reiterate what you've heard from a lot of other
submitters, that underlying support services are required.
We understand it's super complicated around
Getting trust and confidence between parties and
individuals and organizations to find solutions and have
help.
But
it is something that needs to be continued to work on.
For a thriving retail environment and a thriving
city center, what we need are probably four key things.
One of the issues that we have is a lot of
disruption with
construction and roadworks. All of those things create
spaces where we have seen vacancies and
businesses move out of central city
business districts. And then as a result of that, people have come in and they do
occupy some of those vacant doorways, and that creates some
issues in terms of that space. We need
people that are not working from home, but working in the city so that we have
people in the city to make them vibrant.
And we also need a strong economy. Those are things that are really going to help
retailers. And then I guess the other piece is that when there
is disorderly and disruptive behavior, we do want to be able to call on authorities
so that they can come and deal with those situations.
And then I guess the last thing I would really leave you with is that we don't
believe that we should really be addressing this issue
as categorizing people as the issue.
It's the behavior that's the issue.
What we know is that anyone from any walk of life could suffer
from a mental health condition. We know that addictions such as
alcohol or drug addiction can occur with anyone in our society,
not just if you're a rough sleeper or homeless.
So we actually really would like the committee to consider focusing on
behavior, as in parts of the bill, I think eight
A, one A, B, C, and D do reflect
that, but the additional pieces where you specifically call out rough
sleeping and
begging, thank you, Ben,
we don't think is necessary, and I think you've heard a lot of reasons why, and we
would support those. And then I think lastly, I would just say that the police
do a really amazing job, and we support them having the right tools and resources
that they need to undertake this work.
And the Police Association is someone that we reach out to and talk with, as
well as having spoken to police directly around what is it that they need.
And there is some conversation about do they actually have the existing
tools that they need right now, or will this enhance that?
So I think really leaning into that space to understand from the police
perspective.
Fantastic. Thanks, Carolyn. And thank you, Ben. We've got a couple of questions.
We'll start with Rima Nightclay.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. Good morning. Thank you for being here, Carolyn and Ben, and
thanks for the work that you guys do.
Look,
notwithstanding that, I do want to ask because what you're saying doesn't seem to
correspond with what I hear from the retailers in South Auckland, across a
number of electorates that I know retailers there.
So that's the
first thing. And with the
subject matters with respect to profound and complex issues that come
with our people that find themselves homeless.
There's so much that the government is doing in terms of in the mental health
space,
increasing availability and social housing.
But back to the question with South Auckland, have you spoken to retailers
in South Auckland about how they feel about this proposed law?
We've spoken to lots of retailers and retailers right across the country.
And I think the key thing is that what we're saying is that when
issues occur, we do need the police to have the tools
to solve those issues and move people on when there is disruptive
behavior. But calling out
individual types of people and saying that if someone is a rough sleeper or they're
begging, that you can move them on without there being any disruptive behavior,
I don't think that's what retailers are actually asking for.
They're asking for issues when they occur to be able to be addressed.
Yeah, just a response. What I'm hearing is that the fact that they're
begging in front of their store, and people find themselves in those situations, I
accept that. But the fact that a lot of begging is happening in front
of these stores is intimidating people from going in. I'm not intimidated.
I buy the beggar's food. But it's intimidating other people from going
into the stores in South Auckland. That's what I'm hearing.
And I'll just keep it there.
Yes. And so you move someone on and they're going to move in front of another
store.
I hear you.
So what we're saying is we need to actually sit down and take some time to think
about how do we solve this so that they move on from a store in
front of South Auckland. Maybe they go to...
Our camera's going a bit crazy. Maybe they go into somewhere in front of
Southeast Auckland or they're just going to go 400 meters down the road or a
kilometer down the road. So I think it doesn't
solve the problem just moving someone on, because it goes in front of
another retailer.
Thank you.
And that's where the police come in. Yep.
We've got another question from Dr. Lawrence Sunan.
Thank you, Chair. And I think this follows up because from Rima's
question, I think you're maybe in the best position to do that.
What advice would you then give retailers if, for example, they're
faced with customers, et cetera, who said, "I just don't want to go into a
store because I'm worried, even though with begging or I just don't like to
see it."
How would
retailers respond to something like that if they are faced with that when there is
no threatening behavior, like you said?
Yeah, it's tricky, right? Because every member of our community have
different thresholds around what they're comfortable with.
And
no retailer necessarily wants to see someone begging that's right in front of
their store. But
if you go down Lambton Quay or Willis Street, if you go down Manor Street, Courtney
Place, anywhere in Auckland, there are lots of places where people are
begging. So it's really understanding if we want to criminalize
that, then that's probably a slightly different conversation that we need
to have, and we need to think about different tools.
But if we're just trying to address
disorderly and disruptive behavior Then I think we should be
really clear that that's what we're doing, and we're not actually addressing
people that are begging or rough sleeping.
Because they're still going to be doing that activity somewhere else.
Got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you. Thanks very much for your written submission and for
going over those important points today.
I just had a question. I think at the beginning of your submission, you say you're
supportive of the objective of the bill,
but then you go through and list all the existing tools
that police have and I've noted your objection in relation to the begging and rough
sleeping, which I agree with as well.
In terms of the bill,
say if those two aspects were removed,
what benefit to your members is
there in the other parts of the bill, considering the comments
that you've made around the existing police powers and resourcing issues,
which I think are noted too?
Yeah. Look, I think, because it's a really complicated space, and
the advantage is, if there is somebody that is
having a mental health issue and is hugely disruptive in front of a store, if
there's a fight going on or there's any sorts of those sorts of behaviors
that are happening, it gives the ability for a break to
happen and for that behavior to be ceased.
So I think that
having that
breaker for a retailer is really useful.
For example, in Newtown, there's some significant problems in
Newtown and Wellington. There are a lot of support services in that area, and so it
attracts a lot of people that need those support services.
A significant number of people that
reach out to the City Mission, for example, they may have
underlying health conditions, and it means that their behavior in
front of stores continues to be super disruptive.
Now, when you move someone on from that area, they will be back the next
day because that's where the support services are.
So it is truly a complex space, and how to
try and find a safe environment for everyone in
our community is really difficult, because the social agencies need
somewhere to be,
and retailers need somewhere to be.
So how do we find a way that is safe to navigate that
pathway? So having a break point when there is really
difficult behavior happening in front of store is really useful.
But what is the long term solution so that you're not just calling the police back
every day to undertake that behavior
when someone clearly needs some help?
And I would add just to the end of what Rimu said.
Rimu said, beg your pardon. That's where police come in, but hand in hand with
coordinated multi-agency support, evidence-based approaches.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Carolyn, and thank you, Ben, for joining us this
morning. Really appreciate your time and your written submission as well.
Kia ora. Thank you for your work.
Good to see you.
Okay. We're going to have Annette Dixon who's going to present to us next.
Kia ora. I very much appreciate the opportunity to talk to you today.
I'm talking in my personal capacity, and I want to do two things.
Firstly, I live in Central Auckland and I want to tell you a bit about
what I observe around me, and secondly, to pose some
questions and some thoughts about the way forward.
Just introducing myself quickly.
I returned to New Zealand about three years ago after working abroad
for many years at the World Bank. And in the course of my work
and travels around the world, I've seen a lot of poverty.
But what I see in Auckland also deeply shocks me.
Many years ago, when I first went to Washington, DC, to study,
I was really shocked to see a man sleeping on a park bench with his
wheelchair parked up against it. And it was
unfathomable to me at the time that somebody who uses a
wheelchair in the richest country in the world could be
homeless. Fast-forward to 2026 in
Auckland, I have twice seen people using wheelchairs who appear
to be sleeping rough in the city around me.
Now, the people I observe around me living in Central Auckland
frequently exhibit signs of illness. They're not just homeless.
Their lives have spiraled in a direction to get them to this point.
But there's a diversity of
people, and increasingly I see more women.
But there's roughly two groups of people I see.
The first group are
very recluse. They do not engage. They're much,
much more isolated. They're alone.
And I think they come to my neighborhood because they feel safe here.
And they are extremely fragile and withdrawn people.
But there's another group of people who are more outgoing.
They seem to be seeking safety and community in those around them, and
these people are generally a lot noisier.
They gravitate towards shops where there are more people and are
frequently panhandling. And while their
social behaviors may be distressing, it's very rarely of a
criminal nature. I can honestly say I've never felt
threatened, even when I'm bussing home or walking home in the evening
after events in the city. But what does distress me is the
social disaffection of the people that I see.
And to be honest,
living in Auckland, I'm much more
afraid of mostly boys on
scooters and on bikes riding through the pedestrian walkways,
frequently on these very large electric bikes on one
wheel.
But that brings me back to the questions that I think you are
probably asking yourselves. What is the problem that this bill is trying to fix,
and what is the right way to get there?
Now, I have considerable appreciation for the role that the police play in
Auckland in keeping the city safe. I feel very safe here.
But it's my contention that the police already have considerable powers to deal
with the antisocial behavior, which,
as many of you have talked about, it is
actually the issue that's causing concern.
A lot of it is criminal, but in many cases it's not.
And in that sense, the police have
considerable powers already. Now, if the goal of this bill is to enable
the rounding up of scores of rough sleepers to remove them
from view, then I wonder what the police can do with them.
They either take them back to the cells and process them through the criminal
justice system, or frequently they will
drop them at the emergency departments at the public hospitals, which is what
is already happening to a considerable effect, and we know these
departments are already overloaded.
Now, I, like many others presenting to you
today,
emphasize that the increased number of rough sleepers should be
addressed through a comprehensive approach, through access to
emergency housing, and then comprehensive longer term support
to deal with the complex social and health issues that
these people face. Now, if
the bill passes and we continue to fail to provide the kind of
housing solutions that these people need, will it merely drive
these people out to the perimeter to settle under
motorway underpasses or to go into the bush and to
go into even less safe conditions.
And frankly, it makes it harder to bring these people back into society and
back to the services that they need.
So from my point of view, I don't think that the bill actually
addresses the problem that we face.
One last point I would make is that a lot of the people who are
exhibiting antisocial behavior may not be homeless.
They may be gravitating to the streets to be around other
people because of other issues that they have in their lives.
And so from that point of view, I don't think that the bill is addressing the
problem that the retailers and restaurants are concerned about
on one hand, and neither does it deal with the underlying issues related
to the homelessness that
exists in my city. Thank you.
Thanks, Nic. That is the five-minute allocation that we had for you this morning.
I really appreciate your written and oral submission, and thanks for joining us.
Thanks.
Fantastic. We're now going to go hear from James Barber.
Hi, James. Thank you for joining us this morning.
We have read your written submission. We have you down for five minutes.
Five minutes.
And if you can just leave a little bit of time at the end for some questions as
well. Over to you.
Hi. Kia ora koutou. Thanks for the
opportunity to be heard. I hope you can hear me well enough.
I'm actually outside at the moment, partly as political stunt, but also partly
it's the end of the paycheck week, and I'm waiting to pick up some
kai from the bread queue at the Sally's Army because we've eaten through our kai
budget for the week.
I'm a parent, part-time teacher, got two kids.
We live in Berhampore in Newtown. Our kids go to Newtown school,
so we're really familiar with
the issues in terms of people on the streets in this
area.
I usually go to the Newtown supermarket.
It's a fairly regular haunt, and yes, I can't go in without being asked
for some money, but
this bill is not the answer to these issues.
I worry that the way this is worded, that
this bill will lead to people who need help being moved further away from
help. In Newtown, we have, where I am, behind me, a
Sally's Army bread queue and drop-in center.
I worry that people will be moved further away from that.
Down the road on Adelaide Road, we have Whakamaru.
Further down Tory Street, there are things like Orange Sky, the cleaning services,
stuff like that. I worry that people who need help will be moved further
away from that help.
And the answer to these issues is not
moving people further down the road.
The answer to homelessness is homes.
The answer to poverty
is sharing resources,
not giving billions of dollars in tax cuts to landlords.
$14 million in services ain't going to cut it.
That is my submission. I was just asking one person
here whether he wanted to say something, and he said, "I don't think the powers
that be will listen. It'll be like talking to air."
Yeah, that's right.
He's just said, "Yeah, that's right.
That's what I said."
So
prove him wrong, prove me wrong, and listen. Kia ora.
Thanks, James. And we've got a question from the Honorable Dr Duncan Webb.
Oh. Uh, kia ora. Thank you for your submission, um, and the
work you do. Look, one of the challenges for this committee is that we have not
heard from people who are going to be affected by this, um, this proposed law.
So if your friend, uh, who's there w- wants to say a
few words, um, this is Parliament, everybody gets a voice.
Go for it.
Go and taste what it's like to be hungry.
Okay. Well, what I've heard is why don't they get out of their comfort zone and
taste what it's like to be hungry? If you want to listen, why don't you come
down to the places where people are waiting for food?
Sorry, Duncan. That was the response.
That's all right. It's all good. Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, James.
Thank you very much for joining us this morning and for your submission.
We do really appreciate it.
All right. Prove me wrong.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submitter is going to be the Citizens Advice Bureau in New
Zealand. Sasha.
Morning, Sasha. Thank you for joining us. We have read your written submission.
We have you down for 10 minutes. If you can just leave some time at the end for
questions. Over to you.
Kia ora, thank you. Tena koutou katoa.
Thank you for the opportunity to appear before the committee today.
I'm speaking on behalf of Citizens Advice Bureau, New Zealand.
We strongly oppose the Summary Offences Move on Orders Amendment Bill.
Our submission is informed by what we see every day through our network of
80 bureau and over 2,000 trained volunteers across
Aotearoa.
Every year, we support hundreds of thousands of clients
involving issues to do with housing, income support,
employment, debt, family violence, everything you can possibly
imagine. And we believe that this bill
punishes people for the visible consequences of systemic failure
that put people in situations of homelessness and poverty
rather than addressing the causes.
The people we assist who are sleeping rough, who are begging
or spending long periods in public spaces are often there because they've
exhausted every other option.
Over the past year, CAB recorded almost
1,600 inquiries relating to homelessness and
housing precariousness, and that's a 12% increase on the
previous year.
We're also seeing increasing complexity in these inquiries with
more families experiencing homelessness, more people
facing overlapping challenges, including disability, mental
distress, addiction and family violence.
We see an overrepresentation of Maori, more and more situations of
both younger people and older people,
and
an increasing number of women experiencing homelessness.
We also are assisting people who have often sought emergency
housing but have been declined or have been told that they no longer
qualify for support, and we know some of the background to that.
They come to the CAB asking where they can sleep, how they can access food,
and how they can advocate for the assistance they are entitled to.
Against this background of struggle and hardship,
we do not believe move on orders will provide public safety,
and it certainly will not reduce homelessness.
Move on orders, as their name suggests, simply shift people from one
place to another while leaving the underlying issues unresolved.
We are concerned that the bill may make it harder for vulnerable people to
access support. Public spaces are often where people
can access food assistance, transport, public facilities.
We heard from our friend in the previous submission who was standing in
the queue for such support,
and community organizations like CAB.
Many of the people we work with experience also significant
digital exclusion, so they rely on face-to-face
services because
they don't have reliable access to phones,
internet or online government services.
So displacing people from the locations where they do access this
support just risks disconnecting them and
further aggravating
those challenges that they're facing.
We are also concerned that the bill risks criminalizing vulnerability.
As you're aware, failure to comply with a move on order may result
in prosecution and a criminal record.
Through our work, because we have a dedicated phone
line for people who are in prison, but we also then
see many people on release from prison, and we
regularly see the long-term impact even
relatively minor convictions can have on employment, housing and
financial
stability. So this bill will bring further people who are not
disorderly or intimidating or otherwise doing anything we
currently consider offensive or criminal behavior
potentially into the ambit of the criminal justice system for merely
sitting or sleeping in a public place.
We are particularly concerned that these powers would extend to children and young
people aged 14 and over. And to be fair, I
don't know that the police are only going to know how old someone is once they
engage with them. So the risk is that even younger children
are then being
engaged with by the police. Young people experiencing
homelessness or housing instability
require protection and support, not increased contact with the
justice system. So we urge the committee at minimum to remove
children and young people from the scope of the bill.
Finally, we question whether these additional powers are
necessary. I've heard many of the submissions that have made the same
points.
Existing legislation already provides police with powers to
respond to threatening, violent, intimidating, obstructive or
genuinely disorderly behavior. We
consider there's a failure here to identify a clear gap in the
current legislative framework that justifies these additional powers.
Instead, the bill introduces broad,
imprecisely defined powers that may be applied to conduct
that is not unlawful or harmful, but is perceived
by some to be undesirable
What these additional powers do is to allow the police to act to remove
the discomfort people feel when confronted with societal failure,
with poverty, addiction, homelessness, mental distress,
loneliness and exclusion.
Our experience is that communities want compassionate and
practical solutions.
As well as having many inquiries from people who are
homeless, who are in
unstable housing situations. Our experience is that commu-
um, we also have people regularly approaching us,
asking how they can connect people with housing and support, not
how they can be
punished, including business owners.
For all these reasons, Citizens Advice Bureau New Zealand recommends that the bill
not proceed, and that instead there is priority placed on
investment and evidence-based responses to homelessness,
poverty and social exclusion.
If the committee decides to recommend the bill progresses,
we
urge the committee to at least remove children and young people from its scope,
and to limit move on powers to situations involving
clear and demonstrable harm.
Thank you for this opportunity to present our submission.
I welcome any questions the committee may have.
Thank you, Sasha. We've got a question from Rima Nakley.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thanks, Sasha.
Sasha, just confirming, are these your personal
opinions, or are you speaking on behalf of Citizens Advice Bureau?
On behalf of Citizens Advice Bureau.
Okay, that's interesting. And the second thing is,
with respect to you addressing the
underlying issues,
I'm really proud of the fact that the government has a mental health minister
that's addressing a lot of mental health concerns, which are prolific.
Yes.
But I want to say that I just find it a little bit sad to hear
that the feelings and the thoughts and the
real issues that retailers face in south Auckland
with this behavior. And the objective of the bill is not to
criminalize people that are homeless.
It's to actually stop situations
from getting to that point where criminal behavior exists.
So do you accept that one of the objectives of the
bill is to
address that middle gap between behavior
escalating to a point where it becomes criminal?
Sorry, that's a lot in that question.
For starters, I'm confused why you would not have
thought I was presenting on behalf of Citizens Advice Bureau, where
that is very clear here.
In
terms of what you're saying,
if it is about a gap, we're talking then about behavior that is not
criminal, is not at a level that it is
deemed to need that level of intervention.
That's where leaning into the support services that are in our
communities to respond as appropriate, not the police.
And that's what I see in our inquiries, including
one that I've included in our submission there from a local business owner who
was concerned about people
sleeping rough close to their premises and the impact on their
business. But they were coming to us because they wanted to know how could
they access the support services that those people might
need. They had been to the police. The police had told them, "It's not a criminal
matter."
So, I think people are wanting compassionate responses,
and I don't see it as appropriate
for the police to be the ones filling this gap.
Do we have any time, Mr. Chair?
One final question.
So Sasha, the Police Minister, Mark Mitchell, has said
numerous times that part of the police's response will be
to help direct people that are in these situations, that they have to give move
on orders to relevant services. Have you heard him say
that?
Yes, I have. But the
interaction with the police in and of itself escalates the
situation.
Mm.
It puts people in a situation where they are more likely to be
reactive, where it is giving a message, as a
society, that we consider your
situation to be something that has the
potential to be criminalized. And things could escalate quickly,
which does lead into those additional powers the
police might have then to detain someone, to get their
details, to end up in an escalating
situation. So-
If they disobey the move on order. Yes
Yeah. And
moving people on or connecting them with services, we then need to address the
issue of the support and resourcing for those services-
100%
... to respond.
Yeah. Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Sasha.
Thank you very much for your written and your oral submission.
Kia ora.
Okay. We're going to have a submission now from Justice for All Incorporated.
Suzani is going to be joining us.
Good morning, Suzani. Thank you for joining us this morning.
We've got you down for 10 minutes.
Yeah.
We have read your written submission, and if you can just leave some time at
the end for questions that members may have. Over to you.
I try. So I'm Suzani from Justice for All, and I'm out
here in New Brighton at the red zone.
And
I have with me Chris, who is living here at
the red zone. And then I have Fire with me, who is the camp
mother here. And I've got Trudy,
she is running the New Brighton
food bank. And we will just start. So
Fire, can I ask you a question, please?
I would like to know when you heard about this bill-
What was the biggest thing you thought immediately of?
How did it feel to you?
Good morning. It felt really horrible because
imprisonment's not the
answer to it all, because
it's like the 52 people that got shot here in Christchurch, well,
that man went to prison for something real bad that he did.
Well, we have people innocently going to
prison, and
I've been there.
I know what it's like.
And if you're putting innocent people in prison, they're going to learn a
lot more. And for women, I'm very sorry, a lot
of them mothers that come into prison, they end
up
either going lesbian or they're going to
learn more trades of crime. And it's a wrong idea of
putting them in prison. So we're here to help
the homeless to
not go to prison. They won't pay the fines.
We talked about this a bit,
and you talked about the stress and anxiety it caused.
Can you talk about that a bit, please?
A lot of them come here with trauma, most of all.
But after having 10 minutes with them with a cup of
tea, and
getting them to trust me, they soon open out.
And a lot of it,
it is hard because they
intend to
shut off from society.
And-
So we try to bring them back
... and you think the bill is not doing any good for
that?
No, the bill is, that's a load of crap.
Okay.
It is.
You're punishing people-
Yeah
... for
something that is out of their control-
Yes
... really.
I think we're already seeing some of the results here.
They speak for themselves here, of the move-on orders that have come from the ones
from the city that have come out here.
There's nowhere else for them to go, so they know to come out here to New Brighton.
But what we're seeing is some of these, we're seeing mental health issues.
Yeah.
We're seeing that some of them have a different attitude.
They live a little bit differently in the city than what these guys
in this community live. So, it takes a little bit of that
rubbing off and having to say, "How do we live like this?"
And then you've got the ones that don't want to live here, and they've gone into
New Brighton itself, but they're used of living-
Around the orders
... in the city, and in the buildings and under shelter.
So here they are doing that in the shops now in New Brighton, but it's
causing trouble. They're
floundering because they've been moved on, so they've gone to an area they don't
know, and they don't know how to be there.
Mm-hmm.
But what is affecting Fire and Christine that fear particularly
is the mental health.
We have a nurse that comes in, but only once a month.
And that doesn't do any good. And so,
we're really needing that here at the moment, and a place
for them to know they can go to, I think is one of the most important things.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
And so you talked about that sometimes at night people
get-
Uh-
... put here. Can you talk about that a bit, please?
A lot of people who are on the meth,
they are night walkers.
They are night people.
You don't see them during the day. You only see them walking around.
Well, our dogs let us know that they're there.
And, it's really frightening because to them
it's like,
what? Beautiful sunny afternoon, and they're talking loud, they're opening
doors, they're closing doors. We have workers here, so
we're trying to keep the workers safe as well.
So, this
area where you are, you ask for drug-free and
alcohol-free?
Yes.
Is that true?
We put up the signs for drug-free.
Yeah.
That's a proportion here.
The addictions are bad.
Yeah, and there's more too, isn't it?
Like, so that mums-
Mm
... women, and particularly families, like with little children.
They know that there's an area here that is drug and alcohol-free.
Mm, mm.
Yeah.
So mental health is really a big issue here.
Yeah. We
haven't been trained to deal with mental health issues.
Mm-hmm.
It's out of-
Yeah. Yeah
... it's out of our range. It's-
And again, the move-on order is not helping at all.
No.
It's just causing more and more stress.
Yeah.
We're already
trying to survive in winter-
Yeah
... with very little. So the fear of
getting thrown out of here is just-
Mm.
Yeah
... where do we go?
Yes.
What do we do?
But it's also the ones that are coming into here.
Yeah.
That
it takes a little bit to adjust, doesn't it?
It does.
And you get some that don't fit, and they're
causing trouble-
Yeah
... some of them. So.
That's where we have to move them along, because-
Yeah
... we're trying to take care of the people who-
... who actually do want to help themselves.
Mm-hmm.
They just need that support.
Mm.
So that's good. We talked the other day, Fire, about what
is your aim? What do you want to achieve with this?
Keeping our people out of prison.
Okay.
That was the shocker of it all.
Yeah.
It was putting innocent people into prison-
Mm
... so that they can learn more.
But you talked about as well, show them how to get on their
feet and-
Yeah, we've got-
... be independent.
Well, we've got free tech over here on
Pages Road, and we have a free gym. And we
encourage them to give back.
I take them back to their childhood.
What did you like to do when you were in intermediate
school? And their interests, we put that into progress to
bring them back
Because we know damn well that they've been on drugs and alcohol and
everything like that. But if we can bring their minds back to what they
loved doing when they were children, well, we bring that up
to them again to put them back on that.
Encourage them back into it.
We bring them back. That's what it is.
It's like they've gone missing because of all the drugs and because
of all the alcohol, and when they get out here, we shower
them, we feed them, and we then will look after them.
So
just to take over, just for a minute, I think it's very
clear that we don't need the move on order, we need much more help.
And,
so people who are living here, they just told you what they
need. Mental health is a really big thing here.
Mm-hmm.
And they are not equipped. And once a
month, a nurse coming around, it's maybe not enough.
So are you guys okay to answer questions?
Yeah.
Okay. So yeah, please.
Great. Thank you very much. And we do have a question from Dr
Lawrence Sunan.
Yeah.
Thank you, Chair. It's hopefully a quick question. Thank you, Whaea.
Thank you for the submission. Can I check, what do you
think the public got wrong about homeless whanau?
What would you like the public to know?
That we're not
...
Yeah.
We're not criminals.
We're just ordinary people that have found ourselves in a
position. We were struggling financially.
I'm 64 and a half years old. I'm a qualified
chef. I can't find work because of my age.
I don't have a drug or alcohol addiction in any shape or
form. I'm just struggling. We're just ordinary people.
We just need a bit of help and support.
It's simple really.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you.
So, yeah.
What else?
Yeah, and I don't think people don't realize that
the amount of trauma. Nearly everyone here has had so
much trauma in their lives that have-- it's never been dealt with.
If you put it in plain language, you can say
that
an average white person that is at middle income, if
trauma happens in their life, they can go to a counselor. They can talk about it.
Here,
these people, do you think they could even get on a bus, maybe some of these
people, let alone go into office, sit behind a desk with someone
asking them questions. The whole thing needs to be
looked at differently.
How to talk with these people. They do live
differently. This community is thriving because
they have
come together. Whaea is camp mother.
This morning, she's made porridge and mince here for these guys.
And they love her because someone is loving on them, and that's what
they want to know. Someone-
Thank you.
Yes.
Thank you. We've got time for one final question from Kieran McAnulty.
Thank you, Chair. I actually don't have a question.
I just wanted to use the opportunity to thank you all very much for putting this
submission in. I thought it was extremely powerful and
really hit home. And so thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thanks for taking the time to listen to us.
Thanks for joining us this morning. We really do appreciate it. Okay.
Members, our next couple of submitters aren't here with us at the moment, so we're
going to move forward to Daniel Baldwin.
Awesome. Well, we heard you.
Hi, Daniel. Thank you for joining us this morning.
We have read your submission. We have you down for five minutes.
If you can leave a little bit of time for questions, we would appreciate that.
But completely over to you.
We can't hear you at the moment, unfortunately, Daniel.
There we go. He's coming on.
Hey, Daniel.
Hello.
Hello. We've got you down for five minutes. We've read your submission.
Over to you.
Do you want me to start talking now?
Yes, please.
Hi, my name is Danny Baldwin. I've had many years
involvement in the homeless sector.
I have worked as a volunteer in a night shelter in London for 13 years, and
currently I'm on the board of a community housing trust that builds and
provides housing for around 700 people in Auckland.
In getting to know these people, I'm constantly amazed at how easy it is for people
to slip out of their secure existence into crisis, and then just
how frustrating and bewildering it is
facing the housing system and the subsidy system that is constantly
changing and confusing to navigate.
For me, one of the reasons I'm against this bill is that it is essentially
punishing those in our society who most need support.
Forcing someone to move on when they have nowhere to go is not a solution.
It is an act of displacement that strips away their dignity.
It is essentially coming across
someone with a disability and punishing them for not getting out of your way.
The other reason I
oppose this agenda is that it's a
dangerous precedent in criminalizing poverty.
A fine or a prison sentence for being visible in a public space
does nothing to address the root causes of poverty, and it will put
people, some as young as 14, into a justice system by
giving them fines and prison time.
And
this threat of prison brings me to my final point of just how financially
inefficient this solution is for New Zealand
taxpayers especially. We know a single homeless person moving through
crisis systems
such as emergency departments, psychiatric care, and
justice facilities quickly accumulates thousands of dollars
in taxpayer costs. And just one night in prison
is approximately $500.
As I said, I'm a trustee of a community housing provider that was started 40 years
ago, and supporting housing models are proven
to not just take people off the streets, but to help them
face hardships and mental illness or other trauma, to rebuild their lives with
dignity and care. But such solutions do not just benefit the
homeless.
A study conducted by Tu Whare Ora showed that the impact
clearly helped.
It was demonstrated that the hospital stays dropped by 92%
just after one year in one of our homes, which is
a clear saving for the New Zealand taxpayer.
Every dollar that New Zealand invests in a community housing program such as
ours, there is a saving of $4.50 in taxpayers' money.
Look, I know this bill isn't about housing, but the real problem we are
addressing here is, of course, due to a lack of housing.
Currently, public and community housing sits at
3.8% of New Zealand's total housing stock,
whereas the OECD average is around 7%.
And unlike European nations that
invest directly into building physical public structures, New Zealand
actually spends more per capita than all of them on social rental
housing. But this taxpayer money,
to the effect of $2 billion, actually goes
to subsidize rentals in the private sector rather than investing
in future public assets or tax-efficient, not-for-profit
community housing that provides wraparound support.
Look, we just don't look after our homeless people enough.
It starts right there. I want to see the government invest in
tax-efficient solutions to poverty by funding housing first initiatives
rather than policies that are basically an ambulance, or even worse,
if this bill passes, a paddy wagon at the bottom of a cliff.
Thank you.
Thanks, Daniel. I will just see if any members have questions for the last
few moments that we've got.
Doesn't appear to be the case. Really grateful for having you join us this morning
and for your written submission as well. So thank you.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay. We're going to go back to the Waka of Caring Charitable
Trust with Debbie and Troy.
Hi, Debbie. Thank you for joining us this morning.
Hopefully you can hear us all right.
If you can just switch on your camera and unmute yourself, please.
I'm
learning how to use all this. Murray, how do I switch my camera on?
Sorry, guys.
That's okay. We can hear you all right.
It's a learning in progress. So how do I switch my camera on?
You're doing great.
Okay. Well, I'll carry on talking. I'll start my video. Is that it?
No.
That's it. Yeah, hit that one.
Okay. Right.
There you are. We've got you down for 10 minutes, Debbie.
We have read your written submission, and if you'd just leave a little bit of time
at the end for some questions.
Okay then. Kia ora koutou. My name is Debbie Munro, and I run
Waka of Caring Charitable Trust. We have been running for the
last 12 years,
looking after the homeless on the street.
The last eight years, we managed to get a building, so we have
our own drop-in center where we look after all homeless,
and whanau in need.
Yeah, I don't know where to start, to be
honest. We absolutely
struggle with what we see here. The people that walk into
Waka of Caring
at night, nowhere to stay. We've had women, we've had children.
And you know what my biggest issue is?
Not being able to contact the so-called outreach programs that are
supposed to
pick up people like this. And it's not working.
Nothing about the homeless is working.
We cannot lock them up. That is an absolutely
ridiculous answer for people in need,
whanau in need. There's got to be something better than
what is happening now. Why would we want to waste all that money putting
people to jail?
Seriously, it does not make sense to me.
In the last
six weeks, we have had over 32
people walk in our drop-in center that do not have anywhere
to live.
Our last one was a mother with three children.
Now, we're a drop-in center, so people just drop in and ask for help, and
we usually can
reach out to other organizations and get
them into housing and that, and that is not working anymore.
They are either
There's just nowhere to put them.
So where are our whanaus with children supposed to
continue living in cars?
Go to jail. What happens with the kids when they go to jail?
Why are we penalizing our homeless like we have for the past
12 years? It is just
getting out of control. There has got to be a better solution
than what is happening now.
There is so much to say, and it's
sad to see that New Zealand has come to the point where our
answer is to lock them away.
When did we become such a harsh
country on people in need?
I did not grow up with this.
I'm
concerned about my own family, my mokos, my children,
my friends, my volunteers. Anyone can become homeless.
Anyone can lose their home tomorrow,
and there is no
security for people anymore,
especially with the
law about landlords can just get rid of you in 60 days
for no reason at all. We're finding that we get whanau come
here because of that. And what are we supposed to say to them?
"Oh, go and sleep on the street. Get arrested.
Lose your kids." No, that is not
the solution. The government needs to rethink what
they're doing. I'd like to see some of them living on the street.
Perhaps what some of them should do, go and sleep on the street for a couple of
nights and see what it's like.
We did, and it was cold, it was scary, it was
damp.
But honestly and truly, throwing them in jail, giving
them a $2,000 fine, they can't even pay the
$2,000 fine.
Where are they going to get the money for that if they're living on the street?
Where are they going to get that money?
And I think people tend to forget
we have a couple of different types of homeless.
We have the ones that we can see on the street, and we have the ones that are
sleeping in cars, hiding in bushes,
sleeping in overcrowded housing.
Do we really, honestly and truly want to lock them
up because we, as a country,
can't be bothered anymore looking after our less fortunate?
I would like to think no,
but the way that things are going,
people are going to die. People are going to get sick.
We need to be spending money into some good
solid
organizations. Not all these organizations out
there
are doing what they should be doing.
If you've got an outreach program, I would expect to be able to ring that
outreach program at
9:00 at night and say, "I've got a mother and a child that need
somewhere to stay. What are you going to do about it?" You know what?
They don't even pick up their phones.
What does that tell you?
Our drugs, our alcohol are a huge, big impact on our
homeless,
and mental health.
Mental health is just
intertwining with the drugs and the alcohol and the violence
and
not knowing where people's futures are, and our whole system, not just
housing, but our whole system needs to change.
You can't fix one without fixing the rest.
But I'm just
really passionate about helping anyone that
needs help.
Walker of Caring, we did a sleepover on the street
to protest
with
this new law.
We've done a march, and then we did a memorial day that we
remembered the people that have passed on, the ones that have
died on the street.
That should not be happening in New Zealand.
I am embarrassed of New Zealand right now because
we are killing our whanau in need,
whether it be mentally, physically,
and locking them up is not,
and I repeat, is not the bloody answer.
Kia ora.
Thank you, Debbie. We do have a couple of questions.
We'll start with Dr Lawrence Sunan.
Yep.
Thank you, Whaea Debbie. Thank you for your submission.
Can I just ask you, having worked with homeless
whanau, what has the New Zealand public
or people gotten wrong about homeless whanau?
Not all of them are drug addicts. Not all of them are
alcoholics.
Not all of them are beggars.
The assumption that all homeless are
bad, no.
Yes, we have some homeless that are not in a
good headspace, but then we have families.
There's a great big difference, and I think people need
to
understand
why people are homeless. It's not just because of, oh, yeah, they're drug
addicts, or, oh, they're on the benefit I mean, we are seeing
working families come to us because they're living in
cars. So I think the
judgment and the assumption that all homeless fit into
one box, that is not true.
Thanks, Debbie. And we've got one final question from Rima Naklay.
Kia ora, Debbie.
Kia ora.
Local member here from Takanini. I've seen you around, and we've spoken a few
times. Debbie,
the thing is, I first want to reiterate, and I'm very happy to come and see you
when I'm back in the electorate soon to
explain this to you. We're not criminalizing people for being homeless.
It's if they get a move on order and they don't follow it,
which lasts for 24 hours, that's when the police will have to step in
on that next level. That's the first thing.
And the-
But where do they go?
Yep, there's other places they can go, but they need to move away from where the
police are telling them to move away from.
And you know, you're familiar with a lot of those business owners in
Manurewa that are good people that are trying to raise their families too,
that are struggling because of people not coming in because
of the intimidation they feel from people out the front of their shops.
You know, Debbie.
Where's the question?
And the... Sorry, Dr. Duncan Webb?
I said, is there a question in there-
We're talking here
... or is it a lecture?
Thanks very much, Doctor. Come to Manurewa.
Come to Christchurch.
And second,
Debbie. Debbie, those families that are not finding housing,
send them to either me or to Arena. I know Arena doesn't have an office,
but we can forward them to Arena staff member that is apparently
always on the phone and email. We can help them find places.
And what are you going to do?
Help them find a place.
Why?
Because they'd be entitled to find somewhere. We'll help them through MSD.
Oh, absolutely, they're entitled.
But a lot of these organizations are not doing what they should be doing.
I agree with that.
A lot of these organizations are not finding houses for
the ones that really need it. And you know what?
95%, well, hold on, I'll reframe that.
65% of our guys
that are on the street are not homeless.
Did you know that?
That's why they need-
They are not
... they should be entitled to a home.
They are not homeless. You're not listening. They are not homeless.
But they're on the street.
They are not homeless. Trust me, I know.
I'll tell you the ones that have-
Right. Thank you. Thank you very much.
Go down to Manurewa-
Let's talk
... and check out the real homeless.
Thanks. Thank you, Debbie. Thank you very much
for joining us this morning and for your written submission as well, and spending
time with us-
You're welcome
... presenting.
Okay.
We really do appreciate that.
Brilliant, Debbie.
Thank you for listening to me. I was a bit nervous, but thank you.
You guys have a good day.
You did a great job. Did a great job.
Okay then.
Thank you, Debbie.
Thank you so much.
Bye. Bye.
Okay. Members, we're going to come to the Dunedin City Council now.
We've got Councillor Mickey Treadwell who's going to be joining us.
Hey, Mickey. Thank you very much for joining us this morning.
We have read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, and if you can just leave some time for
questions.
Thank you. Just verifying that I am audible on your end.
Fantastic. Well,
tena koutou. Thanks so much for giving me the time to present today.
As you know, I'm presenting on behalf of the Dunedin City Council.
You can take our submission as read, and I'm just going to expand a bit on
basically local context and some of the points that were in that submission as
well.
So
the Dunedin City Council maintains that decent housing is a human right.
As such, we are committed to ensuring our residents live in safe,
healthy homes. And this is reflected in our social wellbeing strategy through which
we maintain 940 community housing units, and also through our
housing plan. Now, to give effect to our housing plan,
council staff work proactively with local police, central government
departments, and other social agencies around the city that care for the city's
homeless whanau.
This includes connecting them with physical and mental health
services and facilitating and supporting them into stable
accommodation where possible.
Homelessness and deprivation are broad social and material
problems in Aotearoa.
And I've outlined a couple of the approaches that we take as a council to address
this in our locality. But what's required is a properly
resourced, collaborative approach between government at a
central and local level and social agencies.
But effectively criminalizing behaviors associated with homelessness,
by doing so, this bill instead shifts the burden of responsibility onto the
police,
which is an outcome that the Police Association does not want.
Earlier this week, Steve Watt submitted against the bill on behalf of the Police
Association, and he noted that the bill risks drawing police back into
managing these broader social issues, while at the same time the organization
is being directed to step back from frontline mental health responses.
The quote here from him, "We don't want to target those with mental health,
physical health, or financial issues. That's not our role.
And where would we move them to? Move on orders will just displace the problem."
Steve also noted that legal mechanisms already exist to address antisocial and
harmful behaviors within the Summary Offences Act. But I won't labor that point.
But the approach that we take in Otepoti
is mindful of the fact that it's often actually the most vulnerable in our
city that are perceived as a threat to safety.
There are people out there facing really extreme hardship, often with complex needs
relating to mental health, sometimes addiction is a factor, and they're the
people who are most likely to be affected by this bill.
Vulnerable people often live in the most visible parts of the city because those
are the safe parts of the city. There are people and lights and
facilities, and they're less likely to live in a dangerous situation.
If, as a result of this legislation, those vulnerable people are pushed out of
those visible spaces, it will increase the likelihood of them coming to
harm.
It's been suggested that move on orders might be deployed to direct people to
shelters or other social agencies,
which is laudable,
but we don't believe that a legal mechanism is necessary for this.
The Dunedin City Council is currently in the process of implementing an in-house
homeless outreach service,
and that's designed to support vulnerable people and tackle homelessness in
Otakapu through assisting people, particularly who are sleeping rough,
assisting to connect them into stable housing solutions.
So if the intent of this bill is to protect the public from harm, it's
unclear how it would achieve that given what we've heard from the Police
Association.
If the intent is to shift homeless people from visible public spaces, it is our
concern that it would place those people in greater harm.
And if the intent is to direct people to support services,
I would suggest that it's redundant.
An effective approach to tackle homelessness is going to be one that
addresses the needs of homeless people.
Obviously, that most immediately means housing, but also just
recognizing their need for support, community, and
recognition.
By effectively criminalizing certain behaviors associated with homelessness,
it takes a punitive approach
rather than a compassionate one.
And on that topic of compassion, and on a personal note, what prompted me to get
involved with this issue is my position as the Portfolio of Youth
Issues.
I think there's an awareness, a broad awareness that housing deprivation is
increasing,
but I think a lot of people are surprised to learn that it's actually children and
young people who are experiencing homelessness more than any other age group.
Otago University professor Neville Pearce has a good quote on this.
"Children and young people do not choose to live on the street.
Many have left unsafe homes, experienced family breakdown,
become too old for state care, or have nowhere else to go.
Yet emergency, transitional, and public housing can be difficult for young people
aged 14 to 17 to access." So while
we recognize and applaud efforts to reduce homelessness,
we don't recognize that it's a problem of criminality, but rather one of
material deprivation and one of health that we are all responsible for.
People can't be punished into health, nor can they be punished into prosperity.
The Dunedin City Council does not support the new powers outlined in this bill,
which will effectively criminalize behavior that is not inherently harmful,
and also suggests that this could undermine our local efforts to both address city
safety and to support people experiencing homelessness and poverty.
Mauri Ora, ka mihi, and happy to take questions.
Thank you, Mickey. We do have a question from Dr Lawrence Sunan.
Kia ora, Mickey. Thank you so much for your submission and the work that you do
with the Dunedin City Council.
I've got two questions. The first one is, from a council perspective,
what should
central government be doing or in collaboration with local
government when it comes to addressing the root cause of homelessness?
It's my first question.
Yeah, I think
that's a broad topic.
One really clear impact
of central government involvement has been the change in direction from Kainga Ora.
So we were sort of operating under the assumption that we'd have another
Kainga Ora housing units, which we no longer have.
So housing supply, I think government has a piece to play there.
But additionally,
continuing the support of community groups through
grants, charitable and otherwise, are actually a really big piece of this puzzle.
A lot of the support around our homeless whanau is through sort of
interconnected charitable and other non-profit
organizations who are often applying for these kind of grants.
And
so ultimately, community grants and things of this nature
play a really critical role in supporting homeless whanau.
So cuts to those kind of things or making them more difficult to access actually
has a big flow on effect to making the struggles of our homeless
whanau more severe.
Cool. And my second question is, you mentioned youth being a
particular group. From
a Otakapu Dunedin perspective, have you seen
an increase in terms of homelessness in Otakapu
Dunedin as well as a shift in the demographic?
We've heard submitters saying there are now more women, more pregnant women,
more seniors, et cetera. Do you also see that in Otakapu
Dunedin?
Yeah, absolutely. So we have-- That is directly informed by
reports from our frontline services.
They have reported increased demand over the past few years, and the
proportion of that increased demand, the youth proportion of that has increased.
I'd also note that OUSA, the Otago University Students
Association, has become more aware of this over the past
couple of years, and they conducted a survey, which I don't have the results
handy for. But they were really surprised at the number of students who were
actually experiencing homelessness, including rough sleeping.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Mickey.
Really appreciate the written submission from the council and for you presenting
this morning, so thank you.
Thank you so much for your time. Kia ora.
Okay, we are going to go to Max Marshall, who's going to be presenting now
Good morning, Max. Nice to have you back with us.
Good morning.
We've got you down for five minutes.
We've read your submission, and if you can just leave some time at the end for
questions. But over to you.
Okay, very good.
Good morning, everyone. Thanks for allowing me to speak
today.
I
want to start by saying that I think
it's the social dimension which the bill misses,
and which
is the half which I think is the most and more
important part. Law is useful, but it fails without this,
an endeavor of social change for individuals in this position,
in terms of pro-social behavior modeling
being done alongside of and support of.
Some comments to give an outline of my thinking.
Charles Merton said the following points, "Humans act
towards things, including other individuals, on the basis of meanings that
they have for them." And secondly, "There is
a particular emphasis on the consciousness of actors as they
interpret their actions."
A law might come in and try to treat the part which offends people most.
That's understandable, and that's what I get about the bill.
Fine. It is what it leaves out, which is more troubling and more
difficult.
And I would say that it is the visibility of this crime
or behavior that society struggles with the
most, and which has provided the impetus for the
proponents of the bill.
What is often missed inside of this or what is not as
apparent is the view of the homeless persons,
individual's own agency. The homeless
person is not a passive subject. This
visibility is intended by the homeless person and serves
a different function to further his own interests.
It has been the recognition of the free
will of the actor towards his actions,
which has been an idea of importance when instituting and
creating law as far back as Bentham.
We, the audience, have been asked to see this homeless person in the
role where they are in an uneven or unequal
position of power to everyone else.
This performance is intentional, orchestrated to make the effect a
spectacle.
And that is why it is important to get with a client's definition of their
problem.
A schizophrenic patient who's required to take medication
compulsorily may start seeing the
medication as the problem instead of the behavior when he is off
his meds. A sexual offender may not take his view of
offending behavior as the problem.
His goal instead might be to avoid detection in the future.
I argue a good society is one that challenges people to look at the
sets of questions which determine their life and their choices.
I argue to not do so is a great injustice.
One's decision to live on the streets,
I would add, is as much
our decision,
not what the one,
only one among many. A person who goes into a
retirement village will have a different set of questions than someone who
chooses to live their life out in their own home.
I argue that empathy cannot serve as a substitute for
pro-social modeling. But what about society's
role? For our part, we allow homelessness to
persist, and this is a society's own reluctance at
undertaking this important work of social
modeling, pro-social modeling. While empathy may set the
path for change,
but we have often used this to
stretch this, leaving no room for pro-social modeling.
Empathy can be an alibi for our lack of action or
even indifference. Empathy in response to
pro-criminal behavior can give subtle permission or sanction for
continuing the behavior, and it is important that we identify with
and model pro-social behavior alongside of this bill.
I argue that empathy is a feature of our society,
in some way is to abandon the group because empathy demands nothing in
return from the individual. Love cannot exist
without the dimension of discipline.
For the police, it is important to acknowledge their difficulty
inherent in their dual role of social controllers and helpers.
The law is useful, but it will fail without this great endeavor of
pro-social change for individuals in the position.
And so it's important that we identify and model pro-social
behavior along with this bill.
Thank you, Max. And that is your full five minutes.
So really appreciate you submitting with us this morning and for your time, and
nice to see you again.
Thank you.
Okay, members, we come to Community Groups Feeding the Homeless, and we've got
Audrey, who's going to be presenting to us.
Hi, Audrey. Thank you very much for being with us this morning.
We have you down for 10 minutes. Please do leave some time at the end for
questions, and we have read your submission.
You are right. Thank you. So I'm speaking on behalf of Community Groups
Feeding the Homeless Incorporated.
We strongly oppose this bill.
Our group came about because the City Mission in September
2018 stopped serving its evening meals.
So various voluntary groups started serving meals, and it
was suggested that we collaborate with each other, which is what we have been
doing ever since.
Two of the groups we mostly support are Waka of Caring, and
you heard Debbie Munro speak earlier today, and Sunday
Blessings, and you'll hear Danielle from that group speak in a few days' time.
So we supported Waka of Caring to get their initial funding to
set up the drop-in center, and we continue to support them.
So rather than talk about why the proposed legislation is
unnecessary,
harmful, inconsistent with the Bill of Rights, and won't
solve the problem of homeless people being visible on our city
streets, I'd like to focus on responses to the perceived
problems.
I'll be talking mostly about Auckland.
So the problems that this proposed legislation is designed to
address are the downturn in business and the lack of
safety in the city center.
The increased presence of homeless people in the city center is taking much
of the blame for this.
They've been blamed for rising crime and disorder, despite
serious assaults in the Auckland CBD dropping over the last year or
so.
The Minister of Justice stated yesterday that if you're lying in a
sleeping bag on the ground, on a bench, or in a doorway,
that is currently not covered by any
offense. We do not see how someone lying in
a sleeping bag is a threat to anyone's safety,
except perhaps to the person in the sleeping bag.
This bill has been described as being about safety for the general public,
but the health and safety of people who sleep on the street is at high
risk.
Homeless people are dying in their mid-50s,
whereas the rest of us expect to live for about an extra 30 years.
The downturn in business in Auckland City Center over the last few years
could also be blamed on the lengthy City Rail Links
works and by ongoing roadworks,
the latter described by Mayor Brown in March 2023
as unjustifiable economic and social
disruption.
Online spending has greatly increased and is now nearly one-quarter of
all retail sales, with much of the spending in
overseas markets.
There is also the increased cost of living
and the preference many have to shop in malls.
We note that homeless people are sleeping on the street in other cities
too. Huge numbers across the United States, for example.
If the bill is passed and homeless people are moved on to
somewhere and business does not improve, what
then?
In New Zealand, as elsewhere, more public housing would help with the problem
of people sleeping on the street.
So would more and better mental health services, more resourcing
of the community services working with homeless people,
more knowledge shared, and better ways of working together.
Our submission states that Housing First needs more funding and
visibility.
We think more landlords need to know that the payment of rent is
guaranteed and any property damage is covered.
We hope that the publicity created by this bill is helping more
people know about Housing First.
We think the government and councils could help to publicize the program
more,
such as in local board newsletters, on billboards, and
on buses.
We also think that a night shelter for Auckland is essential, and we're not
alone in thinking this.
Members of community groups feeding the homeless have
advocated since 2016 for the reestablishment in
Auckland of a night shelter or night shelters.
For people experiencing homelessness, a night shelter would provide a safe
place to sleep, potentially somewhere to store their
belongings,
and it would help those services supporting them and people who know
them to locate them.
Having something to do during the day is also important.
We applaud the programs that the Auckland City Mission and that Heart of
the City have supported for people on the street to be involved
in something and perhaps learn a skill.
The Waka of Caring drop-in center in Manurewa also provides
programs such as literacy, learner
licenses,
and food safety certificates.
We also think lockers for homeless people to store their gear would go some way
to solving the problem of people leaving their bedding and other
items on the street.
The new railway stations could be good places for lockers.
A large part of the perception of threat or lack of safety around
homeless people seems to be an unwillingness for members of the
public to engage with street people.
In our experience, they appreciate being acknowledged.
Our two most recent Auckland central MPs have engaged with homeless
people during their terms,
namely Nikki Kaye and Chloe Swarbrick,
both serving at Sunday Blessings meals at different times.
We would encourage more MPs to meet and talk with homeless people,
especially the ones in their own neighborhoods.
It might have been this comment on Facebook on the bill, "The
homeless aren't another race or species.
They are New Zealanders who, for whatever reason, are struggling
and need help."
That highlighted for me that New Zealand's primary
responsibility is to New Zealanders
And that rather than protecting a cruise ship passenger from having
to step over a homeless person,
our focus should be on giving that homeless person a bed
to step into.
The discussions around this bill have highlighted what is and what is not
currently available to homeless people.
More people now know that Auckland does not have a night shelter.
More people now know that the City Mission hours, as per their
website, are 8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.,
Monday through Friday.
More people now know that for transitional housing, a
referral is needed, followed by an assessment,
and these processes don't happen outside of Monday to Friday.
Maybe now Auckland Hospital staff know to keep until 8:00
a.m. people they have treated in the emergency
department, rather than dropping them off outside the City
Mission in the middle of the night.
Rather than proceeding with this bill, it would seem that what is needed is more
information,
including what works well overseas,
more conversations, and more collaboration between
all those working in this space.
Thank you.
Thank you, Audrey. I'll just see if any members have questions for
you.
Does not appear to be the case. Really appreciate you joining us this morning and
for your written submission, and I think we're going to be seeing you very shortly
again for a private submission from you, too.
That's right. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Members, we're just going to take a five-minute break.
Be back at 10:35 for our next submitter, please.
All right, thank you. 10:35, back for our next submitter.
We are going to hear from Ka Leung Ko,
or I think you might be called Gary.
If you're with us, Gary, we'll bring you up online.
Hey, Gary. Thank you for joining us. We can see you.
We have read your written submission.
We have you down for five minutes, and if you can just leave some time at the end
for questions.
Yeah. Kia katu, and members of committee.
Yes, my name is Gary Ko, and I know some of the
panel over here. But today I'm not representing anyone, but just a Auckland
citizen.
Before, obviously, like everyone, I prepared a script,
but like the other side of the
submission, I would like to ask how many of you have been
on Queen Street in the last three years?
Although there's a lot of concern about
the housing and homelessness, but I think this bill is not a housing
policy
and also not a wider policy of how to tackle mental
health, drug or,
yeah, homelessness or mental health issue.
It is a bill just for front-line people
to protect the public safety of people
who use the public space.
Disregard my personal experience,
how many of yourselves feel safe walking on Queen
Street
in the last four years?
I think fundamental right of people is not only to homeless people,
but to shop owners, business owner, even normal
citizens that who use the same space, and we have a
fundamental right to feel safe.
How many shops has been blocked by
people living on the street? How many bus stop that people cannot sit?
How many places become their private restaurant or eating place,
which actually owned and paid by
businessmen who just try to make a living, like one of the committee
members said.
And if I read the bill right,
no one is going to put someone to jail because they are
poor. The move on order, in my understanding,
is give the frontline officer practical mechanism to
defuse situation before it escalated
to
criminal offense.
And it set a very clear boundary for
destructive behavior and/or just putting people into jail.
So a lot of submission earlier saying that this is
criminalizing poverty is totally out
of contact.
And also, in my understanding, it is only a temporary restriction up
to 24 hours. Only if after 24 hours
it hasn't happened, criminal offense will be enforced.
I understand that long-term social support system has to be
continued funded and addressed, but in elsewhere, in
other policy.
But protecting a safety corridor or a
working place for every single citizen in New Zealand
is vital. Not only cruise ship tourists
or overseas students, but people who use the city, live the
city, and work in the city.
And I support the bill because the bill provide a sensible balance approach to keep
our community safe, open,
and use that for everyone.
So thank you for everyone time, and yeah, welcome for any questions.
Thank you, Gary. We've got a couple of questions.
We'll start with Dr Laurence Sunam.
Thank you, Chair. Thank you for your submission, Gary.
I think one of the things that we've heard from submitters, I guess two
questions. Number one is, if you move people on, where do
you think they should be moved on to?
Because we've heard that you move someone from Queen Street, they will move to K
Road. You move someone from K Road, they're going to move on to Pitt
Street. And after 24
hours, they come back because there's nowhere else for them to go.
So I think I would be keen to hear from your perspective on where do you think they
should be moved on to. My second question is,
you say that everyone should have access to the public space.
Doesn't that also mean that people who are not threatening,
who are--
you get rough sleepers, you get beggars who are not
getting in anyone's way, they will be caught in this bill as well.
How do you think about that? What are your thoughts on that? Thank you.
Thank you, Dr Laurence. That means two questions.
One is,
you're asking me where are they going to move to, and second question is,
yeah, not all of them are threatening.
So I address the first issue. I make a submission to
support this bill. I didn't make a submission to have to
help people where are they going to in the homelessness.
I think the situation over here
is we put all the issue into one bill.
This bill only, in my opinion, fixing one issue.
But I think as a country, I challenge everyone over here
as well,
we as a country, we try to put all the issue together and try to fix
every issue together in one bill,
which obviously
Tell us already it didn't achieve anything. So I think one thing at a time.
And as my submission said, totally understand there should be
some place they go to, but it should
not,
yeah, it got nothing to do with this bill. Put it this way.
I don't think it should be mixed up. That's the first thing.
And second thing is
intimidating or non-imitating is very subjective,
or yeah, subjective matters. But according to my reading on the bill, I
read it quite a few times, it's when it got obstruction, and then when it is
having a public obstructing or public or
threatening behavior, they will be moved on.
So in my understanding, the police are not going on the street just move on anyone
they think they are blocking the road
other than they have behavior or got complaint.
Thank you, Gary. And I'm sorry, Suz, we are out of time for Gary this morning.
But thank you very much for joining us, Gary.
We really do appreciate you presenting to us.
Thank you. Thank you.
All right. We're going to come to our next submitter, which is Rachel Wright.
Kia ora.
Can
you all hear me okay?
We're good.
My name is Rachel. I live in Wellington.
I actually grew up in the Rangitikei, so kia ora to Suz.
And I am a law graduate. I studied at Victoria University
and currently I work in community in a mental health
organization.
I'm also a parent, and I live in Mount Cook and
work in Newtown. So in my travels around the city, I do often
see the real increase in the homelessness,
in the homeless population here in Wellington,
and I definitely think it would be good to find solutions.
I do not think that this bill is a solution.
From a justice perspective, I believe that the main offenses addressed in this
bill are already covered by existing laws.
I don't think it's good law to double up on that or to create an extra targeted
approach for certain communities.
I would like to note that the New Zealand Police Association, I believe, have also
submitted against this bill along those lines and talking about
enforceability. So I don't think it's a practical solution
to bring in the measures proposed here.
From a human rights perspective, I believe that sleeping and begging should not be
offenses, that people who need help shouldn't be punished for
asking for it, and that people who don't have anywhere to sleep shouldn't be
asked to move on and shouldn't be displaced.
I think making homelessness less visible doesn't solve any of the underlying
problems, and if we look at the health outcomes and the life expectancy for people
living on the street,
we can see that there is a real problem.
I think personally, it's pretty clear that the answers there are to provide
healthcare, mental health and addiction support, and more resourcing for our
community organizations that have great solutions to these
problems. I don't think people should be displaced for public
comfort, and I think that walking down Queen Street and feeling uncomfortable about
how many homeless there are is not the same thing as a threat to safety.
I believe, as I said, that if someone is being intimidating or causing property
damage, that's already covered by New Zealand law.
Finally, as a taxpayer, I don't think that criminalization is a cost-effective
solution. According to Corrections 2024 to
2025 report, it costs about $400 to $500 a day to house a
prisoner or about $200,000 a year.
According to a Nelson City Council homelessness report from 2022,
it costs about $65,000 to the taxpayer for someone
to remain homeless in terms of the support and police intervention they might
need. But social housing models like Housing First estimate that it costs
$15,000 per annum to provide someone who's currently on the streets
with safe housing. Those are the methods that I support, and I really firmly
oppose this bill. Thank you.
Thank you, Rebekah. Really appreciate-- Oh, sorry, Rebekah. Thank you, Rachel.
Really appreciate you joining us this morning.
I'll just see if any members have questions for you.
Doesn't appear to be the case, but we really appreciate both your written and your
oral submission. So thanks for joining us.
Thank you for your time. Ka kite.
Okay, members, our next submitter is Jared,
and we are going to just bring him up now.
Morning, Jared. Thank you very much for joining us this morning.
We've read your submission. Please do leave some time at the end of your
submission, but we do have you for five minutes, so thank you.
Roger that. Thanks.
Kia ora. My name is Jared Heager. I'm a recent arrival
to Aotearoa, New Zealand as of the start of this
year. I've been an engineer for 16 of the past 17
years and hold a master's degree. But more than that, I'm a community
activist and organizer.
I come before you today in protest of what I would call an
atrocious bill. The move on orders Bill
310-1.
In total, this bill will result in a waste of government spending and will
worsen the conditions of Kiwis over time, especially the most vulnerable.
There's
no empirical evidence that I could find that the unhoused members of our
community and society impact businesses or
tourism or in these specific areas.
I think it's more of a
vibes or a feeling sort of thing.
In any case, we're in a global spiral of
unaffordability, inflation, social media related mental health
issues,
drug rehabilitation responses that
do not-- I mean, addiction is a tough disease to treat.
There's myriad other issues that combine to make
homelessness
a growing problem worldwide, and
especially here.
Well, at least according to the 2025 Ministry of Housing and Urban Development,
around 3% of the country's population is vulnerable to being
unhoused. But I believe that 2025 study is basing its
numbers on the 2023 study, so it's
very possible that the actual number is higher, and the rate is increasing as
well. Oh, I should have asked, can everybody hear me okay?
Okay.
I think historically, we can say that the root cause
of individuals becoming homeless and staying that way is typically a
fault of the system, the state.
Society has been curated in a way in which everyone must fit a specific 8:00 to
5:00 office mold.
You must be physically capable, and you
must not have suffered trauma at some point, which affects your ability
to work.
Services meant to aid people to fit that mold, like mental health,
women's shelters, battered women shelters, they continue to be
defunded, or they rely completely on
NGOs or the generosity of the public.
And in an environment of mass inflation, people have
less money to donate. They have less time
to donate.
Drugs remain criminalized, making way for organized crimes and gangs,
which scoop up these people that are already on the
margins of society. We've seen that globally too, especially in
the,
I don't want to say Western world. I know there's probably a newer term for that.
But now we have a global fuel crisis on top of it, which is going to add cost
to every single sector of daily life.
None of these things are going to be the least
bit affected by this move on bill, these root causes of the issues.
This is truly
something that would just sweep the problem under the rug or push the problem
to a different street,
away from
what little support system these folks may already have.
So I'd like to draw attention to Finland.
Finland has basically ended homelessness with the logic that it's impossible to
deal with addiction, mental health, or disability whilst living on the streets.
Housing first is their primary
method of eliminating the issue.
Like I do, they consider housing, a roof over your head, to be a human right,
and there are no preconditions that must be met to be given this right.
This bill doesn't address mental health, physical disability, addiction, or
generational wealth inequality.
It only serves to compound the already tenuous situation of these members of
society. Now I'd like to go into the text of the bill, and then I'll probably run
short on time. So
the bill itself gives far too much leeway
to violate civil rights of a person on the street, unhoused or not.
Disruptive, as stated in Section 8 (1) , is far too subjective to use in a
legal framework.
If I sneeze too loud, does an officer think that's disruptive?
I don't have to be unhoused for that to be used in the future.
8 (1) is far too subjective. Sorry.
Officers are already empowered to deal with people that are behaving in a manner of
8 (1)
, so I would call this unnecessary or doubling down, like the other young lady
said. 8 (1) (c) could be used as a cudgel to stop persons
from picketing or other forms of civil disobedience, furthering issues between
citizenry and the state. You press people, they revolt, they push back,
especially people that are already marginalized.
8 (1) does not properly define breaching the peace, and broad language such as
that invites civil rights abuses.
What is the point of this? How will this help Kiwis in their daily lives?
Where are these members of society supposed to go
now that the system's failed them?
New Zealand has a history and an image globally of being an
egalitarian society, being young, very progressive,
and the world is watching.
And things like this,
this is not who we are. We're better than this.
Thanks, Jared. That is the full five minutes of your allocated
time. But we do really appreciate both your written and your oral submission, and
for joining us, so thank you.
Appreciate y'all.
Thank you. Okay, members, we're going to have Audrey come back to present to us now
in her private capacity.
Hey, Audrey.
Welcome back. You know how it works.
We've got you down for five minutes this time for your submission.
Hello again. I'm on a different computer, which may just throw me out, but
I'll email you what I'm going to read if that works.
Thanks again.
This time I'm going to focus on
a night shelter.
Just checking you can hear me okay?
Yes, we can.
Good. So,
talking about Auckland, most other cities in New Zealand have a night
shelter.
Auckland had one until 2012.
I was pleased to hear our city commissioner, Helen Robinson, state at a
public meeting about the move on orders that she has for years
been advocating to central government for a night shelter,
saying she would like to see thousands of them across the city.
I agree that a number of smaller night shelters in different parts of the
city is a good idea
I'd like to read extracts from an open letter to the Auckland mayoral
candidates and Chamber of Commerce that was written on the
26th of April 2016, so 10 years
ago,
by Michelle Kidd QSM,
who retired in 2023 after 31 years as a
social worker at the Auckland District Court.
She helped set up restorative justice conferences
and the Court of New Beginnings, which writes off charges for
repeat offenders committing low-level crime and helps
Auckland's homeless off the streets and into work.
So these are extracts.
"Dear sirs, madams, research by the Auckland City Mission
shows the number of homeless in the Auckland CBD doubled
between 2013 and 2014 and almost
tripled in the four years from 2010 to 2014.
This growth in the number of people living on the streets has been highly visible
in the central city, but now extends into the greater Auckland
region.
Yet the city does not offer the most basic amenity to start
turning this problem around,
a night shelter.
Most of our homeless are victims of either Auckland's deepening housing
crisis or physical or emotional abuse or neglect.
They may suffer from disability, mental health or addiction
issues, have little or no formal education,
or a combination of such factors.
Without a stable base, homeless people have no access to
social services that might enable them to begin confronting
the underlying reasons they are on the streets.
Further, as long as they are left to live on the streets without support,
they will be exposed not only to the elements, but also to harm,
such as physical and sexual violence.
While it is time for the Auckland Council to lead a response,
there is a real opportunity for other sectors to contribute and take
collective responsibility. The corporate sector would be
an obvious partner.
The international reputation of Auckland is at risk.
New Zealand's largest and most prosperous city should lead the country by
example.
Visitors to Auckland are greeted by the sight of our homeless on the streets,
a stark contradiction to the most livable status Auckland
craves.
The city's failure to provide for basic human needs is on display
for all to see.
An emergency shelter acts as a place of transition from where people
can contact their support networks or be put in touch
with the various agencies that can provide
assistance. From the shelter, they could then go on to
another place."
So that's from 10 years ago. I thought it was very
eloquent, and she put
quite a few
aspects about the problem that other people have been talking about as
well. I'll just finish by saying I understand that there are empty
council properties in Auckland, also empty crown
properties.
There have been a number of groups that have tried to set up a night shelter in
Auckland. They need support.
Like Michelle, I believe support would be forthcoming from the
community, service groups, parishes,
philanthropic individuals, existing charities,
businesses, and others.
Thank you.
Thanks, Audrey. We've got time for one quick question from Dr Laurence Sunam.
Thank you for your submission, this one and next one, Audrey, and the previous one.
In your submission, you mentioned about the impression that members of
public feeling unsafe due to
having unwillingness to engage. I guess, what advice would you
have people to engage with people, with homeless whanau
to learn a bit more?
It's just a matter of talking to people when you see them.
They're often on the street. If you say hello, you're often in a
conversation with them. There are also the community meals that everyone's
welcome to come to, whether homeless or not, so that's
another place where you can meet with people, get to know them,
and just have a conversation.
Mm.
Thanks, Audrey. Really appreciate you being back with us this morning, and thank
you for your submission.
Thank you very much.
Okay, members, we're going to go to Ted Howard, who's going to be presenting
now.
Good morning, Ted. Thank you for joining us this morning.
We have you down for five minutes, and we've read your written submission.
Over to you.
Thank you.
Good morning, and thanks for this opportunity to speak.
I don't have a problem with the general idea of a move on order,
provided the police are actually asking for it, like the police
sergeants, the ones who have the most practical experience, but that
doesn't seem to be the case in this instance.
I have no issues with the grounds 8A 1A
through D, which, provided they're interpreted reasonably, are
forms of real nuisance.
My deep issues are with the grounds E and F, begging and
sleeping.
I have once in my life, about 53 years ago, found
myself out of money in a city a long way from home,
having not eaten for 12 hours and having had only about two hours sleep in
the previous two days,
and being in desperate need of both food and sleep.
Tired, hungry, out of resources.
I needed help,
and your order to move on would not have helped in any
respect.
There are plenty of people on our streets in far worse position than I
was back then.
If people need help, then we as a society need
systems that provide a level of assistance that
meets their essential needs.
Telling someone who is asking for help or just needs to
sleep, and they are not causing a nuisance,
as that is covered by other sections, that they need to move on
is not being helpful. It's not meeting their basic level of social
cooperation needed for a modern civil society.
This is not the Kiwi way.
We help people who need help.
Most Kiwis need to be really desperate
before they will ask for help, and when they do, we need to listen.
We need to show respect and compassion.
These two subsections are a step too far,
and I ask that they be removed.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ted. We've got a question from Dr Lawrence Sunan.
Sorry, that was from a previous hand up, but I do have a
question.
Thank you so much for your
submission, Ted.
You've mentioned in your submission something
different that other submitters haven't, which is around automation
and AI.
Yeah.
Would you be able to just elaborate on how--
I guess, what are some of the knock-on effect for that, that then would
contribute towards homelessness?
I'm just interested in terms of how you draw that link.
Okay.
I don't know how to compress this into a short time, but I'll
try. This is one of the most complex things that we
currently face.
But if I can do it simply,
our current economic system is scarcity based.
So in order to generate value, something has to be scarce.
And to prove that to yourself, just think of air.
It's arguably the most important commodity for anyone, and yet it
has zero value on a market. So advanced
AI and automation allow us to take-- give us
the technical capacity to deliver the needs of
everyone to everyone.
But the economic impact of doing that is to drive the value of all of those
things to zero. So there is not simply zero market
incentive to do that. There are an active set of market
incentives to prevent that happening, ever,
because it destroys profit and value in the economic system.
So we are now in a situation where AI and advanced
automation have the potential to make life of
everybody profoundly more
beneficial than most people can imagine, and yet the economic
system is structured such that it
requires poverty to function, and the introduction
of AI and automation into that system will
rapidly accelerate the accumulation of funds to an ever
tinier percentage at the top, leading to ever broader
poverty down the rest of the chain.
So
unless there are profound changes in the next two years, I
see poverty and homelessness becoming far more widespread than
it is currently.
Fantastic. Thank you very much, Ted, for joining us this morning.
We really do appreciate your written and your oral submission.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submitter is Gemma Peterson.
Good morning, Gemma.
We can hear you all right. Thank you very much for joining us this morning.
We have you down for five minutes. We've read your written submission, and if you
can just leave some time at the end for questions.
Great. Thank you. My name's Gemma.
I'm a key worker for Housing First, but I'm here speaking
as myself.
I just want to touch on a couple of points before talking a little bit about my
experience working with our homeless whanau.
So off the bat, the government has tried to draw a distinction between
the move on orders and rough sleeping.
I reject that distinction.
There are already provisions under existing
laws for antisocial behavior, and as others have stated, it is
included in the bill specifically, rough sleeping, begging,
indicating intent to inhabit a public place, which I feel is quite a vague
way of putting that.
Secondly, I view homelessness as a structural issue,
and one that disproportionately affects Maori,
and the statistics represent that almost half of Auckland's rough sleepers are
Maori.
Or, sorry, over half, about 60%. Almost half come from
state care, which is also disproportionately represented by Maori.
Maori are more highly criminalized than Pakeha.
71% of our incarcerated wahine are Maori.
Some of that is socioeconomic,
socioeconomically related from colonization.
Some of that is ongoing bias, and we've got statistics that represent that as well.
So it's an individualized response to a structural issue.
So that's a couple of points I just wanted to bring up.
But speaking more to my experience as a key worker.
One, I'm aware of the reasons why our rough sleepers sleep where they do:
safety, access to support,
walkable access to necessary resources, things
like a daily breakfast and things like that, as well as other
appointments.
Just talking about safety,
almost half of our homeless population are youth.
Almost half of our population of rough sleepers are women.
They're more vulnerable to
rape, abuse, theft, attack, and sleeping in well-lit public
areas is often chosen for safety purposes.
In response to that question of move on to where, I believe we are pushing our
whanau out into darker spaces, unknown spaces where
they're less safe.
That also impedes access to support services.
Some of that is, like say, walkability to breakfast,
to WINZ, et cetera.
Some of that actually, as key workers, we are aware of where our
street whanau hang out. We know, I need to find this person.
Often our street whanau find it hard to hold onto a phone, and so it
can be difficult to contact. So when we need to tell someone we have access
to a house for them or an important appointment, we know where to find them.
We know where they usually stay. They talk to each other.
We're able to walk around the city and go, "Hey, we actually have an opportunity
for a house for you." And we can do that because we've realized where
they are. By moving them on every 24 hours,
we lose that connection. Someone's in the bushes.
They don't have a phone. We have no way of contacting them.
It's harder to do outreach and to do our jobs that we're
contracted for
to support our whanau.
And I also just want to talk to, I think the
cruelty of what I see in the bill.
As others have stated, it doesn't solve the issue of homelessness.
It feels purely punitive in that way.
The government has already cut access to emergency housing significantly since
2024. They've recently claimed that they have not abolished
emergency housing, but effectively, as a key worker working with our most
vulnerable whanau, that is what we're seeing.
Someone who does not have a place to sleep tonight in Auckland has nowhere to go.
No night shelters, no access to emergency housing.
There is nowhere else for them to be.
So yeah, in my view,
to then criminalize rough sleeping is a cruel act or a
punitive act.
Thanks.
Thank you, Gemma. I will just look to see if any members have a question for you.
Doesn't appear to be the case. We're really appreciative of your written submission
and presenting to us this morning, so thank you.
Chair, thanks.
Okay, our next submitter is going to be Donna Cormack.
Donna, thank you very much for joining us this morning. We can see you.
That's fantastic. We've read your submission.
We've got you down for five minutes if you can just leave some time at the end for
questions.
So kia ora, tena koutou he uri tensei, no Kai Tahu, no Kati Mamoe.
I'm an associate professor at the Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences at the
University of Auckland, and my research and teaching focuses on the impacts
of racism, colonialism, and other forms of oppression on health.
And I want to just say, I understand that the
submission has been read by the committee and to say clearly at the outset that
I do not support the bill and strongly recommend it doesn't
progress any further.
It proposes substantial expansion of police powers through the creation of new
categories of offense and the criminalization of people's lived realities and
daily lives. It's part of a broader expansion project
being undertaken in New Zealand to
intensify the carceral state. We can see the
evidence of that over the last years in the increased investment in police
numbers and building of prisons, and numerous pieces of legislation that are
designed to criminalize and imprison more people and for longer periods of
time. This current approach is completely counter to what
we know works from public health research and theory.
It's completely misaligned with what is supported from a public health approach.
As an example, the American Public Health Association has made clear and strong
recommendations, quote, "Towards the abolition of carceral
systems and building in their stead just and equitable structures to advance
the public's health." End quote. As part of this, they recommend
that we need to divest from all carceral systems and invest
instead in the social determinants of health and commit to
non-carceral measures for accountability, safety, and wellbeing.
So from a public health and human rights standpoint, our approach should be the
opposite of what we are doing. It must be to rapidly reduce carceral
systems and move towards the abolition of prisons and all forms of policing
entirely. Investment should be redirected to making sure that
everyone, all communities, have what they need to be well and stay well,
not criminalizing and punishing peoples for conditions that are created and
sustained by racial capitalism.
I've been a scholar of race and racism for many years.
I understand racism is foundational to all systems of policing under settler
colonialism here and elsewhere. Racism is embedded in the history
and prison of policing and prisons in New Zealand.
This is clear in how they were established, whose interests they serve,
and who continues to experience the significant violence and harm of these
systems.
As such, this bill is a clear and further expression of state violence and state
racism. It deploys the same tactics that have been used since the
establishment of police in New Zealand to criminalize and punish people
in the interests of the state and of capital.
The use of vague words and criteria such as disruptive or
indicating an intent to inhabit are
purposeful. They allow the police to exercise racially
discriminatory discretion in the service of the state, a
pattern that is well documented and well established in New
Zealand. Any further expansion of policing can only
deepen racism. There is no policing in New Zealand under settler colonialism
that exists outside of racism.
As such, a commitment to the full recognition of everyone's right to health,
to our international obligations, and to everyone's humanity
requires an urgent disinvestment in carceral systems that further
entrench racialized state violence, and this includes
defunding the police. We need instead to redirect our resources,
energy, and attention to the institutions, practices, and systems
that support communities to flourish, that provide all peoples with what they
need, and that are grounded in aroha in the tikanga of this place.
Kia ora.
Thank you, Donna. We've got a question from Rima Nakley.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. Thank you, Dr. Donna.
So you've mentioned, I presume it's a very
academic term, carceral systems. What is that?
So carceral, there's a lot of definitions of carceral, but carceral is
really a way that we talk about a sort of set of beliefs or an
ideology that when
things happen that are seen to be not desirable or not
normal, that the response is punishment or incapacitation
or excluding people. So a carceral response is one
that responds to an issue with a punishment
mindset, like a punitive approach, rather than responding
perhaps with care or love or support,
rehabilitation.
So a lot of our responses to things like issues with housing,
with drugs, a lot of the responses we have in the health system in New Zealand are
what would be called carceral responses rather than kind of a
wellbeing or a
social determinants response. So punishing people for the conditions that have been
created structurally.
So is there any time, Mr. Chair, for a second-
Yeah, follow-up. You've got one follow-up question.
So when you said the abolition of carceral systems
as in all type of punishment, basically, to abolish,
even for murderers?
Sorry?
Even for murderers.
Yeah. So punishment is only one way in which you can hold people accountable
or have consequences. So it's not
saying that there is not a response that is needed when harm is
caused, because harm is caused. It's saying that the
overwhelming response that we have, particularly for health issues, but not
just for health issues, is one that is
more about punishing people, a revenge type approach, rather than one that
is concerned with changing the conditions that people live in that mean
that the harm is not going to happen in the first place and is unlikely to
reoccur.
Thank you-
Carceral systems have no evidence of preventing harm.
Thank you, Donna. Thank you very much for your submission and for joining us this
morning as well.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Member Shawnee has indicated that they are no longer interested to make an oral
submission to the committee. I will just check with the clerks to see if
Francesca is online and ready to
go.
No Francesca. Sorry, Mr. Chair.
Okay, members, we will suspend for five minutes till 11:20.
Okay, members, welcome back. We have got Francesca online now, which is
fantastic. So we will just promote Francesca.
Thanks for joining us this morning. We've read your submission.
We've got you down for-
Mm-hmm
... five minutes, and if you can just leave a little bit of time at the end for
some questions. Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you so much.
Well, kia ora.
I currently work as a public servant.
I spent many years volunteering alongside people experiencing homelessness, and I
lived through many of the realities this bill seeks to address through state care.
For these reasons, I strongly oppose the Summary Offences Amendment Bill.
To me, this bill reflects a fundamental misunderstanding of where responsibility
lies. By the time that someone is already experiencing homelessness, they
have usually been failed by multiple systems.
They have fallen through gaps in housing, mental health services, addiction
treatment, child protection, healthcare, and income support.
Homelessness is not the failure, it is the outcome of those failures.
Yet instead of fixing those systems, this bill shifts the burden onto the people
who have been failed by them. We cannot continue to expecting police to solve
problems that belong to the health system, the housing system, and the social
welfare system. It's not fair on police, and it certainly is not fair on the people
this bill targets. Moving someone on does not mean that they suddenly have a
home. It does not mean that they receive treatment.
It does not mean that they are safer.
It simply means that they become someone else's problem somewhere else.
That is not a policy solution, it is displacement.
What concerns me the most is that this bill mistakes visibility for harm.
If fewer homeless people are visible in our town centers, homelessness is not being
reduced, it's simply being hidden.
We should not mistake making poverty less visible for making New Zealand better.
The government's own advice reflects these concerns.
The Attorney General has found that aspects of this bill appear inconsistent with
the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act, while government agencies have advised that
there is little evidence that move on powers reduce homelessness or improve public
safety.
If Parliament genuinely wants to make safer communities, then we need stronger
systems, not stronger powers. We need more affordable housing, better mental health
support and addiction services, earlier intervention, and greater investment in the
supports that stop people reaching crisis in the first place.
Ultimately, the measure of good government is not how effectively it moves
vulnerable people out of public spaces.
It is how effectively it prevents them from ending up there at all.
For those reasons, I respectfully ask the committee to recommend that the bill be
withdrawn in its entirety.
Thank
you, Francesca, really appreciate your submission.
I'll just see if any members have a question for you.
Does not appear to be the case. Really appreciate your written submission and for
presenting to us today, so thank you.
Thank you. Thank you for taking the time to listen. Really appreciate it.
Have a good rest of the day. Thank you.
You too. Thank you.
Okay. We are going to go to our next submitter, which is from the Royal Australian
and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists.
Good morning. Thank you very much for joining us this morning.
We have read your submission. We have you down for 10 minutes, and if you can just
leave some time at the end for questions.
Morning.
I am here as part of the Tū Te Ākahakā Rua,
New Zealand National Committee of
Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists.
I just want to seek some apologies, as I understand that our
deputy chair of National Committee, Alison Masters, is also joining, and so is our
policy advisor. So if they're actually on the line, I would ask that they also join
as well. But I am certainly happy to start while we're waiting for them.
Just want to acknowledge first that the opportunity to talk on this issue,
in essence, our college strongly oppose this bill, and we ask you to
vote down this bill. The question for us really is
that this bill is asking- Um,
or leaving the question of moving on and moving on to where.
Look, I just see that Alison has joined me.
I do ask, Alison, I understand that we...
Oh, sorry, she just dropped off. I'll continue on
while she rejoins.
The point that I want to highlight is our concern around
criminalization of this behavior, and the fact that this bill reaches
right down to our rangatahi as young as 14 years
old.
We know that the early contact with the justice
system
leads to higher rates of hospitalization for our mental health and reduced
school attendance.
We know that this also increases likelihood of future justice
involvement, and this
leads to a poor outcome that is well often
documented in the research.
Another aspect for us that's most concerning is the fact that this
seems to be a solution that is being suggested as
part of a in response to a very complex problem with complex needs.
I want to ask if Alison, if you can speak to
this. I might just hand the mic over back to you so that you can
continue on.
Hello.
Sorry.
Is that better?
Sorry, Alison. It's very echoey at the moment, unfortunately.
So I've had to mute my
speaker.
But I will talk. So yeah, I just wanted to outline what
Aram has already talked to.
Yep, go ahead.
Aram, I think it might be in the best interests that you carry on with the
submission, please.
Thank you. Look, I will open it up certainly for Alison to join
in later, potentially for the later part of the presentation then.
So for us, I think the key aspect is that this response that's
required in regard to homelessness, um, and
people who may be affected by this bill, is that we need to
look at collaborative response to complex needs.
We know that people with mental health and addiction issues are
over-represented in this population, although does not explain the whole
of the homelessness. Certainly, they
come from various backgrounds with various needs, and there's
social, psychological, with trauma, and other background as
well, neurodivergence being also a big aspect of this,
knowing that they're over-represented in this population.
So the approach that we suggest that will be much more worthwhile and much
more helpful to approach is to look at examples
of co-response team, for example, where we're responding to
accomplice by inter-agency support and partnership,
and that has been helpful in meeting the needs of people
where they are presenting with distress as well.
I'm mindful that
the care options for those with serious mental
illness and additional layer of homelessness are
very limited, and that is showing across our
inpatient care settings and other settings where we are meeting them and needing to
provide service. And this is now spilling over into the
streets within the homelessness as well.
So what we suggest is that what we need is a sustained
investment and improvement in meeting those people with
complex needs,
including homelessness. And what we need is a
joined up inter-agency collaborative approach to meet the
complex needs of the people.
Thank you.
Thanks, Aram. We've got a question from Dan Rosewarm.
Yeah. Hey, thanks, Chair. And hey, thanks for that submission.
It's a strong one, so I appreciate that.
You highlight that for many people sleeping rough, the street is
not a behavioral choice, but the safer of two
unsafe options. And I was just wondering if you could explain what that
means in practice, and what risks Parliament should
consider before empowering police to move those people on.
Thank you. Just to note that Alison's now popping onto the mic.
So Alison, do you want to give it a try with your microphone and see
whether you want to respond to this?
We can't hear you, Alison.
Oh, okay. Alison, we're having difficulty hearing you.
So I'll start by responding first. Thank you so much for that question.
Look, what we know is that there is actually complex needs there.
For a lot of people, they have
landed into homelessness because they have not been able to find that safe space.
This could be someone experiencing domestic violence
as well as alcohol or drug issues or neurodivergence.
It could be young persons coming from, again, a place where there's a lot of
challenge at home and unable to find a safe place.
So one aspect, obviously, is health response, whereby we need sustained improvement
and investment to develop those places that are not only safe, but be able to
provide appropriate care that responds to the
corresponding need of the person that are in front of us.
At the moment, that obviously is very much in short supply. So that's one aspect.
But we also know a lot of people who are homeless also not just have
mental health issues, but there's complex trauma issues that are intergenerational,
for example. So again, those people, some of those needs wouldn't be necessarily
health response. It'll be social agency, NGO responses as well.
So there's probably no one-size-fits-all solution there, but what we
need is that this is actually a response that requires
inter-agency or cross-sector response.
Thank you.
Still can't hear Alison. I'll just see if any other members have questions.
Oh, God.
Alison, I think we can hear you possibly. Do you want to give it a go?
Oh, you can hear me now?
Yep.
We can.
Oh, cool.
We've got a couple of
minutes left.
Yeah. I keep having problems, I think.
I might have missed, Aaron, but we also wanted to talk to
solutions like the co-response teams that are becoming funded across
New Zealand. So this is a collaborative response to people
with complex issues that are being funded,
and they allow access, including
situations such as on the street, particularly when there's been a call-out to the
police for a response. They attend
together with a mental health clinician, and it allows that
in the moment on-site processing,
assessment, decision-making shared between our
agencies.
And we believe it does lead to a reduction in criminalized behavior.
We know from the initial trial of the co-response team in Wellington
that presentations to ED
did increase rather than people being detained and held
by the police.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Alison, and thank you, Aaron, for joining us both this
morning and for your written submission as well.
Really appreciate having you both here with us. So thank you.
Thank you.
All right. The Children's Rights Alliance Aotearoa is up next to
present to us, and we have both Dr. Rob Thompson
and Dr. Sarah, who are both going to be with us,
hopefully coming online.
Kia ora.
There we are. Can see you, Sarah, can see you, Rob. Fantastic.
Thank you for joining us.
Kia ora.
We have you down for 10 minutes. We've read your submission.
Just leave some time at the end for questions.
Ngā mihi. Tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou katoa.
My name is Sarah Tione. I'm the acting co-chair of the Child
Rights Alliance, Children's Rights Alliance.
I have a background as a kindergarten teacher, early childhood teacher,
and as a researcher.
And I'll hand over to Rob for a brief introduction.
Kia ora koutou. Rob Thompson taku ingoa.
He wati pati taka kāinga.
I'm here representing Family For Every Child, which is a global
alliance of civil service organizations, NGOs
around the
world,
contributing to child welfare.
Kia ora. So thank you for allowing us this opportunity to present, and
thank you also for reading our submission.
As you will have read, the Children's Rights Alliance is a civil society
coalition committed to promoting and advancing children's
rights in Aotearoa, New Zealand. Our vision is
an Aotearoa, New Zealand that actively respects and
realizes the rights of all children.
The other element about our aspect to our organization is that we are
the country focal point under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the
Child, and we provide the alternative parallel report to the
government's reports on how well we are upholding children's rights
using that convention as a basis.
We oppose the Amendment Bill and recommend that it be rejected.
We're concerned that it's inconsistent with Te Tiriti o Waitangi, the New Zealand
Bill of Rights, the Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
and the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child.
As we've said before, the New Zealand governments are obligated
to uphold the Convention on the Rights of the Child.
The principal articles of the convention expect children's best interests
to be taken into account,
to be non-discriminatory, to support survival and development, and to
consider children's views on all matters that affect them.
We're concerned that children's views did not inform this bill.
We're equally concerned that consideration of the other principal rights are not
apparent in the bill.
The convention covers children up to 18 years of age.
We're also concerned that the move on orders apply to children as young as
14 years old, and more than that, potentially
criminalizes them for having nowhere to go.
As well as upholding the Convention on the Rights of the Child, there's an
expectation that governments take on board the advice of the UN Committee on
the Rights of the Child.
These reports provide recommendations for legislation, policy,
budgeting, and programs that position children and their rights at the center.
Based on the 2023 recommendations, excuse me,
a growing body of local research and our on-the-ground
experience, we call for the mandatory use of child
impact assessments to analyze all proposed policy
developments that could significantly impact the rights of children,
and the unique status of Mokopuna Maori is taken into
account.
The move on orders are one such example of where and how the
MSD's Child Impact Assessment tool should be applied.
Homelessness and its negative impact on children, children's
health and wellbeing cannot be ignored when talking about this bill.
All children have a right to an adequate standard of living, a right
clearly not ratified as the latest Child Poverty Action reports released
yesterday outlined.
The United Nations Special Rapporteur on the Rights to Housing
came to New Zealand in 2020 and recommended the development of a human
rights-based housing strategy to specifically address
the impact of severe housing deprivation on
the health and wellbeing of children by prioritizing children's
stable access to adequate housing.
As far as we can see, this bill does not consider the
recommendations of both the UN Committee on the Rights of the Child or the
Special Rapporteur on the Rights to Housing. Thank you.
I'll now hand to Rob
Oh, kia ora, Sarah. So in addition to my role with Family For
Every Child, I've also been a trustee for the Dunedin Night
Shelter, and I currently do a lot of work with tamariki
tahi in state care.
And I think it's important to recognize and actually ask who we're talking
about here. And I don't know any of you very well,
but I assume that you have somewhere to sleep tonight, and you're going to
have something for dinner.
But consider you lose your job for no fault of your own,
maybe in November.
Or consider you've had a relationship breakdown or ill health,
or you've been ripped off by somebody.
These are normal life events, and most of us could deal with one or two.
Probably, to be honest, people in this call could deal with three
or four.
However, if you have five or six
normal everyday life events, you could find yourself
on the street with nowhere to go. So the people we're talking about are
people like us, who have suffered more
negative life events than most of us.
And we're talking about our children
that are on the street. So this bill gives broad
power to police to move on with no independent oversight, no right of
appeal, and no requirement to consider the best interest of our people
who are most in need of care.
It requires somewhere to move on to.
It'll criminalize people who have no money, no housing, and nowhere safe to
sleep. And we know in the last census,
this is over 112,000 people, and we know that it is much
more now.
Many of these are women, many of these are with young children, and move on
orders will push families into unsafe hidden locations, increase
risk to children, and sever connections with
whanau.
It's going to harm children and young people as we know they experience
homelessness at higher rates than any other age groups.
I talk to tamariki. I talk to rangatahi
in state care who find themselves on the streets.
Emergency or transitional housing is often inaccessible for them
because of their age. And what we're doing is creating a new offense
for failing to comply with the move on order that just introduce another pathway
into the justice system,
making it harder for young people to secure housing, employment, and
support in the future. We know it's going to have a greater effect on Maori,
Maori tamariki, rangatahi, and whanau, as Maori make up more than
half of the people experiencing homelessness.
If we want our children to thrive, we must support families and whanau, not
criminalize people who have nowhere to go.
When I talk to my international colleagues, I'm embarrassed to be from New
Zealand because of the way that we treat our families and
children in this country. We need to shift focus to
solutions and put children and their families at the center of policy decision
and decision-making. Kia ora koutou.
Fantastic. Thank you, Rob and Sarah.
I'll just see if there are any members that have questions for you.
Dan Rosewarne.
Yeah. Hey, I appreciate the context that you provided, particularly
around the five or six life events is all it takes for anyone to find
themselves in a rough sleeping situation.
It's an important aspect that we as a committee need to be mindful, so thanks for
that.
So for my question, in particular, the bill creates
powers to move on a 14-year-old who is sleeping rough.
If that person has nowhere safe to go, what outcome
does your organization believe the bill would actually achieve for that
child?
Do you want to hit that, Robs?
Well, they don't have anywhere to go,
so they will go into police custody,
and then they will end up in potentially a YJ.
They will end up in a kids' prison and ultimately end up in adults'
prisons. That is the trajectory.
Thank you. I appreciate that.
Fantastic. Doesn't look like we have questions from anybody else, so thank you very
much, Sarah and Rob, for joining us this morning and for your written submission as
well.
Kia ora koutou.
Thank you, Tom.
Thank you.
Okay, we're up to
Jenny. Jenny Campbell.
Good morning, Jenny. Thank you very much for joining us this morning.
We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, and if you can just leave some time at the end
for questions.
Kia ora koutou.
Just bring my notes up.
Kia ora hoa ma. He iti hē pounamu, it may be small, but it
is very precious. Ko Reti toku awa.
Ko Takitimu toku maunga. Ko Takitimu toku waka.
Ko Ngai Tahu toku iwi. Ko Te Rau Araha toku marae nō
Mossburn toku kāinga. Ko Jenny Campbell ahau.
I'm speaking as co-convener of Coal Action Murihiku along with
Personal Perspectives. He waka eke noa, we are all in
this together. We as CANA members are totally
opposed to passing this proposed Summary Offences
Amendment Bill
for the following reasons.
CANA members feel this proposed bill is heartless, lacks a moral
compass, and is an indictment on our first world society and relative
affluence that we have come to this.
It is not our value system or our philosophy in Aotearoa
to be introducing this bill with these harmful implications and
impacts on other human beings.
They are people first. Our values demand they deserve
respect and help
We are very concerned that this bill does not honor Te Tiriti or
Waitangi principles.
This is a massive
absence
in the bill and shows a lack of consultation with mana
whenua. We are obviously not meeting people's needs and
finding out why they are in this situation in the first place.
Listening to their stories, being compassionate, and ensuring they have their basic
human rights met is essential. These include warm and
safe shelter, water, food, clothes, hygiene
facilities, basic health needs met, and social interaction.
All of these are essential in order that they can not just exist, but
also thrive.
There needs to be compassion by this government and adequate resources
made more available for the social services and compassionate groups
like the Salvation Army, Anglican care groups, and other community
groups to be able to provide decent and life-giving services to people
in these situations. In many cases, through no fault
of their own.
We understand
many of these people are coping with mental health issues, which makes them very
vulnerable and subject to abuse on the streets.
Specialized services and living conditions are essential for them to
gain and retain wellness. I have worked in mental health
and know of the situation on a personal basis.
This is traumatizing for everyone concerned.
We consider the term rough sleepers as a derogatory
term. They are people struggling to survive.
All of these people in government and in our nation must have a
compassionate heart for the people who have ended up in this situation.
It is heartbreaking.
Moving on does not solve the problem.
We need to look at the root cause of why they are in this situation.
Moving on transfers the problem to another town or
suburb with even less resources there than in a central
city situation.
We ask you to imagine how you would cope in a situation like this.
No whanau, no resources, no money, no
warmth and shelter, particularly
in our winter conditions at present.
We particularly feel for the young people who come under this bill.
That is between 14 to 18 years. This bill
empowers police to issue 24-hour move-on orders to
anyone 14 or older found rough sleeping, begging, or
showing intent to inhabit public spaces.
This is a special social concern for these young, vulnerable
people who do not have a home or a place to be under permanent
shelter, which is safe, warm, has sleeping facilities
to be stable, have hygiene facilities, clean water, a place to
cook, and have access to human contact and
chances to socialize. This bill also breaks down the
role of police, making it more antagonistic and not seen
as a helping agency, which is how we in society
expect them to be.
In fact, all these people of all ages need respect as well,
compassion, human intervention, and someone to listen to their story
so their support can be appropriate and humane.
Punishment. Refusing to comply
risks a fine of up to $2,000 or three months in prison.
This is absurd.
Fining someone $2,000 for not having a home is totally
ludicrous.
If they have that kind of money, they could rent a flat for shelter.
Putting them in prison at least gives them a warm place, regular food,
hygiene facilities, but it also gives them a prison record,
which will not improve their chances when they leave prison after three
months.
Twenty-four-hour move-on order is just that.
Moving them to another doorway, street, suburb, park.
It does not meet their needs, change their situation, or provide their
basic needs for a home, shelter. They are stranded in their
misery, and it seems no one cares, which is true for them.
This is heartless, and we know this.
There is no requirement in this bill to actually find these people
accommodation. It is just simply moving them
along.
Where am I up to? Out of sight, out of mind.
We recognize it risks criminalizing homelessness and
poverty while doing little to address the underlying causes.
This is where we need to start to address this issue as a
society. This government has made a deliberate decision to
block people in need from entering emergency housing.
That has led
to the
highest level of homelessness we have ever seen, and there is
little help being offered to solve this problem.
This is shameful. The government must make
more social housing and services available to offer relief in the
meantime.
We had a situation in Lumsden, close to Mosbourne, where I live in Southland
recently, with a man of about 50 years found sleeping under the
veranda of our abandoned squash club rooms.
He had a thin, very wet sleeping bag, no money, no
food, no transport. He was forsaken.
It was about the time we had snow on the ground and freezing temperatures
overnight.
Thankfully, our community worker had compassion when she was alerted to his
situation. She booked him into the local motel for the night to have
a shower, get warm, dry his sleeping bags, and
locals gave him things like blankets, coffee, a meal, and
other basic needs. After speaking to the local police, they took him
to Invercargill. What would happen then?
With no money, no fixed address to be able to get a benefit, no
night shelter or emergency housing, no food, no
friends or whanau I wonder what resources the police could
find. What then for this poor man?
No other options but to live on the streets.
Is this what we really want for our people, our country?
Can members all agree that this bill is not fit for purpose and should be
totally withdrawn?
As a consequence, the government must use that money alongside
more government funds to improve the resources, for example, emergency
housing, listening to their needs, and build suitable long-term
housing to accommodate them. Our recommendation,
withdraw this bill in its entirety.
Kia ora koutou, thank you for the chance to speak.
Great. Thank you, Jenny. We've got a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Thanks, Chair. And hey, thanks, Jenny.
In paragraph eight of your submission, you make the point that
somebody experiencing homelessness is unlikely to
be able to pay a $2,000 fine. What
consequences do you think flow from imposing financial
penalties in those situations?
Well, it makes them much more vulnerable.
If they are actually helped to get into a housing situation,
because that follows with them.
They haven't been able to show any evidence of where they've
actually kept paying the rent. All those consequences
of being homeless leads into all the other issues,
like trying to get a job. Where's your place of residence?
What's your phone number? All of those things, it's just
condemning them to disaster and to being on
our streets longer, not less.
Thanks, Jenny.
It's common sense.
As we fully know. Yes.
We've got one final question from Dr. Lawrence Sunan.
Kia ora. Thank you, Jenny, and apologies for my-
Kia ora, Lawrence
... at the beginning.
Yeah, also just supplementary to what Dan
was asking before,
one of the questions we have been asking submitters is
where
does this act move people on to?
In your region,
what do you think would be some of the consequences of people being moved
on?
Well, it's very cold, as people know, in Southland, particularly in
the winter. There used to be the Salvation
Army with the large hostel, but it doesn't exist anymore.
Those are the places that we had, and people just cannot sustain
a place like that on
charity. We're relying on society as a charity to help these
people out of their situation. It's just not enough.
It's just an overburden for people in society, and we know what's
happening. We know what's needed.
The government has to step in and help these people.
As that previous speaker said, I'm
ashamed to see this happening in our first world country when we
have very rich people here, a government that can make
commitments to help these people and not to see them as
outcasts in society.
Thank you, Jenny. Really appreciate you presenting to us this morning, and for your
written submission as well. So thank you.
Kia ora, and thank you for the chance to talk. Ka kite.
Okay. Now we've got the Maori Women's Welfare League, and we've got Hope who's
going to be presenting to us.
Hi, Hope. Thank you very much for joining us this morning.
We've read your submission. We have you down for 10 minutes, and just leave some
time at the end for questions.
Okay.
I'll just take my submission as read.
What I want to talk about is
when this government came in, I actually met with the Minister of
Housing,
and I also met with the Minister of Housing with the previous government and asked
them one question, "What is our housing strategy?"
And both of them gave me the same answer.
Oh, that they didn't have a strategy, and it depends what
information you read.
And that doesn't swallow with me because the government
gets access to a lot of information about what the population is
that we have here, who's coming and going.
Nobody else really has that information.
So I think a housing strategy, the problem that we don't have one,
underlies why we have a homeless problem today.
And I think that what we really need is governments
to actually have a housing strategy so that we can get on top
of what's the problem that everyone's been talking to you about.
Because that's what's underpinning homelessness in our country right
now. We haven't had this problem like we have
it today.
The other issue, I think, is that the solution that we need
is not a penal solution like this act or this
bill is going to do. We need actually real
solutions and get the communities together, and we need an agency
that's going to take a lead on it.
We've got the Social Investment Agency.
I don't really know if that fits within their portfolio.
Or we've got another model of the Justice Sector Directorate.
I
don't know if that's still working, but you had all chief executives coming
together.
That's fine at a high level, but usually those kinds of things
don't work on the ground because we don't get the ripple effect of the
intent of what that's trying to do down in the
community end. And so what I
challenge you to do is to think about the importance
of bringing together groups in the communities
rather than just being inward-looking.
But we need an agency who has got some
Leveraging with across other agencies to be able to support
community groups on the ground. Because
I live in Levin, but I go to Wellington very often, and I've been in Courtney
Place, where sometimes I've felt a little unsafe.
But actually, I've got a bit of medical background because I was a midwife for a
very long time. So what might look like somebody is drunk
could actually be somebody who's going into a diabetic
state or have mental health problems.
And I've been in other places, like in Lambton Quay,
where I've seen the best of compassion, where people are walking
past and helping someone who also looks like they might be a little
bit on drugs or something. But actually, the situation I saw
very recently was a woman being helped by another
man, a complete stranger across the street.
Now,
I just really
implore you,
can we please look for some solutions that are not going to put people
in jail, not going to give them a fine?
Something where we can actually put them into housing and give them the kind of
support they need.
The league has experience of working with agencies.
In the main part, the agencies and the public servants that work with us
want to try and do a good job. They
usually got limitations around them.
But
sometimes, well, actually, the majority of times,
usually the agencies are looking inward and not really looking at the
community groups where they should be looking to.
You've got hapū and iwi. Usually,
people just go to them when they need the marae for a
massive climate event. I'm just saying to you, there's
communities out there, including ours, which are being overlooked
to help with situations. And there are plenty of groups.
A lot of them have talked to you
and given submissions. And it's the communities
that can give you the answers, not just the government.
The government's just coming over, and this is just--
I'm not going to repeat because everybody's already said it, but you know the
position of the Māori Women's Welfare League.
That's all I really want to say today.
But I'm just saying to you, there's better options
than what's being put in this bill.
That's-
Thank you, Hope. We've got a couple of questions from members.
We'll start with Rima Nakley.
Kia ora, Dr Hope.
Just a clarification, if I may. You did say that
the current government doesn't have a housing
strategy, but
just wondering if you were aware that we do have a government policy statement
on housing and urban development, and that's a framework that
includes housing supply, social housing, planning, et cetera.
Sorry, doctor. That was released in 2025,
which replaced the 2021 one. So just wondering if-
Did you think it's working?
Well, it's a whole framework. And part of-
But is it working is my question.
There's a lot of work to do. But part of-- as you would know,
there's
a focus as well as allowing more papakāinga to be built in
a more easier way. There is a focus-
But the move on orders are mainly being applied into some of our cities, isn't it,
rather than papakāinga. In papakāinga, you're talking about mainly in
rural areas. But the move on orders are really
attacking so people are not visible anymore. Is that correct?
Not necessarily attacking,
doctor. With papakāinga, it's one of the things that's available
as what we're doing because you were saying there's no strategy.
But with the move on orders, it's 24 hours.
It's a response to as well people that have families, that are running
businesses, that are saying, "This is causing a problem for us as well
to pay our mortgage and send our kids to school." So it's
a whole approach. It doesn't deny the fact that there's issues for our
homeless people. That as well, we've got a minister for mental health.
He's doing a lot in that area as well.
Can you answer me a question there?
Where can I find that information about the number of complaints you've had from
business owners?
I don't have the number
here, but I know what I hear in South Auckland as a local community-
Yeah, I don't want to hear anecdote. I want to know what's your evidence.
Anecdote's evidence for me.
To be-- And I'm not undermining or trying to minimize what
business owners are saying to you, but I'm hearing a lot from this
government about somebody said, and I really am interested in the
evidence that underpins the decision to have this bill.
Fair enough, doctor. We've spoken to a lot of people that run
businesses that have families.
Yeah. It'd be good to see where the information is, though. Kia ora.
We'll go to a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Kia ora, Dan.
Yeah. Thanks for that submission.
You highlighted in the submission that some people remain in
busy public places because they feel safer there.
What do you think could happen if those people are moved away
from places where they are visible into areas where
fewer people can see them?
I think there's a
bigger chance of them being exposed to
violence or abuse. That's why I think they place themselves
there,
is because they are lit up streets. There's people walking by.
They're visible.
If they have to start to move, which street are they going to move to
if they have to move from that street they're in?
They're homeless, full stop. So if they have to
move, then whose street do we want them to move into?
Or do we want them to go off streets and
somewhere else? That's what
is a big concern because we do have a lot of women.
We work closely with Women's Refuge, who are also seeing a lot of
homeless who are not just women, but elderly
Kia ora. Thank you.
Thank you, Hope. Really appreciate you joining us this morning.
Thank you.
And thank you for your written submission.
Okay, we're going to come to the Wellington Community Justice Project, Howard
League submissions team, with Gemma and Mai.
Hey, Gemma. We can see you nice and clearly.
Mai's just coming online now.
And there you are as well. Fantastic. Thank you both for joining us this morning.
We've got you down for 10 minutes. We've read your submission, if you can just
leave some time at the end for questions.
Awesome. Kia ora. We are Mai Khalid and Gemma Benin,
law students, volunteers from the Wellington Community Justice Project,
specifically the Howard League submissions team, which advocates for penal
reform and criminal justice. While we are supported by the Howard League,
the opinions expressed in this submission are our own.
We are opposed to the Move on Orders Bill for the following reasons.
I will be addressing two issues. First, why we submit the move on
orders are inconsistent with fundamental rights and Te Tiriti
obligations. Secondly, why we submit they are likely to increase
incarceration while placing New Zealand at odds with its international
obligations.
Turning first to rights, our concern is that this bill
gives police broad discretion to issue a move on order where they
suspect someone has behaved in a disorderly or disruptive
manner. Those concepts are broad, subjective, and open
to inconsistent application. We submit that where
Parliament grants powers that interfere with fundamental rights, they must be
clearly defined, proportionate, and demonstrably justified.
These concerns are further reinforced when viewed through the lens of Te
Tiriti o Waitangi.
Maori continue to experience disproportionately high rates of homelessness and
severe housing deprivation. We are particularly concerned about
the impact on rangatahi, as the bill applies to young people aged 14
or over.
For a young person sleeping rough, a move on order does not resolve the
circumstances that brought them there.
Instead, it may require them to leave an area where they feel relatively safe
or risk breaching the order and entering the criminal justice system.
We submit that this disproportionate impact engages the Crown's obligations
of partnership and active protection under Te Tiriti.
And turning briefly to our second point, our written submission explains why
we are concerned that the bill will increase incarceration.
We would emphasize that this is not because the bill responds to conduct
that police currently cannot address.
Existing provisions under the Summary Offences Act already
provide police with powers to respond to genuinely threatening or disorderly
behavior. Instead, the bill creates a new offense for breaching a move on
order, carrying the possibility of imprisonment.
We therefore question whether this additional offense is either necessary or
proportionate. Finally, we submit that these concerns
extend beyond domestic law. New Zealand has
longstanding commitments under international human rights
instruments, including the International Covenant on Civil and
Political Rights. Those commitments reinforce the importance of protecting
freedom of movement, expression, and peaceful assembly while ensuring imprisonment
is used consistently with human dignity and only where justified.
Ultimately, we submit that the bill expands the reach of the criminal law without
addressing the circumstances that give rise to the conduct it seeks to regulate.
For those reasons, we respectfully ask the committee to recommend that the bill not
proceed. Ngā mihi nui. I will now pass on to Gemma.
Kia ora.
The second half of our submission, we're just going to talk about why we think
a better approach to the policy issue is social welfare.
But first, just using the Scottish Sentencing and Penal Policy Commission report
that was published in February, we'd like to highlight why criminalizing the issue
is a poor approach.
Scotland's like us. They have overcrowded prisons with staff stretched to their
limits, meaning that rehabilitative opportunities are limited and remand numbers
are on the rise. Considering this, their Justice Directorate recently found,
among other things, that having a high prison population does not
equate to a safer society, and that reconviction rates are actually higher for
those imprisoned for short sentences.
And finally, that general overcrowding reduces the effectiveness of rehabilitative
programs for people convicted of more serious offenses.
So, the point to draw from that is that if, as per kind order statistics,
6,000 Kiwis are without accommodation each night, then it's actually for the good
of all of us that those people first and foremost are provided a home and
do not go to prison. They need addiction treatment, they don't need to be arrested
when they mouth off to an officer who's asked them to move on.
And they do not need a criminal sentence, which not only stretches our criminal
justice system further, but is a much less efficient use of taxpayer money.
If the government is worried about people feeling safe, as noted by Mai, the police
already have powers to deal with public disorder.
Their comments on the earlier version of this bill did support increased powers to
deal with aggressive behavior specifically, but they expressly rejected the
idea of criminalizing homelessness.
As the government has chosen to ignore this, we argue therefore that the bill is
not about safety, but having an out of sight, out of mind approach to
people and giving them the right services and
operating the criminal justice system to achieve this.
In sum, we'd just like to point out that there are many ways in which Kiwis are
feeling unsafe at the moment, from people dying in ED waiting rooms to
unprecedented climate weather events.
We would argue that a child sleeping rough is not one of them.
Therefore, we implore the government to abandon this bill because we believe it
distracts from real issues, and it has caused so much controversy.
And finally, even the New Zealand Police have said that they do not support it, and
it will actually take away from police resourcing in other, more appropriate areas.
Ngā mihi nui. We thank the committee for their time, and we will now take
questions.
Thank you both for your submission.
We've got a question from Dan Rosewarms
Hey, thanks for that submission. It highlights that the
bill identifies a real problem but criminalizes
the symptom rather than addressing the cause.
And I suppose my question is, what do you see as the root causes of the
behavior that this bill is targeting, and how should
Parliament respond to those causes instead?
I'll just jump in if that's okay. I actually went to a book talk of Asher
Manuel's beautiful "The Valley" novel there last night, and
I think it's mandatory reading for absolutely everybody.
But that really identifies, I think, the main issues, which are
that housing, healthcare, education, these are all things that we know
prevent crime because they prevent poverty, because poverty is one of the main
drivers of criminal behavior. So I think, when we've seen an
underfunding of all those services in recent years, that it's no wonder that
there are more people on the streets.
And actually, if you want to target that issue, it's those social reforms that you
need to focus on rather than moving people into prison.
I don't know what Maia thinks about that.
Thank you, and thank you for your service, too.
Kia ora.
Thank you both for your time this afternoon.
Really appreciate you presenting to us and for your written submission as well.
Thank you.
Okay, our next submitter is going to be Kickback, and we're going to have
Aaron, who's going to be presenting to us.
Hey, Aaron, thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, if you can just leave some time at the end for
questions from members. Thank you.
Yeah. Kia ora. Aaron Hendry, te koro. Look, I'm the general manager of Kickback.
We are a youth development organization that is responding to youth homelessness.
We run the Front Door service, which is a crisis response early intervention
service for children and young people.
Right now, we're monitoring over 200 children and young people who are either
experiencing homelessness or at risk of homelessness.
Over 20% of those over the last three months that we've been supporting
have been children.
So that's under 16. So look, we really want to highlight that this bill is a piece
of legislation that directly impacts the children and young people we see every
day.
We're seeing an increase of children in terms of the context of what this bill
comes into. We're seeing an increase of children experiencing homelessness.
We're seeing an increase of young teenagers, 16, 17, who are sleeping rough.
We've had an increase, which is really unusual at this time of
season, within winter, for this demographic to have such a high
level of children, young people sleeping rough.
Over the last year, we've seen an increase of rough sleeping of young people in our
service at least of about 12% since last year.
It's really important to highlight that the levels of harm that we are
seeing for these kids,
significant mental health, mental illness, disability, addiction,
real clear physical illness, significant levels of trauma.
It's very distressing and alarming.
And this is the context that the move on orders are being introduced in the midst
of. Look, Kickback's view is that this
legislation, and the impact it will have,
is potentially significantly dangerous and potentially fatal to some of our most
vulnerable children and young people.
We're very concerned that the rhetoric surrounding the bill is
already having an impact, and young people in general
are getting viewed through a lens of antisocial behavior
rather than the appropriate lens of care and protection when they're turning up in
our city centers, clearly distressed and unwell,
and unsafe. And the impact of this already, and we
believe it will only increase,
is that children and young people are being criminalized, moved on, and mistreated
rather than receiving appropriate support and care.
And to highlight again that this is children and young people who, for no
fault of their own, are sleeping rough, who are unsafe, who are
significantly unwell, and are being put in harm's way as a
result of not receiving the support that they need to when adults,
sometimes public servants, are coming into contact with them in our city centers,
whether that is police, medical professionals, or security guards, or otherwise.
Another clear point, the bill's not going to achieve a safe outcome.
I think what
we need to name very clearly is the real problem we have here specifically around
homelessness and rough sleeping, is that people do not have safe places to live,
and that is why they're turning up in our city centers.
In terms of the outcome the government's been talking about, Kickback is currently
delivering that outcome. Say, for example, through being very clearly
connected to our communities, able to be responsive and to move fast, we are able
to support young people who are sleeping rough to access shelter within
ours. And I know many of my colleagues across the country and in the sector are
doing very similar brilliant work.
And our point to the government is, if you want to resolve that issue that you're
naming in this bill, then what you do is you start investing in what works, and you
scale that to ensure that we have the resources we need to be responsive.
And that's the other point. Look, the resources don't exist right now.
We don't have the resources or the social infrastructure you need to
operationalize this without risking significant harm to vulnerable
people. Outreach housing services are overloaded.
We have huge gaps in homelessness response services.
There's significant gaps in access to emergency housing and immediate housing.
Right now in Tamaki at least, there's only two youth-specific immediate housing
services in the city.
Only one of those is a kind of government-funded service.
The other one is a community-based service. So the gaps are there.
Mental health and disability services, they either don't exist or they're not fit
for purpose.
If you're going to proceed with this legislation, we recommend that you remove the
provisions for this to be applied to begging and rough sleeping.
You remove the provisions for this to be applied to young people 18 and under.
But to be very clear, Kickback does not believe that this bill
should be going ahead. We urge the government and the Select Committee to move on
the move on orders and kill the bill.
Instead, look, we ask that you start implementing and backing what really works.
Instead of moving forward with this bill, we'd call on the government to roll back
the emergency housing policy to ensure no one experiencing homelessness is subject
to sanctions. We're seeing a huge kind of harm that has been
caused as a result of that. We'd urge you to invest in outreach
services and integrated service centers. Services like the Front Door.
Kickback's the Front- Front door, Auckland City Mission's home ground.
Invest in public housing and kaupapa Maori housing solutions, and invest in duty to
assist legislation. This legislation, if it goes ahead,
it will create increased risk for some of our most vulnerable children and young
people. In the worst case scenario, that will be fatal.
And we all have, I believe, a duty of care to ensure that young
people and children are supported and cared for, and that we're investing in
solutions that work. Yeah, look, I'm happy to take questions.
Thanks, Aaron. Thank you for your submission. We've got a question from Dr.
Lawrence Nguyen.
Thank you, Chair. Sorry, there's just a little bit of feedback.
Kia ora, Aaron, thank you so much for the work that you do.
My question is
what perception, I guess, have people got
wrong about homeless whanau, particularly when it comes to homeless
youth? Because we do hear a lot of people just generally
being afraid of rough sleepers or people just begging or getting
along their day in a public space.
Yeah, look, in terms of perception, I guess there's a couple things.
One,
often it is our homeless whanau and our children and young people who are the first
victims on the street. They are at increased risk of harm and are often the
victims of assault and harm as a result of homelessness, right?
In some cases, we're talking about 14-year-olds who are sleeping rough in our city
centers because of unsafe environments that they are coming from, right?
So this is who we're discussing.
Perception that children and young people choose homelessness.
That is just not the case. Young people are making very
difficult decisions around how they're going to keep themselves safe
because they do not have the support that they need.
They are often there because of failure, collective failure from all of us to
ensure that we're resourcing the systems and services that they need.
They're slipping through the gaps, and they're ending up on our streets as a result
of that.
And a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Thanks, Aaron. Your submission mentions that in the best case
scenario, your team can move a young person from street to a
shelter within an hour. What effect would this bill
have on your ability to find those young people and connect them with the
support they need before a crisis escalates?
Yeah, look, what we're concerned about specifically is kind of the effect of
driving youth homelessness back further underground.
Right now when a young person ends up in the city center, there's a way for us to
consolidate our resources and move really fast.
There's a lot of eyes in the city center.
We work very collaboratively with MSD, with the library, with the police, the like.
And as soon as a young person is turning up, either they're coming here-- About 60%
of our young people walk through the doors themselves.
They're referred by their mates. The risk here is by driving more of our young
people out into the suburbs, further and further underground, they're going to be
at higher risk of harm, assault,
murder,
mental health kind of disintegration.
All of those things are going to be harder to access.
You're going to have to start thinking about resourcing outreach services far more
significantly than you are now, and I know that's already a challenge because we're
going to have to spread ourselves across the whole city, and Auckland's a really
big place.
Thanks, Aaron.
Fantastic. Thank you, Aaron, for joining us this afternoon.
Really appreciate your time and the submission you've made, too. So thank you.
Kia ora.
Okay, we now come to Kit.
Hello.
Hey, Kit. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We have read your submission. We have you down for five minutes, and if you can
just leave some time for questions, that would be great.
Okay.
I'd like to start off
by thanking the committee members for this opportunity to speak here today.
Thank you. And I'd like to start us off by asking for
a show of hands, if you feel comfortable, from all of you,
to please raise your hand if you have ever experienced homelessness, if you have
ever experienced rough sleeping, if you have ever
slept in a home under a roof that was not yours because your own
you were unable to return to. Please raise your hand.
Okay, thank you.
No one chooses to be homeless.
It is simply unfortunate circumstances that lead to
people on our streets,
that lead to people begging and rough sleeping.
This bill seeks to attack our most vulnerable.
It seeks to illegalize homelessness.
It is a human right to occupy the streets,
and people have no support.
I would like to tell you a story
of when I was 10 years old,
holding my mom's hand as we walked down Queen Street
to the WINZ office down there.
And after the third
meeting with this support worker,
I had broken down crying and had the entire office staring at me because I
was screaming.
I didn't want to be homeless.
It was then that this support worker finally softened and realized
the impact of what she had done, that
she had scared a child shitless,
that they thought they were going to end up sleeping on the
streets.
My mother did the best she could,
but she needed help.
Instead,
WINZ antagonized her for doing what was right for her
child.
We need to implement stuff like duty to assist, not implement this bill.
This bill helps no one.
If you do not provide
your biographical details,
if you provide false ones,
you get a $500 fine.
If you straight up refuse to provide them or violate
the
order that you've been given, the move on order,
you may face a $2,000 fine or
three months imprisonment.
A block of cheese is more than $10. The
average person cannot afford a $500 fine,
what leads me to my story from my friend
Simone. This happened 14 years ago.
She was walking down
Ponsonby Road,
and once a week she would see this homeless man
as she was going to her appointment, and she would chat with him
for a couple of minutes.
And every week she was somebody different, somebody new.
My favorite is that one time she was Princess Diana.
Usually, she was someone different, somebody famous,
somebody dead.
This man did not have the mental capacity to recognize
her as someone different,
as herself, sorry. He recognized her as someone different every time.
So I worry about people like this man who
are unable to provide their own biographical details and may
be fined
with a $500 fine, or worse, three months imprisonment.
This is inhumane.
This bill also,
it attacks people who are over the age of
14.
14, children. Can you imagine if this was your child?
Can you imagine if this was your child who was homeless, begging on the streets
because you had died or something had happened to you and no one was there to keep
them safe? I don't know a single person,
I don't know a single person who has had a positive experience with OT.
Single person.
So how can we possibly justify this bill?
Thank you.
Thank you, Kit, and thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
That's actually your full five minutes.
But I thank you very much for your submission to us this afternoon and for joining
us. So thank you.
Okay, members, we are going to hear from Jackson.
Mr. Chair, we don't have Jackson online, but we understand he is coming online.
I would recommend suspending until 12:25.
Yeah. I think we'll just wait. Maybe, members, if we just
wait a couple of minutes.
So maybe 12:23, if that's okay. We'll see if Jackson's come back online.
All
right. Kia ora.
My name is Jackson Duguid.
And-
Hey, Jackson, just give us a couple of moments.
Members are just coming back online in one minute.
So if you just hold fire, and then I'll
let you know when you're ready to go.
Perfect. Thank you.
All right, Jackson. We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for five minutes, and if you just leave a little bit of time at
the end for any questions members might have. But over to you.
Are you just on mute? You can go.
Yes. Perfect.
All right.
I think what I'd like to start off with is just that I completely
oppose this bill, and I think that everyone here should as well.
I think this bill should be abandoned, dropped entirely.
I don't think there's any changes to the
functionality of this bill. I don't think there's anything that you can do to it to
make it actually achieve any positive change for Aotearoa.
I think there's a couple key reasons for that.
The first is that this bill inherently holds the view
that homelessness is a problem that can be solved by making homeless people
go elsewhere. The idea of a move on order
seems to think that homelessness can be solved by just pushing it somewhere where
we can't see. And I think that is probably the biggest issue, is
that when you tell homeless people who are really struggling, who are out there
just trying to survive,
and you tell them, "Okay, well, you can't be here.
You have to go somewhere else," the idea that somewhere else is going to be
somewhere where the problem of homelessness
disappears
just doesn't make any sense. When you tell these homeless people to move
elsewhere, they're going to have to go somewhere else.
They're going to have to find somewhere where they can survive.
And that doesn't mean that they magically get to find a place to live.
The options are that they either accept
this, they move somewhere else, and then they try
to survive in other places, those places likely not as easy to survive
in than inner cities where there are places that people can stay under
rooftops or find people to give them some aid
or things like this. It's going to be areas where it's harder for them to survive.
So that's going to increase the risk of homeless people dying, which I think
Maybe not everyone agrees is a good thing, but I would say is something that we
need to focus on. These are people, these are people we should care about.
And I think the idea that we should just tell them to go somewhere else and
deal with the fact that they're really struggling to survive is a terrible thing.
The second option they have is to just get arrested.
And that's what I want to focus on a bit here, is the fact that this has been
pretty clearly
shown by a lot of experts in justice, a lot of experts
in homeless issues, to increase the rate of
people getting arrested for a crime that we've effectively made up by
criminalizing homelessness to an extent, criminalizing homelessness in areas that
we don't want homeless people to be.
And there's a lot of issues that come with that.
There's a lot of issues that come with making people who are really struggling to
get by, making people who are really just trying to live in our society,
and get back on the rung, get back into housing, get back into
work, all these things, giving them that criminal record, forcing them
into
the justice system when they've done nothing wrong, when all they've done is try to
survive in the best way they can.
The big issues that come with that are obviously the criminal record.
It's way harder to get a job, it's way harder to get employment, it's way harder to
get
housing when you have this criminal record.
It indicates in our society that you're a less desirable person,
that you're someone that we shouldn't give things to.
And it kind of justifies that person as being homeless in the eyes
of a lot of people, because criminals have done something to deserve it, when
all this person has done is be homeless and be struggling in
our communities. So,
the criminalizing of this, forcing people to have that criminal record,
is just going to create a far bigger barrier for homeless people
reentering our society. So if you, as the people writing this bill,
or if you, as the people looking to move this bill further into our
law, actually believe that homelessness is an issue that we should focus
on solving, the solution is not adding another barrier for homeless
people to access housing, to access jobs, to get
up into the rungs of society. Because this just means that less
people are going to be able to escape homelessness.
They're just going to end up with a criminal record.
They're going to end up in our justice system.
They're going to financially clog that justice system up more, something that we
all know is a struggle that we need to solve as well.
This just adds more issues to our broken system.
It makes it harder for people to pull themselves up by their bootstraps, if that's
how you want to word it. And I think it's a terrible thing for us
to put into our legal system. Thank you. Any questions?
Thanks, Jackson. We've got one question from Rima Nakli.
Hi, Jackson. Hey, Jackson. Look, thanks for your passion.
Can I just ask, you repeated that this will not solve
homelessness.
And I know this is kind of technical, but the explanatory note of the
bill doesn't say that it's aiming to solve homelessness.
It says that it's
part of the government's commitment to ensuring that the police have necessary
powers to maintain public order.
Just clarifying whether you were aware of that, that this bill isn't aiming to
solve the issue of homelessness. That comes with other
measures around mental health and social housing, et cetera.
Yes, I am aware of that. I just think that the idea that
telling homeless people to go somewhere else is going to maintain public order is
quite silly. I don't think that homeless people
disturb public order to the extent that this bill is claiming, and additionally,
I don't think that homeless people being in a different part of a city or a
different part of a suburb is going to make them any less of an issue,
if that's how you view them.
Thanks, Jackson. All good.
Yeah. And a little bit on top of that is if you
believe they're a public disorder and you want them off the streets, the best way
to do that would be to give them housing, to give them jobs, and forcing them into
a criminal system is not going to help with that. That will exacerbate the issue.
It's not sorting if they have-
Thank you very much. Thank you. Thank you, Jackson.
Really appreciate your submission this afternoon and for taking the time to be with
us. So thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Members, we will now be suspending for lunch until 1:00 p.m. We'll see you then.
All right. Good afternoon, members. Welcome back.
Hope you all had a nice lunch break.
We're back into our submissions for this afternoon.
We're starting with the Law Association of New Zealand, with Devon
and Ryan, please.
Hi, Devon.
Hi there.
There's Ryan.
Great to have you with us this afternoon. Thank you for your written submission.
We have read it. We have you down for 10 minutes.
If you can just leave a little bit of time at the end for questions. Over to you.
Sure. Excellent. Thank you again for having us.
I'm sure Ryan will be joining us shortly, if he hasn't already.
I represent the Law Association. Myself and Ryan are on the Criminal Law Committee.
We filed some detailed submissions, so I'll defer to those and just
highlight the main points. Put simply, the bill needs
adjustment. The Law Association doesn't support it in its current
form. We take no issue with its intent.
But the adjustments we suggest are required to ensure the right
balance is struck between enabling police to respond to disorderly
behavior without encroaching on basic human rights or
unfairly criminalizing what we would consider, and what we think many would
consider, non-criminal behavior.
As stated in our submissions, currently the bill risks punishing status and
circumstances rather than harmful conduct.
However, with some adjustment, that could be avoided The basis for our
opposition can be synthesized, I'd suggest, into three points,
and I will propose some solutions along the way.
The first point is to remove begging, rough
sleeping, and demonstrating an intent to inhabit a public space
from the behaviors justifying a move on order under Section
8A.
As we well know, Section 8A provides an officer the
ability to make such an order to persons over 14 years
old, provided they have reasonable grounds to suspect the person
is engaging in or is recently engaged in a number of behaviors, including
begging, rough sleeping, and essentially setting up camp to do
so.
So no issues taken with an officer issuing a move on order for behavior they
reasonably believe to be causing public disorder.
The issue, however, is that begging and rough sleeping, in our
submission, are not in themselves disorderly behaviors.
They do not undermine public order.
For that reason, they should be excluded from Section 8A.
The purpose of the bill is clearly stated to ensure police are
equipped to address public disorder and address the public sense of
safety, as well as supporting urban economies.
Begging and rough sleeping do not in themselves undermine any of those
things. Disorderly behavior is what upsets those things, so
that should be the focus of Section 8A.
I think, in his recent paper commenting on the bill, the Attorney General,
Chris Bishop, highlighted this very same point.
What's the solution then? We suggest excluding begging and rough
sleeping from Section 8A. In reality, begging and rough
sleeping, which an officer considers are
causing public disorder, would be caught by the provision anyway.
But by excluding them as specific behaviors, you would
avoid the risk that officers would issue the move on orders simply because
somebody is begging or rough sleeping.
If I can rephrase that, if somebody is
begging or d-- rough sleeping in a way that is causing public disorder or
is causing a problem in that way, then the officer could make the order
regardless of whether those
terms are included within Section 8A. That's the first point.
The second point concerns the threshold for which
an officer could make a move on order.
Specifically, we propose that the current
basis being reasonable grounds to suspect should be changed to
reasonable grounds to believe. The short point on this is
that effectively reasonable ground to suspect unduly
legitimizes speculation as a basis for the officer to issue a move on
order. If the wording was changed to belief in
practice, our view is that it would impose upon the officer a little bit more of
a rigorous analysis as to why the order is being
given,
which would, in our view,
curtail some of the risks of misuse of power,
in that respect.
The third and final point that we want to make really goes to
practical implications
of the bill in its current form, and I want to highlight two points.
The first is in terms of the order, once it's given,
officers under Section 8A (2) are allowed to
impose a specified distance from which the person should
go. They, under Section 8A (2)
, are also allowed to make an order that the person remain at a specified
distance from the public space. But there's no limitation on what that
distance would be. The issues are twofold.
First, these people are obviously homeless and without resources,
so there's a risk that by not having no limit to that
distance, you may be setting these homeless people up to fail if they can't
actually get the specified distance in the required timeframe.
Also, there's no requirement that the distance
be reasonable, particularly. This is a more broad point.
The distance should be specified as being reasonable and
proportionate to the specific issue of public disorder in
question. In other words, if somebody is setting up camp in Auckland CBD,
you shouldn't require them to go all the way out to South Auckland to avoid that
issue. You should just say, "Get out of Auckland CBD for the specified
period." So the solution we propose is effectively to
include a parenthesis which says, "Provided the distance
specified is reasonable and proportionate for the purpose of maintaining public
order."
The final point very quickly is really just in respect of the penalties.
There's a suggested $2,000 fine. These people are homeless.
They don't have money. We suggest just remove the option of a fine and
suggest a maximum of three-month penalty.
Judges can impose appropriate other means
for sentencing, such as community work and supervision.
The suggestion of a fine is nonsensical in our view.
Those really are our submissions in a nutshell. Any questions?
Thank you very much, Steven. We've got a couple of questions. We'll start with Dr.
Duncan Webb.
Kia ora. Thank you. Thank you for that submission.
Just interested in leaning on your legal expertise.
One of the challenges that may exist here is
kind of around what amounts to the conduct.
I'm particularly interested in rough sleeping,
which is defined as setting up personal possessions, makeshift
shelters, or other structures indicating an intent to inhabit.
Now,
I would have thought inhabit means to kind of move in or to live.
So if you
happen to be just stuck
in front of a doorway overnight, would you say that's inhabiting?
Do you see any problems with definitions of these kind of relatively, what I would
have thought, loose terms?
That's the problem.
They're relatively and far too loose.
I think
they would be open to too much interpretation, and so refinement
of those definitions would be required, I think.
Thank you.
And a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Yeah, thanks for that submission.
If you could clarify for my understanding,
your submission describes this bill as moving away from the
traditional criminal law model, where police powers generally
respond to completed offending towards a
intervention-based or anticipated conduct.
Could you explain why that shift should concern us
as a committee?
Sure.
I suppose the criminal liability comes into place once an order is
breached. And so an order would have to be given
first and then disobeyed in order to become criminal.
So, in that respect, the criminal act comes after
the actual decision not to institute the order.
But the whole basis of the order being given is sort of a presumption of
criminal behavior, right? That's where the offense would begin.
So that becomes effectively an element of the offense, criminalizing
somebody before they've actually done something, which inherently just doesn't sit
right, in my submission, with the criminal justice process.
Thank you. That's very helpful. Cheers.
All right. Thank you, Devon, and thank you, Ryan.
Really appreciate both of you joining us this afternoon and for your submission, so
thank you.
Thanks for listening. Thank you.
Okay, members, we come to our next submitter, and that is going to be the Methodist
Alliance, and we've got Hamish who's going to be joining us.
Hi, Hamish. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We've got you down for a 10-minute submission.
We have read your submission, but please do leave a little bit of time at the end
for questions.
Kia ora. Awesome. Thank you.
Kia ora, members of the committee, and thanks for your time
today.
The Methodist Alliance, as you will have read in the submission, we're a formal
alliance of Methodist missions, parishes, community-based social services,
cooperating ventures.
And we provide a range of services across the areas of
tamariki children, rangatahi, and whanau.
So I wanted to start by saying that this legislation is
unnecessary and in our opinion is cruel.
Laws which are needed to control and penalize antisocial and
aggressive behaviors are already in place, and as already stated by
many of the opponents to this bill, it won't make a meaningful difference
in the day-to-day in our city centers in particular.
The number of people sleeping rough on the streets in Aotearoa is a direct result
of multiple failings at the government level, which make
life harder for people who are already living in distressing circumstances.
The cost of living, unaffordable housing, limited access to employment,
insufficient income support when employment cannot be found,
and inadequate mental health and addiction services contribute
to people being impacted by a combination of these issues and
living and sleeping rough.
Without a stable address and income, some are resorting to begging to scrape
together the money needed to survive and, as previously mentioned, setting up sort
of makeshift
housing
in our city centers in particular.
We're also seeing a notable increase in both young people and elderly people
sleeping rough, people who are impacted more severely by the risks
inherent in sleeping on the street, like the cold and
security issues. Despite this, police data
doesn't support the perceived increase in disorderly or aggressive behavior by
these people. So again, it's
a solution
looking for a problem
in reality.
For this legislation won't do anything to mitigate these issues and will actually
criminalize people who are living with the result of systemic failures.
It's window-dressing, optics-based policymaking, which will have
devastating impacts on real humans who are already struggling.
So
by shifting people who are sleeping rough,
and as mentioned by the previous submitters,
the bill as it stands
has the potential to criminalize people just for the intent of sleeping rough,
which, in itself, it's a pretty
difficult thing to wrap your head around the intention to sleep rough.
Most people are not setting out to sleep rough.
They're there
because of circumstances outside of their control.
And if they had access to housing, the majority of people would be in that.
Shifting people
won't solve the issues that they're dealing
with and has the potential to shift them further away from the services that they
need and the support that they need.
Vast majority of the support that's available for people living
in these circumstances are in city centers,
and shifting them further and further away from them will only exacerbate their
problems. And forcing people to shift from these areas
won't just shift them away from that support, but will actually take them to places
where they're less visible and issues that arise are unable to be
addressed.
So we can see examples of that in some areas of
Aotearoa already, where encampments come up outside of the
eye of
the majority of the public and in some cases the police, and security concerns
come up for the people living in those areas who are not homeless, but also for
vulnerable people within those communities who have nowhere to go for
help.
I wanted to also touch on the criminalization of people as young as
14.
People who are in this circumstance, in particular under the age of 18,
are often there as a result of untenable living
circumstances at home.
You know
Violence in the home, drug addiction, the things that
we'd really want to be supporting people to escape from,
and falling through the cracks and ending up living on the street.
And to criminalize people because of the circumstance that they've been put in,
it's
setting people up to fail, and it's ruining people's lives before
they have a chance to begin.
So that's
my oral submission for the day, and I'm happy to take any questions if
there are any.
Fantastic. Thanks, Hamish. I'll just look to see if any members have questions.
We've got a question from Dr. Duncan Webb.
Just on a practical point, I guess.
Is the gist of your submission that the police are going to be put in a position
of making people go from a not particularly good
situation to one that's pretty much outright dangerous?
Absolutely.
Yeah. All right. Thank you.
And I'll just see if any other members have questions for you.
Doesn't appear to be the case, Hamish.
We thank you for submitting to us this afternoon and for your written submission as
well, so thank you.
Awesome. Thank you.
All right, members, we come to Jason, who's going to be presenting to
us next.
Kia ora, Jason. Thanks for joining us this afternoon.
We've got you down for a 10-minute submission.
We have read the submission, but just leave some time for questions.
All right. Thank you. Tēnā koutou, Chair me ngā mema o te committee.
Ko Jason Alexanders tōku ingoa, and I'm the Chief Operating Officer here at
Hāpai Te Hauora, for whom I'm presenting on behalf of
today. Thank you for the opportunity to speak on this
important kaupapa.
Just a little bit of background on Hāpai.
So we're a national Māori public health organization, and we're grounded in Te
Tiriti and kaupapa Māori approaches to health and
well-being.
We oppose this bill in its entirety,
and our main point is simple. This bill uses
criminal justice tools to manage what is fundamentally a housing,
health, and poverty crisis. It does not address why people are
sleeping rough, begging, or experiencing distress in public
places. Instead, it just criminalizes the behaviors that people
are using to survive when our housing, health, and social systems
have failed them.
We recognize that our businesses, workers, and members of the
public have some legitimate concerns.
And where someone is violent, threatening, harassing others, or
even blocking access,
police have
existing powers to respond to that harmful behavior,
and they should intervene. But sleeping
rough and begging are not the same as violence or intimidation,
and I think there is an important difference between responding to harmful
conduct and criminalizing the visible signs of poverty,
and this bill, in its current form, crosses that line.
The basic question, and one that we've heard repeatedly is, when someone is told
to move on, where are they expected to go?
And for many people, the answer is nowhere.
And that's because a move on order does not create a home.
It does not provide a mental health bed,
addiction treatment, transport, or a safe sleep
space. It simply moves someone in their distress elsewhere.
From a public health perspective, displacement can
make people less safe. It might push people away from
central, familiar, and well-lit areas into darker or more isolated
places that can increase their exposure to violence and other
harms. It can also break important connections with support services, and
we've heard a lot about that already.
Health providers, outreach teams, community organizations often rely on knowing
where at-risk whānau are located, and that's how they can provide them with
medication, kai, mental health support, and connections to housing and other
services.
If people are constantly moved, then those
relationships can be disrupted. Whānau may lose contact with
outreach workers, become separated from their belongings and support networks, or
even miss opportunities to enter treatment or accommodation.
So stability is a predictive factor for whānau.
Once again, displacement creates more stress.
It creates uncertainty and isolation.
It makes it harder for people to address addiction, mental distress, poor
health, or housing insecurity.
The bill may make poverty less visible in one location,
but that is not the same
as making the community safer.
We have to remember that homeless whānau are part of our
community.
Quite often we're hearing people talk about them, but they
are us.
Like others, we're also concerned with the penalties.
So a person who does not comply with an order could face a fine of up to
$2,000 or three months in prison. Fining someone who
is already experiencing extreme poverty is
obviously troublesome. It will not change their circumstances.
It creates debt that they
cannot pay. So
that brings them further into the justice system,
and this is how poverty becomes a pathway to criminal conviction.
I think an important point is that the impact of this bill will not be
evenly shared. So Māori are significantly
overrepresented among people experiencing homelessness,
housing deprivation, and contact with the criminal justice
system. It sort of reflects the ongoing effects
of colonization, land loss, economic dispossession, and policies that have
undermined Māori access to secure housing resources and economic stability.
Law directed at rough sleeping, begging, and occupying
public spaces will therefore fall more heavily on Māori, even if
its wording appears neutral
Obviously, we're especially concerned that these powers can apply to our rangatahi
from the age of 14.
Yeah. I mean, a 14-year-old sleeping rough or begging, they need
protection, they need safe housing, they need support.
They should not be exposed to police orders and possible criminal conviction just
because the systems around them have failed.
The bill, it relies on broad and
subjective judgments around who is disruptive or disorderly,
and we're not suggesting deliberate discrimination by individual police officers,
but we cannot ignore the evidence around how
discretion is applied and operates within the justice system.
So the police's own understanding, policing delivery research
found that when the other variables examined were held constant, Māori
were on average 11% more likely to be prosecuted than New Zealand Europeans.
The research does not prove deliberate discrimination in any individual
case, but it demonstrates a significant unequal outcome that
requires consideration.
The Ministry of Justice has also found that discretionary decisions
within the justice system contribute to the unexplained overrepresentation
of wāhine Māori. Although wāhine Māori only make up around
15% of the female population, they account for 44% of women
subject to formal police action.
So when this bill gives police another broad power based on
subjective judgments about behavior, there is a
foreseeable risk that it will not be applied evenly and that Māori will
again carry a disproportionate share of the consequences.
And I think
that this raises some serious questions and concerns under Te Tiriti.
So the Crown has an obligation to actively protect Māori and prevent
foreseeable inequitable outcomes.
It also has an obligation to ensure that Māori participate
meaningfully in decisions that will affect Māori communities.
Yet there was limited Māori consultation and no robust Māori
impact assessment, despite the clear likelihood that the bill will
disproportionately affect Māori.
Applying the same law to everyone does not create equity when that law
operates in deeply unequal circumstances.
There's still no substantial
evidence that move on powers deter crime or even reduce
disorder.
By contrast, there is well-established evidence base for interventions that do
work. So when people are supported into stable housing,
we know that they're hospitalized less, that they experience
better mental health, they have greater opportunities to earn income, and have
less contact with police.
The government's own regulatory,
sorry, impact statement also concluded the likely cost of this bill would outweigh
the benefits and recommended maintaining the status quo.
So if the goal is to
reduce disorder and improve outcomes for people experiencing homelessness, the
evidence points to long-term wraparound housing support, not
expanding enforcement powers that have no demonstrated deterrent effect.
Legislation should respond to evidence of actual harm and evidence of what
works, not simply to the discomfort caused by the
visibility of poverty.
True public safety comes from stable housing, accessible mental health and
addiction services,
outreach support, and properly funded
kaupapa Māori providers.
We can't arrest our way out of a housing crisis.
Moving someone two streets away does not create safety.
It simply relocates the distress and makes poverty less
visible. Therefore, we ask the committee to recommend that
this bill
not proceed, and instead, Parliament should invest in housing-first
approaches, emergency and transitional accommodation, mental health and addiction
services, and iwi and Māori providers that address the underlying causes of
homelessness and create genuine, lasting safety for
everyone in our communities. Nō reira, tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou, tēnā
tatou katoa.
Thank you, Jason. Thanks for your submission.
I'll just look to see if there's any members with questions.
Does not appear to be the case. Thank you so much for your time this afternoon and
for the written submission you've made as well.
Thank you.
Thanks, Jason. Okay, members, our next submitter is going to be
the New Zealand PC, Aotearoa New Zealand Sex Workers Collective,
and we're just going to have them both promoted.
It's going to be Catherine and Ana.
Hey, Catherine. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
If you're just able to turn on your camera so we can see you.
Great.
And thank you for joining us. We've got you for 10 minutes.
We've read your submission, but just leave some time at the end for questions.
Tēnā koutou katoa. Ko Catherine Healy
toko i ngā. And my role is to coordinate
NZPC for short, Aotearoa New Zealand Sex
Workers Collective, formerly the Prostitute
Collective.
We've contacted, uh, the government health agencies for
nearly four decades and to provide services to sex
workers nationally. So our daily work brings us
into direct contact with sex workers who will
potentially be negatively impacted by this proposed
legislation. Um, I think our experience is
somewhat unique. We were delighted in 2003 to
see the old laws around soliciting in a
public place repealed
From the Summary Offences Act, the act that's at the
heart of this legislation proposed.
These old unjust laws had been used to arrest youth
as young as 14 and turn them away from avenues of
support so necessary for young people, and potentially
harmful situations. And
I well recall, we all well recall the revolving door
for sex workers who were arrested, convicted, and processed
through the court system only to return to work the streets
to pay the $200 fine, hiding
from the police and all who could've provided more tangible
support. Our recollection is that soliciting laws did not
make a dent in the amount of sex work-related
activities that occurred, but contributed, of course, to
the alienation for youth and adults alike.
There were significant changes when these laws were
repealed from the Summary Offences Act, and we moved away
from the punitive model. Relationships with the police improved,
which benefited not just
sex workers, but other people sharing this space,
such as residents. We're
not unaware of tensions that arise between sex
workers and residents and businesses but are
experienced in what academia refers to
in this context as the more progressive
collaborative model. For example, in Christchurch,
residents on and near Manchester Street and
residential areas had concerns about
street-based sex work and
its potential to disrupt their peace at night.
And the council made a small investment, somewhere
like 20,000, to support
extra outreach in order for our staff from the sex work community
to liaise with residents and sex workers to address
and resolve these
incidents from time to time. The sex workers are
supported to work in spots that don't trigger
complaints, and the relationship with the police is also
key. It's our impression that it's important and
far more effective to move on from punitive
legislative models and strengthen community resources
to enhance the well-being for the most affected.
We sincerely hope this legislation will not pass
further scrutiny.
Its effects, if so, will be deeply
harmful. Thank you.
Kia ora koutou. I am Anna Pickering.
I've been doing outreach work for NZPC with street-based sex workers
since 2003 throughout the Tāmaki Makaurau region.
There are probably 150 street-based sex workers, but only
20 to 30 would work on any given night.
The problem with this move on order legislation is it will recriminalize sex
workers and make sex work unsafer.
Many sex workers face financial hardship, have health issues, and
deal with stigma and discrimination.
A small number of street-based sex workers are homeless and face extensive
hardship and abuse. Society often regards street sex
workers as over there, and as if they are not part of society.
So recent media coverage of street-based sex workers in Karangahape is not
new, but it ignores the positive working relationship with
agencies like NZPC, sex workers, and police
that helps minimize unsafe behaviors.
Other people often label sex workers as a threat rather than understanding their
vulnerability in street settings.
If you're a sex worker who is homeless with mental health and addiction challenges,
this legislation could mean you are pushed into less safe places.
For example, I've dealt with a sex worker who was homeless and
pregnant. If she was moved on, I may not be able to find her as an
outreach worker to support her accessing prenatal care and
get her secure housing. Right now, if you are one of these workers or
an underage worker, you can seek police help and the help of other
agencies through NZPC. The move on legislation would make
already vulnerable sex workers more at risk.
Rather than seeking police help, sex workers would fear entrapment.
Moving sex workers onto less safe spaces means it will
be harder for NZPC and other agencies to provide help.
Move on orders would separate sex workers from other workers.
Working together in the same space means street sex workers can try
to make their interactions with clients as safe as possible.
They can screen clients by having a conversation, have time to check
there's just one person in the car, and other workers can note number plates,
all to help ensure the worker is as safe as possible.
Then there's the financial impact of proposed penalties, which would also
mean that certainly some street workers will be sent to prison.
Decriminalizing sex work means sex workers can operate without fear
of prosecution. The relationship between sex workers and the police have
moved from an adversarial to cooperating, with sex worker
safety and community safety are threatened.
There are always going to be tensions in street-based sex work, but
NZPC's experience, and that of other agencies is that working
collaboratively and openly is the key to better outcomes.
Move on orders would reduce openness and access.
They would stigmatize street-based sex workers and other soft
targets. Decriminalization of sex work made sex work safer.
It helped police and sex workers create safer environments for sex work in the
community. This proposed move on legislation threatens
those gains and will recriminalize sex workers.
Move on orders will reduce, not enhance community safety.
Move on orders will make sex work more hazardous. Kia ora.
Thank you, Catherine, and thank you, Anna. We've got a question from Dr.
Duncan Webb.
Kia ora. Good to see you, and thanks for all the hard work that you do do in this
important space. Hadn't really thought about this intersection before,
but obviously Manchester Street is in the middle of my electorate, and it's
actually a really good example there
because some of those street-based sex workers were a little
disruptive.
But the insertion of a
support worker was really useful, and it might be useful if you could
just talk a little bit more about how that worked, because that was a
pair, if I remember rightly, and she was quite someone.
Can you just tell us about how that worked and why that might be a better option?
Exactly. And I guess it stopped the letters to your office.
She's there. She's still there. And, I suspect and I
know, I think, that there haven't been complaints stacked up
for council either. So she goes out.
She's intimately known in that community.
She is a force. And she has really good direct
contact with the police
and the sex workers respecter, the residents as well.
So, we encourage residents to
make contact with us if there is an issue.
So, I don't know if they're presenting to this committee, but
it says a lot if they're not.
Thank you.
Right. Thank you, Catherine, and thank you, Anna.
Really appreciate both of you spending some time and submitting with us this
afternoon. So thank you very much.
Members, our next submitters are the Human Rights Commission.
We're going to have Prudence and Michael who are going to be submitting to us.
Hi, Prudence. Hi, Michael. Thank you both for joining
us-
Kia ora
... this afternoon.
We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, if you can just leave some time at the end for
questions.
Kia ora. Kia ora koutou. Thank you for this opportunity to expand
on some of our written submission, which, as you've signaled, we take as
read.
Everybody in Aotearoa and New Zealand should be able to move through public
places, use public transport, work, gather,
rest, and connect with others safely and with dignity.
The commission recognizes that workers, businesses, residents, and
communities may have real concerns about behavior in public
places, that is, or that they perceive to be
harmful, threatening, or distressing.
These concerns deserve an effective response.
However, public safety is not strengthened by moving people
experiencing hardship, and many of who are not engaging in
social behavior out of sight. Sorry, antisocial behavior.
The bill
creates wide powers to exclude people from public places.
That may shift where hardship is seen, but it will not reduce harm,
prevent homelessness, or create safer communities.
I know from my engagements around this bill that in speaking to two primary
concerns today, I will be reiterating points made by many
other submitters. The two areas I wish to briefly highlight
today are that the bill is a poor solution to a complex
social problem, and that it is unnecessary and unworkable.
Before doing so, I wish to briefly remind the committee of the human rights
engaged by the bill as set out in our written submission.
These include the right to adequate housing and the right to the
highest attainable standard of physical and mental health.
Move on orders also engage several fundamental civil and political
rights, including freedom of movement, expression, peaceful
assembly and association, and the right to liberty and security
of the person. These rights are protected in the New Zealand Bill of
Rights Act 1990 and the International Covenant on
Civil and Political Rights, to which New Zealand is a
party. New Zealand's implementation of the
ICCPR is scheduled for a
review by the United Nations Human Rights Committee in
2027. Should the bill be enacted, it is
likely to be of significant interest to the committee.
And I draw this to the committee's attention because New Zealand's strong
record in upholding civil and political rights
underpins its international reputation,
including its diplomatic relationships, trade interests, and overall
effectiveness on the global stage.
First, the bill is a poor solution to a complex legal
problem. The bill is ineffective and a
counterproductive response to the problems it seeks to address.
I note that the commission is not alone in this view.
Many social service providers, religious leaders, businesses,
Retail New Zealand, and the Police Association, and the Ministries of
Justice and Housing have either opposed or raised
significant concerns about using move on powers to
respond to homelessness, poverty, and low-level public disorder.
The RIS reaches a similar conclusion.
It states that formal law enforcement responses are neither
appropriate nor effective responses for public
disorder that falls below the criminal threshold, and that
move on orders are not necessary because other responses may be more
appropriate. The bill is likely to have discriminatory
intersectional impacts because the proposed grounds for issuing a move
on order include begging, rough sleeping, and conduct
said to indicate an intent to occupy
a public place are closely associated with issues which
disproportionately affect certain groups.
These issues include poverty, homelessness, unmet disability support
needs, mental distress, addiction, family violence,
and housing insecurity. They're caused by barriers to inadequate
housing, healthcare, income support, safety, and
public participation. Barriers such as discrimination,
which the Special Rapporteur on the right to adequate housing has
identified as both a cause and a consequence of
homelessness.
The bill may have the compounding effect of making already marginalized
people less visible to outreach workers and community
support services, disrupting informal safety networks
and pushing people into more isolated or unsafe
locations. There are better solutions to address the concerns
this bill attempts to respond to. A human rights based
approach requires the state to identify and address the
structural drivers and social determinants of issues
like homelessness and disorderly conduct.
This requires accessible, culturally safe, disability
responsive, gender affirming, trauma informed, and
community-led houses and support services.
There is no provision in the bill to facilitate these.
The focus on reform should be on evidence-based
solutions that address the root causes of homelessness.
Effective approaches already exist, including properly
resourcing Housing First, investing in kaupapa Maori housing,
and significantly
expanding public
housing supply. These must be accompanied by sustained
investment in outreach and integrated social services to ensure people can
access the support they need to secure
and sustain housing.
Secondly, the bill is unnecessary and unworkable.
The bill creates new powers in an area where the law already
provides police and local authorities with a range of tools to
respond to genuinely harmful or disorderly
conduct. The commission is therefore concerned that the bill
duplicates existing offenses and powers rather than filling a
clear legal gap.
Where conduct is genuinely threatening, harmful, or
criminal, it can already be addressed.
The proposed response is disproportionate.
The Ministry of Justice's offense and penalty vetting
process found that the proposed offense for breaching a
move on order is disproportionate to the harm caused and would
create inconsistencies in the law.
Sentences of imprisonment should be reserved for serious offending given the
significant infringement on human rights that imprisonment has.
There is a significant risk of inconsistency and arbitrary
application and enforcement. The bill gives police
significant discretion to issue move on
orders on the basis of broad and potentially subjective
concepts, including disorderly or disruptive
behavior, begging, rough sleeping, and conduct said to
indicate an intent to occupy a public place.
In policing, discretion is a double-edged sword.
It can allow police to make appropriate decisions about
whether or not the conduct they're dealing with merits a punitive
response. However, it may also mean orders are issued to
people simply because they are visibly poor, homeless, distressed,
disabled, or present in public space in
ways that others consider uncomfortable or undesirable.
Whilst discretion will allow police to make judgment calls, it also
introduces a real risk of inconsistent or discriminatory
application if decisions are made based on appearance,
location, perceived social status, complaints from particular
members of the public, or stereotypes around homelessness
and public disorder.
The bill also creates difficult legal distinctions and
likely unintended consequences.
For example, the bill exempts people whose primary
purpose is demonstrating support for opposition
to or publicizing a point of view, cause, or
campaign.
This may mean that a person protesting homelessness or poverty while sleeping rough
or seeking donations is protected from a move on order,
while another person in the same circumstances but without an
expressly political message is not.
For these reasons, the
commission recommends that the bill should not proceed.
More effective and rights-consistent solutions would focus on preventing
and ending homelessness through stable, accessible housing,
accessible health and addiction services, outreach, whanau-centered
support, and stronger social protections.
Addressing the underlying root causes of poverty would directly and
significantly improve the safety and wellbeing of communities
in an enduring way. If the bill does proceed, the commission
recommends in line with option two proposed in the RIS
that begging, rough sleeping, and any intent to
occupy grounds be removed. That move on orders
not apply to anyone under 18.
That there is a requirement for the issuing of orders to only be
done when strictly necessary and proportionate to the circumstances,
and that there is a requirement for connection to referral
pathways for housing, health, and social support
responses when an order is issued Thank you again for the
opportunity to speak to the committee today.
We're available to answer any questions that you may have in the remaining
time.
Thanks, Prudence. We've got time for one question, and it's going to be from Dan
Rosewarne.
Thanks for that submission. Reading through it, point six on
page three is a good one. You highlight the bill creates a
pathway from poverty-related conduct to detention,
prosecution, fines, and then imprisonment.
And I was just wondering if you could talk the committee through quickly on how
that pathway might occur for a person experiencing
homelessness.
Sure. I'll just hand over to my colleague, Chief Legal Advisor, Michael.
Thanks for that question. So how that pathway would
work, so a homeless person who's been issued with a move on order, and
then doesn't follow that move on order is then subject to
penalty. They're now, instead of being exposed to
social services and support to assist them,
they are within the criminal justice system.
And as we know that the criminal justice system
often perpetuates
hardship,
and can result in
that individual then engaging
in what could actually be harmful behavior or
conduct beyond the homelessness issue without
actually addressing homelessness in any way.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Thanks, Prudence, and thank you, Michael.
We appreciate your time this afternoon and your submission.
Thank you.
Right. We are now going to have
Marion, who's going to be presenting to us.
My apologies, Marlon.
Marlon, my apologies.
Thank you for joining us this afternoon. We have read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, if you can just leave some time at the end for
questions.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Kia ora koutou. My name is Marlon Drake.
I'm the lead organizer of Te Ohu Whakawhanaunga Tāmaki Makaurau, a community
alliance here in Auckland made up of 37 faith, union, and
community organizations, including Salvation Army, Lifewise,
St Heliers Church and Community Center, St Matthew in the City, the Auckland
Anglican Diocese, Community Housing Aotearoa, and many others.
Collectively, Te Ohu represents over 100,000 people in Auckland through our
institutions, and today, that is the perspective from which I am speaking, an
Auckland Community Alliance's perspective.
From our perspective, here's the reality.
Move on orders would criminalize the victims of a failed homelessness policy.
Instead of providing homes and support services, which are proven to
help solve the issue and work to solve the issue of homelessness,
we are asking police to move homeless people around the CBD.
Homelessness and housing experts do not want this.
Communities like those represented by Te Ohu do not want this.
The Police Association doesn't think this is the way to go, and even businesses
like the Cairo Business Association and the Uptown Business Association have come
out and said that this is not the way to go.
And yet, here we are at a select committee meeting, entertaining a
policy that asks police officers who would rather be doing actual police
work to move homeless people from one street to another,
outside of one business to the outside of another business, or arrest
them and send them potentially to jail.
This is a bill which serves nobody.
To put it bluntly,
the perspective of Te Ohu is that the move on orders are a total moral
and political failure. I want to speak briefly to two core issues with this bill,
although there are many. But presumably many of them will be covered by others
with areas of expertise. The first, though, is the fundamental criminalization of
homelessness. Including rough sleeping and the intent to inhabit a space
amounts to a broad criminalization of homelessness.
Instead of providing support, we are asking police to manage a complex issue that
is fundamentally outside of their remit.
Homelessness has increased immensely over the
past two years. It is now broadly understood that this is due to policy
changes. Crucially, one example, the decrease of access to emergency
housing. People become homeless in the first place for a variety of
reasons. Last year in March, we held a community meeting
at Merge Cafe on Karangahape Road.
We held it with 15 to 20 members of the street community in Auckland
CBD. Some of them were now or just recently in
social housing, but many of them were at that time living on the street,
including under bridges.
For some,
well, we heard the stories of how they ended up rough sleeping.
For some, they were escaping a traumatic situation.
For example, a woman escaping domestic violence, or when they were
younger children escaping family violence.
For others, they ended up on the street due to
addiction issues, and for others, it was mental health.
And in fact, one story we heard
was from a man who said everything was fine. He had a full-time job.
He had a home. He had friends and family, and then one day, he
simply had a mental health break out of the blue, out of nowhere, and ended up on
the street.
These people are not criminals. They are New Zealanders, and they, in our case, are
Aucklanders who need help. And the fact that people as young as
14, children as young as 14, are being included in this
is a total moral failure. The second big issue is that
we have a solution that works. Housing first policies, for example,
providing a home and providing wraparound support services, has been proven to have
up to an 83% success rate. That is the kind of project that we should
be spending our resources and time talking about.
How can we implement housing first policies in Auckland to address homelessness?
Public housing even, which is currently being sold, and public housing projects,
many of which have been canceled, is another solution which we know works.
And the fact that we are selling off some of these houses at these different sites
in Auckland, and there are canceled projects in Auckland, and then on the other
hand, we're talking about sending police to address the issue of homelessness,
is a bizarre contrast. Finally, I just want to reference a letter
which was written and sent by representatives of Te Ohu.
So 31 clergy within Auckland wrote an
open letter to the government. I wanted to read out a couple of points here.
"This policy is far broader than simply giving police greater power to respond to
aggressive antisocial behavior.
It can affect anybody who is rough sleeping or intends to inhabit a space and can
be applied to children as young as 14.
We see the introduction of move on orders as a superficial and unhelpful approach
that has the potential to cause real harm to those members of our community that
are most vulnerable.
If this policy is not accompanied by significant increases in support for Housing
First programs and transitional housing, then we are not solving the problem of
rough sleeping. We are simply kicking the can down the road, except in
this case, the can is a human being."
Te Ohu Whakawhanake Tāmaki Makaurau
obviously stands against this policy and would like to see it
not progress to a second reading. Kia ora.
Thank you, Marlon. I'll just see if we've got any members who'd like to ask you a
question.
Does not appear to be the case. Thank you so much for joining us this afternoon.
Really appreciate your written submission and your oral submission as well.
Thank you for your time.
Okay. Our next submitter isn't with us at the moment, but Epilepsy
Waikato Charitable Trust are, so we're going to have Esther and David present to
us.
Hi, Esther and David. Great to see you both.
Thank you for being here nice and early.
Really do appreciate your punctuality, which is fantastic.
We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, if you can just leave some time at the end for
questions. Over to you.
Awesome. Thank you. Tena koutou katoa, and thank you for the opportunity to
speak. My name is Esther Little. I am the epilepsy advisor for
Epilepsy Waikato Charitable Trust, and with me is David Nichols, our
administrator and secretary, who is also a member of EWCT
and a representative of the epilepsy community.
EWCT is the leading epilepsy specific organization in the
Waikato. We work directly with disabled people, their
whanau, carers, and communities, and we see every day
how disability, poverty, housing insecurity, and health
inequities intersect.
We also fill a major data and policy gap in Aotearoa,
because epilepsy is almost invisible in disability policy, homelessness
reporting, and government decision-making.
I want to speak today about why this bill will harm disabled people, especially
people with epilepsy, why it will worsen homelessness, and why it will make
our communities less safe.
Firstly, disabled people are already over-represented in homelessness, and
this bill targets them.
I want to start with something simple.
Disabled people are already over-represented in homelessness.
We see this in the Waikato constantly.
This includes people with neurological conditions, chronic illness,
mobility impairments, sensory disabilities, and mental health
conditions. People with epilepsy may fit into multiple of these
subcategories.
New Zealand media has repeatedly reported disabled people sleeping in cars,
garages, riverbanks, and public spaces, including in the
Waikato,
after being denied emergency housing or being unable to access
disability appropriate accommodation.
Emergency housing is often inaccessible, unsafe, or
unsuitable for people with seizures or mobility impairments, and often
simply unavailable.
Let me start with a vignette that illustrates several of the issues we see.
Vignette one, the car park.
A middle-aged man with epilepsy sleeps in his car behind a supermarket
because the emergency motel has stairs he cannot climb safely.
He keeps his medication in a chilly bin because the car gets too hot during the
day. He avoids the city center because he worries someone will mistake
his seizures for intoxication.
His situation shows how disability, inaccessible housing, poverty,
and stigma intersect, and how easily a person like him could
be moved on under this bill.
This bill does not address any of those issues.
Instead, it gives police the power to move disabled people away from the places
where they feel safest and where their support networks are located.
Point two, epilepsy is invisible in homelessness policy, but it absolutely
is present in reality.
Epilepsy is one of Aotearoa's most common long-term neurological
disabilities,
yet it is almost entirely invisible in homelessness reporting, disability
data, and policy design. That invisibility is dangerous.
International research shows epilepsy rates among homeless adults are three to
four times higher than in the general population.
Homelessness increases seizure frequency through sleep deprivation,
stress, exposure to cold, and inconsistent access to
medication.
Homeless adults with epilepsy have two to three times higher mortality,
including increased risk of sudden unexpected death in epilepsy,
SUDEP.
A major 2023 study in the Journal of Neural Transmission found
homeless people have higher prevalence of seizures and epilepsy.
Children in homeless families have higher risk of epilepsy, often
undetected.
80% of homeless people miss medical appointments due to lack of transport or a
fixed address.
Medication cannot be stored safely or taken consistently.
Hospitalization rates are five times higher, and epilepsy plus
homelessness creates a stigmatized, neglected, under-researched niche.
This is exactly the population that move on orders will target.
Point three. EWCT's own data shows the scale of this problem.
EWCT holds data on 960 clients.
At least 29 of those 960 people have been homeless, face
homelessness, or are currently homeless.
Some have lived in vehicles, garages, emergency accommodation, or
severely overcrowded housing.
Many more live in homes that are completely unsuitable for their condition: damp,
cold, inaccessible, unsafe during seizures, far from medical
services, or unaffordable due to disability-related poverty.
One of our members was featured in the "Waikato Herald" last year in an article
titled, "A Hamilton woman with cerebral palsy living in a campervan with three
dogs because she could not access safe, affordable housing."
This is not an outlier. It is a pattern.
Move on orders will directly harm people like her.
Point four. Move on orders will criminalize seizure-related behaviors.
I want to be very clear about this. A seizure can look like disorderly
behavior. A seizure can look like confusion,
wandering,
sitting or lying down suddenly,
appearing disoriented, involuntary movements, or
inability to respond coherently.
Under this bill, those behaviors can be interpreted as disorderly,
disruptive, intimidating,
breaching the peace, or attempting to inhabit a public place.
People with epilepsy may be unable to comply with a move on order,
unable to provide biographical details, detained or arrested for
non-compliance caused by disability, or displaced from areas where they
access medication support or safety.
Here is another vignette that shows how easily this could happen.
Vignette two. The bus stop.
A young man has a seizure at a bus stop.
He's confused, pacing, and unable to answer questions.
A passerby thinks he is acting strangely.
Under this bill, a police officer could interpret his behavior as
disorderly or disruptive
and issue a move on order,
or detain him for failing to provide details he is medically unable to give.
This single moment touches on disability, policing, stigma,
health risk, and criminalization all at once.
This bill creates a dangerous precedent, criminalizing medical events
or disability-related behaviors.
Point five. Move on orders will harm disabled youth.
The bill applies to 14-year-olds.
Youth homelessness is rising. Epilepsy in young people is
often misunderstood.
Young people with epilepsy may experience postictal confusion,
sensory overload, communication difficulties, or sudden
collapse.
These behaviors can be misinterpreted as disorderly or
disruptive. Youth advocates warn of a street to prison
pipeline. This bill will accelerate it,
especially for disabled Rangatahi and Māori youth.
Point six. Homelessness is rising because of policy choices.
Across Aotearoa, rough sleeping increased 40% each quarter from late
2023 to early 2025.
Emergency housing grants dropped from 6,429
to 1,290 in one year.
Emergency housing spending dropped from $23 million to $3
million.
Social housing rents are increasing.
Temporary additional support is being cut.
State house builds have been canceled.
Emergency housing access has been restricted.
People are living in cars, garages, riverbanks, and under
bridges.
Move on orders will punish people for homelessness created by government decisions.
Point seven. The bill breaches Te Tiriti, the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act,
and the United Nations Convention for the Rights of People with Disabilities.
The Waitangi Tribunal found that policies increasing Māori homelessness
breached Articles two and three of Te Tiriti.
Māori are disproportionately represented in homelessness and in neurological
conditions. Move on orders will worsen inequities in health,
housing, and justice.
The Attorney-General's Section Seven report found the bill is inconsistent with the
New Zealand Bill of Rights Act, breaching freedom of movement, freedom of
expression, and freedom from discrimination.
The bill also contradicts UNCRPD obligations to ensure
disabled people are not criminalized for disability-related behaviors
and have access to housing and support.
And our final point, the bill is opposed by experts, social
services, and even police.
Social services call move on orders superficial and
unhelpful,
totally and utterly ineffective,
abhorrent.
The Police Association says the bill will drain resources and be ineffective.
Housing and Justice Ministries advised against it.
Even the Police Minister has said police should not lead homelessness responses.
This bill is not evidence-based.
What do we ask of the committee? EWCT urges the committee to
reject the bill in its entirety.
If the bill does proceed, we ask that you remove rough
sleeping, begging, and intent to inhabit a public place.
Prohibit move on orders for disabled people.
Prohibit move on orders for anyone under 18.
Require disability and neurological literacy training for police.
Require co-design with disabled people, Māori, and homelessness
organizations. And invest in real solutions,
housing first, kaupapa Māori housing, public housing,
outreach and social services, duty to assist legislation,
ending benefit sanctions,
restoring emergency housing access, disability appropriate
housing, and community-based supports.
These are evidence-based, rights-based, and effective
People with epilepsy, disabled people, Māori, young people, and people
experiencing homelessness deserve safety, dignity, and support,
not displacement, detentions, fines, or imprisonment.
Move on orders will harm the very people who are already most vulnerable.
They will criminalise disability-related behaviours, worsen homelessness,
breach Te Tiriti, breach New Zealand Bill of Rights Act,
breach the United Nations Convention for the Rights of People with Disabilities,
and increase health and justice system costs.
We urge you to reject this bill and invest in real solutions that uphold
the rights, safety, and wellbeing of all people in Aotearoa.
Nga mihi nui.
Thank you, Esther, and thank you, David.
We appreciate both of you joining us this afternoon.
We have reached the allocation of your 10 minutes of time, but thank you both
for your oral submission and for your written submission to the committee as well.
Thank you.
Thanks for joining us.
Okay, we will go to Marian, if Marian is online,
please.
Mr. Chair, we don't have Marian on the line yet, but we're just working to get
someone else on. So if you just don't mind holding on for a couple of
minutes.
Members, we'll take a five-minute break, and we'll come back at 2:08,
please.
Okay,
thank you, everyone.
I'll just double-check with the clerks.
Jackie is here. Fantastic. Okay.
We will have Jackie come and present to us.
If you can just promote her, please.
Hey, Jacqui, thank you so much for being with us this afternoon.
Really appreciate you coming nice and early, which is fantastic.
We have read your written submission. We've got you down for five minutes.
If you can just leave some time at the end for questions, that would be amazing.
Right.
I'll see how it goes. Thank you very much, tena koutou, and thank
you for giving me the opportunity to speak today.
I want to just add a couple of perspectives which spring from
my personal experience.
My academic background is in history, so
I like to look at the broad sweep of cause and
effect,
and there are two things in particular.
The first goes back as far, if you'll bear with me, as the English
Poor Laws of 1601 and then
1834.
They both reinforced the notion of the deserving
poor and the undeserving poor, and
I
believe that these draconian move on orders
reflect that
ancient notion of the undeserving poor.
They're addicts, they're rough, they're vagrants, they're an eyesore,
and that whole notion, I think, sadly, is still
alive and well.
The second bit of history is what I see as the destruction of our
welfare state by Ruth Richardson's Mother of All
Budgets in 1991.
And I think we can now clearly see the corrosive
long-term effects of those policies,
particularly shifting state housing to market-based
rents. And this has been made so much
worse by the accommodation supplement, which just siphons
state welfare into the private rental market instead
of building more housing.
That's why we have chronic housing unaffordability and a housing
shortage and soaring rents, and I think that's the recipe for the
poverty we see in New Zealand today.
And just to make it worse, the savage cuts to emergency
housing, those have caused a flood of rough
sleepers, and I have witnessed that dramatic
change for myself
in the course of my work as a tourist guide
in Auckland in particular.
Usually guide tours of
mainly American tourists in Auckland and
Rotorua.
The first thing we do together is walk around the Auckland
CBD.
Our visitors, these are very well-educated Americans in
our groups, they're astonished to see rough sleepers and
beggars here. And I tell them, when I moved to
Australia in the 1980s,
there were no homeless people. You just didn't see anything like that.
I returned in the '90s, and homeless folk and
beggars had appeared on our streets.
I think that's something to do with the government policies, since the
advent of neoliberal philosophies in the
'80s and beyond.
Then the next thing we might do with our group of tourists, and we walk down to
Michael Parekowhai's The Lighthouse art
installation,
and I can tell them all about the sturdy
1950s state houses this
installation represents.
The next day, we often visit Bastion Point, and they read the
inscription on Michael Joseph Savage's memorial.
"He loved his fellow men. There is no fame to rise above the
crowning honor of a people's love." And they want to know what
was so special about this politician.
I tell them the story of the founding of our internationally renowned
welfare state in the 1930s, particularly the state
housing initiative, which has now sadly
gone awry over the last few decades.
Then we leave Auckland, and we head into the Waikato, and we
pass through Ngaruawahia, and there's the
pub. I tell them about Mayor Wayne Brown's quip that
a scruffy homeless person would look better here, and
quote the Mayor of Waikato District's scathing reply, "It
must be nice having a city so flash you can evict people
for not matching the decor."
Because I think that's all this move on idea amounts to,
let's get rid of the visually unappealing instead of
addressing the root problems of poverty.
Where are these homeless folk to go?
Why be so cruel, and why not actually
help with the programs that they need, with the funding that's
needed to address the root problems of poverty?
When I've talked to some of these people, as I do when I get the opportunity,
they turn out to be individuals like you and me.
They're not monsters,
and they're really chuffed to talk to someone friendly.
We know the police already have the necessary powers to address any
unruly behavior, because there is some.
We know that the City Mission is chronically underfunded.
It can only do so much, and that's not nearly enough.
They close at 5:00. We also know, or we should know, that
this short-term policymaking, it doesn't make economic
sense in the long run. It never does.
I find it sad to see our international visitors
increasingly disillusioned about our little South Seas
paradise.
I want to see our country return to being a world leader in a
cohesive, flourishing society, where we don't leave anyone
behind, or at least we try not to.
So I recommend that this foolish and
draconian legislation is abandoned.
Ngā mihi.
Thank you very much, Jacquie, and that was bang on your five minutes, so fantastic
job. And thank you for joining us this afternoon, and for your written submission
as well.
Ngā mihi. Thank you.
Thank you. Okay,
members, we're going to have Rimu, who's going to be presenting to us now.
Thank you, Rimu, for joining us. We have read your written submission, but
if you can leave a little bit of time at the end of your five minutes for any
questions.
Kia ora. Yeah, my name's Rimu. Thank you, committee, for the
opportunity to speak to you today.
I know that you've heard a lot of submissions already, and I don't want to lecture
at you. Instead, I'd ask that you reflect on some of
the questions that I am presenting you with now.
If you fundamentally believe that someone who has nowhere else
to sleep but the street deserves to be punished, I'm not sure how I can change your
mind on that. But I'm going to try, because
this amendment is outrageous,
and I vehemently oppose it, and I really want you to
understand why.
Do you believe that going to work with a sore
back is virtuous? That it would make you a good worker,
a hardworking person? Yeah?
Okay. What happens when the repeated pressure makes the
disc slip,
and you end up hurting the nerves in your back?
And your sick leave runs out because you're still in incredible pain and you can't
walk,
and your job fires you. Which, because of the Employment Leave Bill,
they now can.
Are you still a good worker?
What about when you're really difficult to be around because the pain is
uncontrolled, because the hospital keeps pushing back your appointment time
another six weeks, another four weeks,
and you fall down the stairs because your back is spasming, and you end up with a
brain injury that changes your personality completely, but all
ED can do is discharge you with a prescription for codeine and rest because they're
code red for the second time in 24 hours.
Are you still virtuous when your relationships
end and your friends stop coming by after the seventh, eighth, ninth
month of you being stuck in bed, miserable and in pain?
What about when your savings finally run dry and you can't pay your mortgage or
your car payments and you have to leave your rental home because the Residential
Tenancies Amendment made it legal for your landlord to
evict you with no cause?
Are you hardworking when you cannot make it to the MSD office for an
appointment because you don't have a wheelchair, you don't have a car anymore?
Are you still virtuous when you have no bed and no friends to let you crash on
their couch?
What about when the only thing you can get your hand on to dull the
pain is illegal, and the only way you can pay for food
or pain relief, or anything, is to ask people for money?
Are you still a good person when the society we've built
fails you at every step? At every
tipping point where there should've been a safety net to catch you, you're instead
pushed further and further into poverty.
I really hope your answer is yes. Because if you can see yourself in any
part of this story, whether that's because you have sciatica that you're gritting
your teeth through, or you don't have private health insurance and you
rely on the public health system for appointments with specialists,
it's as easy for you as it is for any of us to end up on the street,
sleeping rough and without the people who loved you, care for you.
You might be wondering what all this story has to do with the bill.
So let me say it really clearly now.
This bill seeks to criminalize, by stealth, having nowhere
to sleep and no one to support you.
If it passes, it would make it a criminal offense
for you to beg or sleep rough by proxy
because it makes it illegal for you to be caught doing so, and for you to access
the public space that was in, again, within a 24-hour
period.
Now, the Minister for Justice himself has described these move on orders as to
deal with those who refuse to take up extra help.
But in the 330 OIA release pages I read last night, there was
no evidence that there's any number of people who are refusing support
services. I repeat, no evidence.
In fact, the move on
orders regime were disavowed by the few government agencies that the
minister did choose to consult with, whether that's the Ministry of Justice,
including its offenses and penalty vetting team, Oranga
Tamariki,
Housing and Urban Development, Ministry of Social Development, the
police, and just as a by the by,
the minister also included the rough sleeping section entirely without
any consultation from any ministry or government
agency.
So actually, it sounds like the move on orders, you
want them to be used as a punishment.
The minister has said if you're told to move on and you go up the road and you
start doing the same behaviors again, well, then you'll be subject to another move
on order until the message gets through that society doesn't tolerate
these activities. Activities like what? Having a disability?
Living in a country that's dismantled its social security net?
How is any of that an individual's fault?
Move on orders are formally issued notices that go on your
record, and non-compliance is a Category 2
offense, just like careless driving
resulting in death. I want to make sure you understand that by setting the
penalty at three months imprisonment or a $2,000 fine,
it implies that the government believes that returning to an area designated in a
move on order for disorderly or disruptive behavior in a public place is
more serious than other category 2 offenses in public
places which have way lower penalties, like throwing
fireworks at a person or two people beating each other
up. Existing passively in a public
place
or returning to it when you're told to leave because you engaged in legal
behavior like begging or rough sleeping,
that's not reasonable grounds to charge someone with an offense.
The Summary Offenses Act already covers many of the behaviors listed in this
amendment, so the duplication of laws is
bad lawmaking.
I beseech you, read the reports and the briefings by the ministries I've mentioned
before you make any decisions, recommend the bill is abandoned,
and write a report back why.
It's not going to improve economic outcomes for retailers.
The evidence is there. It won't decrease social harm experienced by
workers. The evidence is there. And it won't stop
people from doing stuff that annoys you or you think looks
ugly. Please abandon this bill.
Thank you.
Thank you, Rimu, and thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
That is the full five minutes for your allocation of time, but we do
appreciate both your written and oral submission, so thank you.
Okay, members, we now come to Vee Bloom, who's going to be presenting to us.
Hey, Vee. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We've got your written submission. We have read it.
We've got you down for five minutes.
Just leave some time at the end for questions, but over to you.
Kia ora. I will do my best.
I was very privileged. My parents owned our own home, and we always had food.
I grew up in the same house from the time I learned to walk until I was strong
enough to run away. I was probably the most privileged kid at the
pedophile ring that my father took me to.
Remember that while you listen to how hard it has been for me to access housing and
healthcare, because most of the kids who were raped alongside me and the adults
who still find themselves homeless today have had much less privilege than I
had. They have never known stable housing and can never forget
days and weeks going without food.
My white skin did not get beaten half as much as my Brown friends.
I don't get profiled or harassed by police.
Hey, Pakeha, I've never had to face the institutionalized racism that is
woven into our schools, our welfare, and our healthcare systems.
I saw the kind faces of those systems, and still, they almost killed me.
ACC cut off support just weeks after I had been raped for the last time.
For months, while I was searching for a flat, I had no place to live.
I survived because friends let me sleep on their couches.
That's what homelessness looks like for women predominantly, because it is much
more dangerous for us out there on the streets.
I found a place. I was lucky. I found a place within four months, whereas I've
talked to one Black friend who was searching for four years.
I grew up middle class, so I have a law degree, and so I
knew when our landlord kept showing up without notice that I could tell him
our tenancy rights. I knew his attempts to threaten us with photos he'd
taken of my flatmate's bong were not going to land either of us white females in
prison.
We had to leave that house in a rush after being sick for months.
We discovered mushrooms and mold growing from the ceiling.
And I could speak the legal English we needed to get through tenancy tribunal,
but that privilege only helped us get back a fraction of the rent we'd lost.
It did not help us find safe, healthy, long-term housing.
Again, we were privileged to have middle-class friends who already had housing
that could accommodate us, but it strained those relationships.
You've got to understand that many people on the streets would rather sleep rough
than feel like a burden to their friends and family.
And you've got to understand that many people do not have
families like you.
The most dangerous place for me to live was with my family, and the same is true
for countless survivors of domestic violence and sexual abuse who would rather
rough it on the streets than go home.
New Zealand has one of the worst rates of child sexual abuse in the OECD countries,
and still, we know that 92% of sexual assaults aren't even
reported. We have absolutely no idea how many
children were abused in pedophile rings like the one my father took me to,
let alone how many adult survivors are sleeping rough still suffering with the
consequences.
During the 11 years that my father took me to that place, I saw thousands of kids
pass through it, yet I have met only two adult survivors who've trusted me enough
to talk about it, because we survive by keeping quiet.
So I can't tell you exactly how many rough sleepers have escaped from abuse, but I
can tell you that every single one of them will be harmed profoundly by this
bill. Most of them can't talk about it, especially not the
ones who are just escaping, kids who are aging out of the pedophile rings
right now. These move-on orders would apply to them.
14-year-olds who have just grown strong enough to fight back against their abusive
father or 16-year-olds who are just having sex for the first time and
realizing that what their mother called their special time was actually rape.
Where do you think they should move on to?
If you were them, would you rather go back home and get raped again or sleep
rough on the streets?
Next time you hear somebody say homelessness is a choice, I want you to tell them
about these kids and the choices that they are facing, abuse
or homelessness, because that's the lived reality,
not just for survivors of pedophile rings, not just for survivors of
sexual abuse, but anybody who's impacted by domestic
violence, which we know is rampant in this country.
Should they stay with the violence they know at home or risk being moved into the
violence of prisons? If you can have compassion for these kids,
please do not hear this and simply raise the age from 14, because
life does not get suddenly easier at 18.
There is no age at which we are free from the effects of this trauma, especially
not in a society that continually compounds them and ignores them and
blames us for them. Not when ACC
re-traumatizes us and leaves us out in the cold.
Not when our justice system leaves 90% of rapists free to assault us
again and then locks up our tane who are willing to defend us.
I'm not asking you to fix these systematic justices today that create
homelessness. I'm not even asking you to do anything to help us.
I'm asking you not to make it 100 times harder for us to survive.
I'm asking you not to make it worse, and this bill will only make it
worse. I have seen friends after they've just come out from prison, just for
a night, and they're never better off for it.
They are more traumatized, and they are more tightly wound, and they are more
likely to react aggressively.
If you give more people who already feel worthless
more proof that the world does not care about them, you're going to get more
violence, not less. If there's any time, I will take questions.
Thank you, Vee. I just want to thank you for your bravery and for coming and
speaking with us this afternoon, and for sharing your story as well,
alongside the submission that you've presented to us. So thank you.
It doesn't look like we do have any questions from any of the members, but we're
just really grateful for your presentation and the written submission you've made
as well. So thank you very much.
Have I got a moment to add one extra point then?
Yes, absolutely.
I just want to speak to
question how many actual people who've experienced
homelessness you're hearing from in all of these submissions, because it's been
really hard to get anybody else to feel like there's any
point in talking to you,
because they already feel hopeless.
And I think if you're going to be making laws about people's lives, you need to
understand what their lives are. And you can't do that if you're not
talking to them, because you don't know the specific challenges that
we face. Even if housing had got the perfect place for
me, if my next door neighbor had even looked like my dad,
I wouldn't have been able to sleep there.
If they'd said, "Oh, I knew your dad at school," I would've run.
I would've been out of that whole area and
never told anyone.
You have to talk to the people
who the laws that you're making are affecting,
and I don't see that their voices are being heard in this process.
Thanks, Vee. We have heard from
a very diverse range of submitters.
This is only day two of us hearing submissions.
We're still hearing submissions on Tuesday and Wednesday of next week as well on
the bill. But we have heard from a vast range of different
people on the bill.
We obviously just take the submitters that submit on the legislation when we
listen to submissions,
which is open to everybody to do. But appreciate that-
Yeah, that's what I mean, though. The submissions process isn't open to everybody.
It's been shortened, and it's already in a
process that is not accessible to huge portions of the
population if they don't have access to phones or computers or an
understanding of the legal system.
Vee, many of us agree with you.
Understand.
Thank you, Vee. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We're going to come to our next submitter, which is from the Coalition to End
Women's Homelessness, which is Victoria
and Amanda.
And Wendy, I believe.
Wendy won't be joining us, just Victoria and Amanda today.
So thank you to the chair and to the members of the committee.
We appreciate you and your time. And I just want to acknowledge Vee
before us and her bravery, too, because much of what Vee spoke about, we
will be reflecting in our submission.
So my name is Vic, and I am the co-lead of the
Coalition to End Women's Homelessness, alongside Dr.
Cathy Irwin. I'm joined by our Collective Impact lead, Amanda
Kelly, and the coalition includes Dr.
Jo Cribb, who is the chair of the Wellington Homeless Women's Trust, Helen
Robinson, the Auckland City Missioner, Carolyn Hidewini, who leads Te
Whare Tīāki Porirua Maori Women's Refuge, and also
Jill Hawkey, who leads the Christchurch Methodist Mission.
What brought us together three years ago to start the coalition was a
recognition that there is a complete void of
policy and funding response to the specific needs of women
when it comes to homelessness.
We have been funded and supported to
undertake and commission research to work with the sector
to strengthen their practice in response to women's
homelessness and to advocate for change.
And it's on that last point that we are here
today. We're submitting because of the insight and
expertise of our colleagues, and also of the people with
lived experience who have shared their stories with us
through the providers on the frontline, the outreach services, and
also our research. Our initial research included the stories of
37 women who have experienced homelessness.
We are also here because we believe that we, as New Zealanders, must look to our
best and strongest instincts for care and
manaakitanga in order to end homelessness.
And it is our firm belief that the Move On orders, as they are
proposed, represent anything but that
best instinct. I'll hand to Amanda to talk you through
our submission.
Kia ora koutou. Ko Amanda Kelly toku ingoa, and I work as
Collective Impact lead at the Coalition to End Women's Homelessness.
Thank you, Vic. From a gendered perspective, we are extremely
concerned about how this proposed bill will impact women
experiencing homelessness, in particular wahine Maori, who
make up around one third of the 57,000 women
who are homeless across this country.
We are also deeply concerned about the impact that this will have
on their children and young people, as young as
14 years of age. And for children and young people, being on the
street is the consequence of circumstances that is way
beyond their control.
Our research tells us that women experience homelessness
very differently. They are extremely vulnerable, and they are
often less visible, and they have survival
mechanisms like we just heard in the previous submission from
Bea.
We are concerned that move-on orders risk making women's homelessness
even more invisible by pushing women to the
margins rather than bringing women closer to the support
and safety they may need.
Move-on orders may disrupt trusted relationships and connections with
key outreach workers, reduce access to vital healthcare
and housing services, increase isolation, and force
women and children into more dangerous and harmful situations.
I want to take a moment to acknowledge Wendy Proffitt
and her late daughter, Caitlin, whose story was shared
this week by RNZ.
Caitlin's heartbreaking story reminds us that
housing is the foundation of health, wellbeing, safety, and
connection, and of the devastating consequences
when systems that are actually in place to support
people fail the people that they're there to support.
When people lose access to stable housing, the impacts are felt across
every aspect of their lives, and that is why homelessness must
be addressed as a housing, health, and wellbeing issue, and
not as a public order issue. Those connections to
health, housing, and social services are vital
lifelines to get people like Caitlin the support that they
need.
This bill prioritizes enforcement over care,
displacement over housing, and punishment over prevention.
This is actually about people's lives, their dignity, their safety,
their health, and their right to belong.
It's about someone's daughter, someone's sister, auntie, mother, or
grandmother.
On these grounds, we respectfully ask the committee to reconsider
and withdraw this bill in its entirety, and instead, we urge the
government to focus on the long-term solutions that will end women's
homelessness.
Thank
you, Amanda and Victoria.
I will now look to see if there are members that have questions for you both.
Doesn't appear to be the case. That is no reflection on the quality of your
submission. I just want to reassure you on that fact, and we thank you both for
joining us this afternoon, and for the written submission that you've made on the
bill as well. So thank you very much.
Thank you. Thanks for the opportunity.
Thank you, Victoria. Thanks, Amanda. Thank you both.
Okay, members, we don't have any further submitters who are online now, so we're
going to take a break till 3:00 p.m. If you can come back online then, please.
All right, members, welcome back.
Thank you for joining us. Ruth, great to have you with us,
and thank you for being patient. We've got Ruth from People Against Prisons
Aotearoa, who's our next submitter. Ruth, we have read your submission.
We've got you for 10 minutes and just leave a little bit of time at the end for
questions. Over to you.
Yeah, that's good. Thanks. First of all, just make sure can you see and hear me
okay?
Fabulous.
Yeah, no problem. I know you all need a break.
It's long hearings,
and everyone's human, so I will get into it. Tena koutou katoa.
I'm Ruth, and I'm submitting on behalf of People Against Prisons
Aotearoa.
We are a prison abolitionist organization working for a safer,
fairer Aotearoa. Thank you for having me.
This is actually my fourth time submitting to select committee on behalf of PAPA
and my second time submitting to the Justice Committee.
So today, I'm just going to highlight a few parts of our full submission,
which you have,
and focus on how this bill would criminalize
poverty and homelessness and how it would cause disproportionate
harm to Maori, constituting a breach of the
Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
There's been obviously a fair amount in the media lately, so I'm confident that
PAPA is not alone in our views on rejecting this bill, especially in a
time of increasing cost of living, with more and more people
experiencing periods of homelessness.
This bill could potentially bring an even larger portion of our community into
contact with the justice system, and that is not an outcome that will improve the
quality of life for people in Aotearoa, New Zealand.
So we urge the committee to reject the bill in full, and the
two topics that I'll just focus a little bit more on are firstly, the
criminalization of poverty, which this bill sets up.
It explicitly lists rough sleeping, setting up makeshift shelters,
and begging as grounds for issuing a move on order.
These are not crimes. They are actual invisible consequences
of poverty, of housing insecurity, and the failure of our
country to adequately resource social services.
So to respond to these with police powers, with detention, and the
threat or actuality of imprisonment is misguided, and it will
only decrease the
living situation of our already most vulnerable.
It will also convey a message to the young people of our country that it
is a crime to be poor. That's not something that we believe in,
and that's not something we want to see for Aotearoa.
This would be a form of moral failing.
In addition to
funneling more people into a justice system which causes harm, it would also be a
moral failing of our society to extend protection to our
most vulnerable.
So it's no secret that we're in a housing crisis and thousands of people
are without stable homes. And so many of those who sleep rough do so because they
have no alternative. But this bill does not come together with
any support for housing, mental health support, drug and
alcohol treatment, none of the things that would actually address these primary or
secondary causes of homelessness.
Instead, it gives police the power to move people on,
just forcing them out of sight without doing anything
additional to protect them.
So these issues require a different instrument than this bill.
This bill does nothing to resolve the underlying causes.
It's stated just this week by the head of the Police Association,
emphasizing that the bill would simply put police in the role of managing the
effects of homelessness, addiction, and mental health.
This is classic ambulance at the bottom of a cliff, stuff with far
too little being done in the system to keep people from falling off the cliff in
the first place.
The response of Justice Minister Paul Goldsmith to some of the comments this
week shows his woeful under-education about the basic
facts of sleeping rough and homelessness.
His vague statements about the Auckland City Mission, which are negated by mission
staff, display total ignorance of the basic facts of how
homelessness manifests in our cities, especially This feels like
unaccountable lawmaking, throwing a band-aid fix at a complex social problem
rather than looking and addressing its underlying causes.
And all it will do is increase the already growing prison populations.
It will put more people with serious vulnerabilities and mental health challenges
into prisons, a place where they will receive much more harm than
help, which is something we know already.
So in short, this part of the bill, the bill itself reads like a chapter in a
dystopian novel, a weak attempt to protect
those with means
from having to face and encounter the homelessness that is all
around us, rather than contributing to resolving challenges like housing
scarcity and an underfunded public health system.
So our second issue I'll cover briefly is a treaty breach.
By targeting homeless where Maori are already significantly
over-represented in statistics.
They make up roughly 31% of people experiencing
housing deprivation, although they're only 17% of the
population. This over-representation tells us that the
housing system, and by association, the
population experiencing homelessness, is not an equitable
situation, and the bill would simply condone these inequalities, increase the
number of Maori in the justice system,
in prison, or who've had contact with processes in the justice system
as a result of precarious and unstable housing options.
So in closing, we call on the committee to reject the bill in full.
It would take us closer as a country to a dystopian future where we fail
to look after our most vulnerable.
Instead, we would be criminalizing them for their position,
which is itself a result of institutional inequality and
a severe housing crisis. We want Aotearoa, New Zealand, to be a place where people
are looked after when they're in need, not thrown into prison to become part of a
justice system we already know causes more harm than anything.
Thank you for your time. I'm happy to answer any questions that I'm able to.
Thank you, Ruth, and thank you for your submission this afternoon.
I'll just see if members have questions.
We've got a question from Francisco Hernandez.
Thank you, Chair.
You earlier referred to in your submission, you referred to
effective solutions that would actually go to
the heart of addressing the housing crisis.
What are those instead of this proposal?
Well, what I should say is that PAPA is a prison
abolitionist organization. So for us, our focus is really on
rehabilitation and community solutions.
We would defer to housing experts at the Ministry of
Housing,
or the new MSIRT, and other housing justice groups around
the country for what the best policy solutions are for housing.
But there's no shortage of them. They're out there, and they've been
put forward. So looking at building more social housing,
for example, and more transitional housing, as well as weaving
that in with rehabilitative efforts.
So people who
are experiencing homelessness and/or who have harmed
others,
their healing happens best when they have rehabilitation and community and family
support around them. There are a number of examples around the country doing
that, and there are plenty more opportunities to do more of
that.
Fantastic, Ruth. Well, thank you very much for your submission and your time this
afternoon as well. We appreciate it.
All right. Thank you very much. Ka kite.
All right, our next submitter is Talia.
Hi.
Hello. Thank you for joining us this afternoon. We've read your written submission.
We've got you down for five minutes.
Mm-hmm.
If you can just leave a little bit of time at the end for questions, please.
So my name is Talia, and I have a background in psychology.
I've worked in the social work field as a volunteer counselor and support worker,
and now I'm in education as a psychology and science teacher.
So in my submission, I wrote about how New Zealand's homeless numbers have been
increasing.
This year it was announced that our homeless rates have reached an all-time high,
and this is expected to continue increasing, which isn't entirely surprising
given that New Zealand has reached milestones in achieving lowest wage growth,
significant increases in living costs, and the lowest number of employment
opportunities in years. The groups represented in New Zealand's homeless
population also indicate major systemic issues, just like Ruth was saying.
So firstly, 50% of our homeless population is under 25.
This is partly to do with youth having nowhere to go once aging out of Oranga
Tamariki's care, but it's also to do with youth having the least amount of
access to financial support and emergency housing.
Secondly, the number of retirees and elderly people that are homeless is predicted
to increase based on increasing living costs compared to superannuation and lack of
home ownership. And thirdly, compared to the OECD, we have one of the
highest rates of female homelessness, which is just over 50%, which is very
unusual.
The major issue with this bill is that it doesn't address the issues contributing
to homelessness. This bill punishes people who the system has failed and will
contribute to further discrimination, reinforcing the homeless cycle,
and increasing the cost to the taxpayer.
This is based on evidence from America and European countries which introduced
similar policies. So here are some examples of consequences from similar
policy overseas. So the policy wording, which allows police to make
assumptions about intention, like assuming that someone is going to sleep or beg,
leads to discrimination based on appearance.
So even if someone's just passing through with their belongings, they could be
accused of intending to sleep nearby and be asked to leave.
New Zealand already has policy that covers antisocial behavior, so creating
legislation to move people that are purely sheltering in the city is highly
discriminatory, and it's not based on risk or danger to the public.
Also, the CBD contains most of the Ministry of Social Development buildings.
So this means that people could be moved on from the city centers even if they're
trying to access assistance. MSD support, like job seekers, requires
people to meet obligations like meetings.
So preventing homeless people from accessing city centers where the
MSD centers are is creating another barrier for these people.
People who already have very little may need to abandon their belongings to avoid
the risk of being profiled. And in America, one of the most commonly lost
belongings was identification like passports, and this was creating another
barrier to things like employment, accessing benefits, and healthcare.
Overseas police found that verbal warnings were really ineffective as there wasn't
a consequence. Homeless people couldn't pay the fine, so this led to
increased arrests. This took police and the court's time away from more serious
crime, which led to increased costs due to having more court cases
and more people in prison. Criminal charges meant employment was harder to
get, and some people who are homeless and employed meant that the charges could
impact their employment already.
This is reinforcing the cycle of homelessness.
According to stats from 2016, each homeless person costs about
65,000 in police and healthcare costs.
In 2016, it cost 15,000 to house someone, so it's
significantly cheaper to house someone.
In 2025, it cost 49,000 for 90 days in prison,
and this is the estimated time for people who cannot pay the fine.
Homeless people also have increased risk of health and psychological problems due
to the stress of living on the street, and exposure to things like the elements,
like the wind. So homeless people are also targets of assault and
harassment, and given our high numbers of youth and female
homeless individuals, this is an even more vulnerable group.
CBD is safer for these people, as it's safety in numbers.
There's surveillance, there's higher police presence, and buildings are also
providing shelter from things like wind.
So skin infections are a really common health risk in people who are
homeless. There are also hygiene facilities like public toilets.
So being moved on from these centers means it's harder to keep people safe,
especially homeless people, because there's less police presence.
You can't monitor the behavior. They're also exposed to the elements.
Reports from overseas also stated that scattering homeless people meant that you
couldn't warn them around weather warnings like cold snaps.
This led to increased risk.
People didn't trust the system, they didn't trust the police, which led to more
aggression and stress and that kind of thing, because this is just incredibly
unstable and stressful if there's no place to stay safe.
So essentially,
because it's harder for social workers to contact people as well, they're being
further isolated, they've got increased risks.
This is damaging their health and their psychological wellbeing.
This further increases our healthcare costs because it increases the number
of people presenting at the emergency department.
Overseas says that criminal legislation, when we change it, we
also need to change our social legislation as well together.
So this means addressing those issues that are contributing to
homelessness.
So for instance, Norway, they reduced their number of homeless people by having a
housing first policy, which as Ruth was saying, basically
increasing the number of houses available to people who are homeless,
especially permanent housing.
Now, thanks, Talia. We do have only 30-odd seconds left, so if you've got any
final remarks, now would be the time.
Yeah. Essentially, this bill should not be occurring because it's highly
discriminatory.
If this bill were to proceed, there really needs to be social legislation
alongside it. So those issues that are contributing to homelessness
need to be addressed, otherwise it's just flat out discrimination.
Especially given the changes to the MSD recently with KPIs and that kind of
thing. We're just punishing people who the system is not supporting.
Fantastic. Well, thank you so much for joining us this afternoon, and for your
written submission as well. You've done a great job.
No problem.
And yeah, thank you very much.
Awesome. Thanks.
Thanks, Talia.
Okay, our next submitter is going to be the New Zealand Outdoors and Freedom Party.
We're going to have Sue Gray who's going to be joining us.
Hello, can you see me and hear me?
We can hear you, Sue. There we go. We can see you now too.
Oh, fantastic.
Fantastic. Thank you.
Thanks, Harry.
Thanks for joining us this afternoon. We have read your written submission.
You're down for 10 minutes. If you can just leave some time at the end for
questions.
Thank you very much. Look, thank you first for the opportunity to be heard today.
I'm a lawyer specializing in human rights and other complex emerging
issues. The New Zealand Outdoors and Freedom Party is in
the process of changing its name to the Freedom Party, so you may
see some other information from us.
But we've got a long history of submitting on issues
that undermine fundamental human rights,
and which undermine the rights of New Zealanders, and
particularly where there's discrimination or unfair treatment, we're
strongly opposed to any law change which may
undermine these rights, whether it's the intention of the law change or not.
So, we support much of what the previous submitters
said about the discrimination. But our particular
concern is the example from the Parliament
occupation back in February and March 2022,
when the police used basically a
de facto version of that
move on orders without having the law at the time, but they
effectively, it did move people along, a lot of people
along, and it showed a
lack of judgment, and I'd have to say a lack of
humanity, in the way the New Zealand police treated members
of the public.
And it's really concerning to give more powers
to an entity
that
currently has lost a lot of respect for the public.
The police need social license to operate
effectively,
and
they've lost social license because of the conduct of the prior
deputy commissioner, the prior commissioner, and the
ongoing investigations, and now the current Commissioner of Police is under
investigation.
And at that type of situation, we should not
be giving more ad hoc powers to the police.
We should be
Principled in what we do. We should be, as
a country, respecting fundamental human rights,
and we should be working out why people are dropping out of the
system and struggling with the system, rather
than punishing those who do stand up and
do behave a bit differently from everybody else.
So we understand that there are some intended
protections in the bill, but we don't
believe that the bill is justified at all in the first place.
And we believe that the move
on orders is a slippery slope,
and an unnecessary slippery slope, which will take
us further away from public trust in government,
further away from public trust in the police, and it gives
the police the opportunity to pick on people just
because they're different, they're doing something a bit different, they're in a
different place. We understand that it's intended
to have some protections for fundamental rights, but in
practice, there's been a long history
of lack of respect of human rights, even when the New Zealand Bill of
Rights is written into our law.
So
it's
not a necessary law,
and it goes against the thread of what needs to be done in the
current regime,
and the consequences of the police conduct over the last few years
from the perspective of the public, and we deal with the public a lot, from the
perspective of the public, the New Zealand police
have clearly lost social license.
They need to work with the community
to regain trust and confidence.
This bill is one of a whole series of bills.
We have the random
drug testing bill that gives the police more powers.
We have had an enormous amount of public
engagement
on our posts on that bill because the public don't
trust the establishment.
And again, with the other bills which take
away public powers. So the objective of the New Zealand
Outdoors and Freedom Party is to empower the people,
not empower the system.
And it's one of the things about the New Zealand Bill of Rights.
It's one of the limited amount of legislation that we have in New Zealand that is
supposed to empower the people
against the establishment. Whereas what is
happening with all these ad hoc law reforms is the
people are getting further and further disempowered, and
the legislation that we do have is being fritted
away step by step. So we've been through the period with the
mandates. We've been through
all of these other challenges. We're now facing the
possible restrictions from the bird flu.
Whether or not that's a proportionate, justified response will be
another question.
But anything that takes away these rights is a
concern to the Outdoors and Freedom Party.
And it's such a serious situation that
my former leader and I wrote this book, "Freedom Village," about what
happened at
Parliament at the end, where Alan ended up in hospital for
a week getting a replacement hip after he was
assaulted by the police when
it was really an attempt by them to use a move-on type power
against the people. I haven't been able to find any lawful power for the
police to do what they did on that day, on the 2nd of March
2022.
But it actually met the definition of a riot
against the public. That was the police conduct at 6:00 in the morning.
So
we need to have a really good look. We need to have a
big-picture look at what kind of place we
want New Zealand to be,
and
what kind of society do we want. What
rights do we want our people to have?
Do we want our people to enjoy the fundamental
rights, the freedom of movement, the freedom of expression, the
freedom to assemble, all of those rights that are written into our New Zealand Bill
of Rights Act? Because
if those rights are to mean something, if the New Zealand Bill of
Rights is indeed important, if it does
matter, we cannot have these ad hoc
laws undermining it.
And what happens is we create a
group of people who are the least able to defend
themselves. They're the least able to afford legal advice.
They're the least able to deal with the paperwork,
with the bullying, with the discrimination.
And we actually create, if we're not careful, more of the very problem
that we are trying to overcome.
So I've had a big week preparing some court injunctions and things.
I don't have much more that I need to submit today, but I'm very happy
to provide any answers to any questions you may have
about this.
Thank you, Sue. I will just look to see if there are members that have questions
for you.
Doesn't appear to be any, but we thank you very much for your submission.
All the best with the change of your name as well.
Thank you very much. It's appreciated.
Thanks, Sue.
Thank you for your time today.
Have a good afternoon. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Goodbye.
Okay, our next submitter is going to be Mana Mokopuna, and we've
got the Children's Commissioner, Claire Achermann, who's going to be presenting to
us.
Hi, Claire. Thank you for joining us this afternoon. We've read your submission.
You've got 10 minutes, and if you can just leave some time at the end for questions
Tena koutou katoa, e ngā mema o te komiti o te Pāremata.
Nei au e mihi atu ki a koutou i pohiri
mai ki a hau ki te whakawhānui i taku
tapatanga ki tēnei pire.
Ko Claire Achmad tōku ingoa. Ko ahau te Kaikomihana mō ngā
Tamariki Mokopuna o Aotearoa. I'm Claire Achmad, I'm the
Children's Commissioner, the independent statutory advocate for all
children in New Zealand under the age of 18, and all children and
young people under the age of 25 who have been in or who are in the
care of the state. And I'm supported in my work by my team at Mana
Mokopuna Children's Commissioner.
I'd hoped to have some young people alongside me today to
speak to this bill. As you know, it's always my intention as Children's
Commissioner to share my platform with the children and young people who
I serve and advocate for.
I think it's important that they get to directly share their views with you.
Unfortunately, that hasn't been possible today.
However, it's not just my responsibility to hear the voices of
children and young people. It is yours as well.
The policy and legislation decisions of the government and of our
parliament, like the bill that I am here to oppose today,
have a significant and direct impact on the daily lives of
mokopuna, our children and young people, and on their rights, their interests,
and their futures. So it's critical that both you as a
committee and each of you individually take seriously your
responsibility to directly hear from children and young people, and
I am disappointed that this has not happened to the extent that
I would have liked to have seen on this bill.
As Children's Commissioner, I oppose the Summary Offences
Amendment Bill because it lacks logic, it's unnecessary,
it will generate harm to children and young people, and frankly,
it is offensive, especially from a human rights and
children's rights perspective.
You have my written submission, which goes into more detail.
Today, I want to highlight the key reasons for my opposition to this
bill from a children's rights perspective.
To begin with, this bill lacks logic.
The people moved on, swept out of sight by this bill, they are
not a problem. They are our brothers, our sisters, our
uncles, our aunts, and some of them are children.
They are people.
Instead of contending with this bill, I think that this House
would do much better to use its time to focus on
urgently solving how to get every single one of these
people who are living on our streets a hot meal and a roof over their
head today, to uphold their human rights in action, and to
lift children and young people out of poverty, ensuring that
everyone in this country has an adequate standard of living
consistent with their fundamental human dignity.
No part of our response to homeless children and young people
should include harsh, unrealistic, dismissive, or
punitive action like this bill does.
These are dear children and young people.
We should be cherishing them. We should be seeking to uphold
their rights and prevent them from being on the streets in the first
place.
We need to recognize that living on the street, it is not a crime.
If young people are on our streets and have struggles with mental health, that is
not a crime.
Their complex trauma is not a crime.
These things require our kindness and our humanity.
This bill, proposing to sweep people, including children
and young people, out of sight, is simply
cruel. The
fact that the government and this House is even considering criminalizing
people in this way is shameful.
When a young person is sleeping on the street, our first question
should be, "How can we help you?" Not, "How can we move
them on somewhere else?"
In my role as Children's Commissioner, children and young people are my
priority. The cherished young people who stand to
be impacted by this bill, they require wraparound
support of government and of you, not a
punitive justice response.
This bill does absolutely nothing to bolster the
supports that are so obviously going to be the only effective
solution for their specific needs.
And it also does nothing to incentivize the community
to respond with kindness or support, which is ultimately what
children and young people always need, and especially these most vulnerable
children and young people living in severe housing deprivation or
who are feeling excluded and isolated from our society.
Instead, this bill will effectively criminalize homelessness and
poverty. It will waste police resource that's needed elsewhere, and
it will increase exposure to further harm for homeless
mokopuna. We also need to be really honest about who
will feel the impact of this bill the most.
And we know it will disproportionately affect mokopuna Māori,
Māori whānau, and young people who are leaving our state care
system.
It will also permit collection of young people's personal data when
no offense has been committed. This will be an unwarranted
breach of their rights, and it should not be encoded in our law.
This bill is focused on
managing the visibility of homelessness and begging in public
spaces rather than addressing the underlying causes, which are
so well known to us: poverty, housing deprivation, family
instability, and inadequate support services.
It is proposing measures that are punitive, which will be
ineffective And are likely to increase harm to mokopuna who are
homeless by criminalizing their personal circumstances.
And the solution that this bill is offering, it is in no way
relevant to the problem. Perversely, it is likely to
increase the difficulties particularly faced by homeless young
people and drive them further away from the support that they so
desperately need.
Article 27 of the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, it could
not be clearer. Every child has the right
to an adequate standard of living, for their
physical, mental, spiritual, moral, and social development.
And states parties shall, in the case where need is
required, provide material assistance and support
programs, particularly with regard to nutrition, clothing, and
housing. This makes absolutely clear what the state's
task is when it comes to children and young people who will be
affected by this bill, and these duties and obligations are not
only clear under the CRC, the Children's Convention, but also
under Article Three of Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
To be absolutely clear, if passed, the Summary
Offences ,
Bill will have a negative and compounding impact on
some of our most vulnerable mokopuna.
We're at risk of punishing children for being homeless.
This is a welfare issue being treated as a justice issue.
Mokopuna experiencing homelessness often have complex needs
arising from poverty, family breakdown, poor health,
addiction, inadequate housing support, and transitions from
state care or youth justice systems.
Sweeping mokopuna away from some public places does
not resolve these issues at all. Instead, it is going to
displace vulnerable individuals to unfamiliar and less
likely safe environments where they will be vulnerable about being
complained about again if people are emboldened by such a
law, and then they will be swept away again. To where?
And where does this end?
This impact, if this bill is passed, will be compounding for
mokopuna, particularly those transitioning out of state care and
youth justice, noting that this group already
experience increased harm compared to their non-justice
or non-care experienced counterparts.
And further, I'm deeply concerned that creating move on
orders and enforcement powers will increase the likelihood of
vulnerable young people becoming involved in the criminal justice system.
We should be doing all we can to prevent mokopuna from
entering the criminal justice system because of how
detrimental it is to their lives, their
childhoods, and their lifetime outcomes.
I think we can all agree this is not the kind of country we
want to be. Instead, I advocate for stable,
secure, and healthy housing to be upheld as a
basic right for all mokopuna. They are all
entitled to this. They are all guaranteed to this.
Stable, secure, and healthy housing is the only logical
solution to the problem that this bill is seeking to address.
It is essential for improved wellbeing, education,
development, and health outcomes, and positive
participation for mokopuna in our society.
Nothing short of a comprehensive social policy
response to homelessness will do, and children and young people,
families and whanau must receive a specific focus
within that response. It must ensure increased
investment in social and community housing, improved
youth-specific housing services, earlier intervention and
support for vulnerable children and young people, more comprehensive
and more widely available mental health support for young
people, greater investment into Maori-led and culturally
grounded services, and stronger inclusion of children and young
people in the development of housing policy.
In closing, I want to reflect on my time sitting before
you as the Justice Committee over the last few years.
You may be aware that I have not been reappointed as Children's Commissioner.
During my two-and-a-half year term as Children's Commissioner, I have made over
a dozen oral submissions to your Justice Committee.
In almost every case, the bills I spoke to you
about overtly breached children's rights.
It is crystal clear to me that the government must do better to
uphold children's rights as it is duty bound to
do as a states party to the Children's Convention.
Continuing to pass laws that create breaches of
children's rights is a stain on New Zealand's history.
As a Justice Committee, I call on you to do much more,
say much more, achieve much more for our nation's
mokopuna and their rights. It is your duty
under the Children's Convention and Te Tiriti o Waitangi, and more
simply, as adults in positions of power and
decision-making influence.
I am disappointed that my last time speaking to you on a
bill is on a bill that is so offensive
to the rights of children and young people, and those who are most
vulnerable in our communities.
The right choice before you as a committee is to
not let this bill go any further.
Mm.
During my time as Children's Commissioner, I have held the highest
aspirations for all children in our country.
They should all be living their best lives, experiencing all of their
rights at all times, under all circumstances.
And so, as I come to the end of my tenure as Children's Commissioner,
this is the wero, the challenge that I lay down before you
today Kia ora koutou.
Thank you, Claire. Thank you very much for your submission this afternoon
and for being before us, and also your written submission and your work over the
last couple of years as well. We do appreciate it.
Thank you, Claire. You've been an amazing submitter.
You've done great work in advocating for children and against all
odds.
I agree. Thank you so much for all--
Right, our next submitter is Landa
van de Berg, and we'll just bring them up in front of us.
Great. There you are. Fantastic. You've got five minutes.
We have read your written submission, but if you'd just leave a little bit of time
at the end for questions.
Yeah. Thank you, and tena koutou
katoa. Ko Landa toku ingoa.
Thank you for opening this space for me to share some further thoughts
on my view that I strongly oppose this
particular bill.
But before doing so, I want to acknowledge my privilege, because I'm
speaking to you
from the safety of my warm and comfortable home, as you can see.
And I really want to acknowledge that we are speaking about folks
who will, yet again, tonight face another
winter night cold on the street.
And I know that you've already heard from so many experts in the
field, and I trust
that you will read the statistics, that you will read all the research.
So what I hope to do is speak from the position of
being a trauma therapist, a Buddhist meditation
teacher,
as well as, most importantly, just a human being,
a human being whose heart is crying.
Because I believe that when those move on orders would
be put in place,
that would be a genuine act of cruelty.
Now, as a trauma therapist, I'm witnessing
firsthand how, unfortunately, so many folks across Aotearoa,
as no doubt all of you know, are struggling with profound
trauma,
often intergenerational, caused by the lasting impact
of colonization.
And for many, I've witnessed that through
being impacted by trauma,
they suffer a whole range of mental health and physical health issues,
which then leads to genuine difficulties to live
a life, ongoing financial instability, and poverty.
And so for some of them, there's an ongoing risk of ending up on
the streets, and unfortunately for many of them, that becomes reality,
not because it's their choice,
but because they haven't got any alternatives.
Those folks are extremely vulnerable and I believe need
our support.
Now, at the beginning, I used this word
cruelty, and I know it's a big word, but I did so deliberately.
And based on my Buddhist practice, I want to invite
you for a moment.
I hope you want to come along to a short personal
reflection, a short contemplation,
letting go for just a minute of all the facts presented, the
pros, the cons, the worries.
So if you feel comfortable, perhaps
allow yourself to close your eyes for a moment
or just stare at your desk away from the
screen.
And I want to invite you to just take two deeper breaths and tune
into this body of yours present right here, right now.
And then for a moment, what I want to invite you to do is
just imagine
how it would be like for you
if you would have one of your loved ones living on the streets
right now.
Is it possible to tune into their experience being cold,
perhaps hungry,
fearful of being attacked?
And while this might be difficult just in a short moment,
is it possible for you to notice how your heart is responding?
Is there perhaps a glimmer of some trembling,
a contraction?
Do you notice some sadness or worry?
So if it was possible for you to tune into that,
I really want to point to the fact that this is the response of the
compassionate heart,
my heart
trembling with your suffering.
And I believe, I strongly believe that if we allow ourselves
to now and then tune into that innate capacity of
the human heart,
we can clearly see
that we need to follow the wisdom that comes through in all spiritual
traditions. Those in need deserve our
understanding, our compassion, our support.
So I want to end with a Buddhist quote that comes
straight from the classical texts,
and it goes like this:
"Just like a mother protects with her life her
child, her only child,
so with a boundless heart
should one cherish all living beings."
So may I please call on you decision-makers, and
all decision-makers,
to
allow yourself to be guided by your moral compass.
To listen to the potential trembling of your
human heart,
and allow yourself to tune into that,
and let that guide you in finding other solutions
for a problem that indeed exists, but
other solutions than cruelly treating our fellow human beings
who find themselves living on the street.
Thank you, Landa. Thank you very much for your submission this afternoon.
We have gone quite significantly over time, but I do appreciate you, both
your written submission and presenting to us this afternoon.
So thank you very much.
Thank you.
Okay, members, our next submitter is Rachel, who's just going to be coming online
now.
Hi, Rachel. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We've got you down for a five-minute submission. We have read your submission.
Please just leave some time at the end for questions.
Kia ora, Tom. Thank you very much. Sorry for not having my video up.
Some tech difficulties on my end, but thank you so much for letting me-
We can hear you nice and clearly.
Perfect. Thank you very much. So tena koutou katoa. I'm Rachel Doig.
Thank you for the committee for giving me this opportunity to speak.
I'd like to note first that although this is an individual submission, I do work in
the homelessness support sector, and have a research background in public
health, including a focus on youth homelessness.
So I work directly with the communities that would be most impacted should this
bill pass. Listen, I strongly oppose this bill on
the grounds that it will not achieve the aims it intends to, and will cause
significant harm to vulnerable members of our community.
By conflating begging and rough sleeping with disorderly
behavior, this piece of legislation will have unintended
harms to our homeless whanau. It might not criminalize homelessness
explicitly, but it will effectively do this through
criminalizing survival behaviors like situating yourself near a food
bank or support center.
I often find the easiest way to speak about homelessness is to consider the
pathways into homelessness, and the pathways out of it.
And as I've heard previous speakers today say, we know those pathways into
homelessness. We know they include poverty, untreated mental illness and
other health concerns, disconnect from support services, and our
increasingly unaffordable housing market.
On the opposite end, we know that affordable, appropriate housing, healthcare,
and addiction support really do work.
They are the keys to rehousing people.
And hey, while I think it's appropriate that we're all shocked and uncomfortable
with the rising rates of homelessness on our streets, I don't
really-
Hey, Rachel, I think we've just lost you there. You've just dropped out.
If you can still hear us.
All right. Members, we might have to move to the next submitter unfortunately.
I'm not quite-
Oh, sorry.
Oh, Rachel.
Sorry about that.
You are. There you are.
Am I there?
You're there.
Sorry about that. Apologies about that. The tech issues go on.
Yeah, I'll just come to my last bit. I won't take too much more time.
But I just wanted to say that it's really appropriate that we're
all shocked and uncomfortable that there's rising rates of homelessness, but
we really shouldn't be that surprised.
We know these pathways into homelessness, and right now they look more like
highways with many New Zealanders left out of our housing and welfare systems.
Given this, it would be really surprising to me if we were not seeing a rise in
homelessness. It's an unsurprising, if really awful,
outcome of what the system is looking like at the
moment. So with this in mind, I would really like to see us
work alongside our homeless whanau to support them into housing,
increase our affordable housing, increase our allocated
Housing First placements, and really meaningfully
address the causes of homelessness.
I'm glad to see that homelessness is being discussed in lounges and communities
around the motu at the moment, though it's sad it's this bill which has brought the
conversation to the table.
But let's not respond just by sending these people down the road.
I'd like to see the government discard this bill and respond to our homelessness
crisis head on. Nga mihi nui. Sorry about all the tech troubles.
Thank you for listening.
You're all good, Rachel. I'll just see if anyone's got a question.
We've got a question from Carl Bates.
Thanks very much, and thanks, Rachel.
Rachel, I was down at the City Mission in Whanganui at
7:45 this morning.
Yeah.
There was no one there in front of it this morning when I arrived, but a couple
of weeks back when I went down at a similar time, there was someone there.
The City Missioner and I sat down with him, had a cup of tea, and then the City
Missioner helped him out with some stuff that he needed.
Mm-hmm.
I cannot see how you think that this bill's going to
move
for the City Missioner, for example, here in Whanganui, to then want
to call the police, who are only 200 meters down the road, and say, "Come down and
issue this guy a move on order." That's not the situation that this is trying
to prevent. It's trying to prevent where
those
circumstances where individuals such as him choose rather to sit outside
a dairy and beg from people who are trying to go into that
dairy, and both affect their process and
the dairy sales. Interested in your comment.
Yeah, thank you. Thank you for that, Carl. I appreciate the comment.
No, that is a really good point. I think the situations I was thinking of, I should
say I'm based in Wellington, and in our CBD,
support services, businesses, everything is in really close
proximity. So my concern would be that someone that may have
been outside a
... small business or something to that effect where the police may have been
called would then be effectively banned from all the services in the
region that are in really close proximity.
So I'm certainly not suspecting that someone in the not-for-profit sector
would use that mechanism, but I'd be concerned that other businesses using it might
have flow-on impacts on that person.
Thank you, Rachel. That is our full allocation of time, I'm sorry.
But we appreciate your submission this afternoon and your written submission as
well.
Thank you very much.
Fantastic.
I'm sorry, Carl, I saw you did have a follow-up question, but
ruthless chair in here, got to stick to time.
Andrew is our next submitter. Andrew, great to see you this afternoon.
We have read your submission, got you down for five minutes if you can just leave
a little bit of time for questions.
Kia ora tātou.
First, a general question. Why is this
legislation proposed
and being continued with in the face of the overwhelming advice,
legal, social, housing-related, police-related,
welfare-related against it?
The aims put forward in the preamble to the bill
ensure the police are adequately equipped to address public
disorder,
increase the public's sense of safety, support urban centers and
economies.
As a smoke screen, it's also noticeable that
it does not talk about the
homelessness and
difficulties that people are having. It's totally unrelated to that.
The real reason for this legislation, I contend, is
so that people do not see the real and tragic evidence of
the government's failed housing and social support policies.
It is the wrong approach to suppress the evidence, the symptoms of a failed
housing and social support policies.
Fix the cause, not the symptom. Fix the cause, not
suppress the evidence.
It comes down to choices made. Choosing to follow the false
ideology that the government is like a household, which has a number of
implications. Choosing to direct resources away from housing
and social services to prisons, to defense, to supporting the already
wealthy. There are other choices that could be
made.
What should happen is this government should own up to
its creation of increasing homelessness and fully resource housing
first programs, not kick people when they are down.
Finally, let us remind ourselves of Article 25
(1) of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
It says, "Everyone has the right to a standard of living
adequate for the
health and wellbeing of himself and his family,
including food, clothing, housing, and medical care and
necessary social services, and the right to security
in the event of unemployment, sickness, disability, widowhood,
old age, or other lack of livelihood in circumstances
beyond
his control." The bill is totally inconsistent with this.
And we'd also just note that the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights is one of
those international relations triumphs of New Zealand, and
that it was a very active participant in developing it in the first place.
Kia motu.
Thanks, Andrew. I will look to see if there are any members that have a question
for you.
Doesn't appear to be the case. We're really grateful for you coming and joining us
this afternoon, and for your written submission to the bill as well.
Great. Okay, members, our next submitter is going to be Philippa.
Hello?
Hey, Philippa. Thank you for joining us this afternoon. Great to have you with us.
We've read your submission. We've got you down for five minutes, and if
you can just leave a little bit of time at the end for questions.
I'm not sure if you can hear me, but I can't hear you at all.
We can hear you.
I can't hear you.
So I'll just talk to a silent screen. If you can hear me, that's fine.
Kia ora. I'm Philippa Thompson Ng.
I am a social worker here in Wellington.
I support people with housing issues
day in and day out.
Most of the people that I work with are families, so they are more
likely to be what you would call the invisible homeless.
They're not the people who are on the street
and begging. So they're unlikely to be affected by these orders.
But what I see is that it's hard enough for these families
to get and maintain appropriate housing.
So therefore, it would be infinitely harder for someone
who already has a history of maybe addictions, maybe mental health
diagnoses, maybe prison time,
and who's already on the street to get and maintain that appropriate
housing. So we just have this
whole of system issue with
housing that needs to be urgently addressed, and
this move on order is just a Band-Aid on a gaping
wound that is our housing system at the moment, which is why I
am very strongly opposed to it.
And I've only listened to the last three submitters,
but what I'm hearing is that so many people are opposed to it.
I know the police have opposed it. Social services are opposing it.
And what I understand is that the police already have the power to deal
with disruptive behaviors. Being homeless
should not be a crime. We need
to-
Provide places of belonging for people.
As well as being a social worker, I'm also,
in a voluntary capacity, part of a community group that has
an open door dinner where people come who are homeless,
who might have
bad reputations elsewhere. But we very seldom have problems
with disruptive behaviors because
people are known, they belong, they're able to participate, able to
contribute.
And that's the society that I would love to see,
where there are places of belonging for people.
And the only other thing I'll add there is that I did some maths.
So
according to a Herald report that I read earlier
this year, the cost of keeping someone in prison is $552
a day.
The penalty for failing to move
on is three months in prison. So three months times
552 is $49,680
for three months.
So as a social worker, my salary is about $100,000.
So for two move-on orders, you could employ me full time to work with
just two people.
Or say you could have a counselor and a social worker work
with four people. A counselor, a social worker, and a budget advisor work
with six people. You get where I'm going with this, that the cost of putting people
in prison is by far the highest social housing
cost that you can pay.
Building houses, supporting people to get into houses
is a far cheaper solution, actually, in the long term.
Thank you. I'll stop there.
I would say thank you, but I don't think you can hear us.
I can't hear you. So if anybody's got any questions, but I don't have the time for
them.
I'm saying thank you. Thank you. All right, members,
the rest of you can hear me, so that's fine.
We'll thank Philippa, and we'll move on to our next submitter, which is Julie.
And if the clerks can maybe just say thank you to Philippa, and that we thank her
for her written and oral submission, please.
Hi, Julie.
Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
We've got you for a five-minute submission.
We have read your submission, and if you just leave a little bit of time at the end
for any questions members might have.
And you might need to unmute yourself, and if you can switch your camera on, that
would be great.
Okay.
Doesn't look like that's going to be a goer for the moment while Julie sorts out
some of the technical matters she might have.
So we will move on to the Wellington Lived Experience Advisory Group with Richard,
please.
Hi, Richard.
There we go.
Fantastic. Thanks, Richard. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We've got you for 10 minutes. If you can, just leave a few minutes
at the end for any members that might have questions. Over to you.
Yep. I'm sorry my camera is playing up.
Thank you for allowing me to speak to the select
committee.
I am one of the co-chairs of the Lived
Experience Advisory Group, which is made up of
people with lived experience of mental
distress and/or addictions, and
provide policy information and
support under Te Whatu Ora.
We are very concerned about this
proposed bill,
and view that it does not address any of the
underlying causes of antisocial
behavior, begging, or rough sleeping
that the move-on orders are meant to address.
It just moves it elsewhere. A classic
example is something that Rachel talked about
earlier,
with her being in Wellington.
Wellington City Council years ago passed
several bylaws to address concerns
of business owners of antisocial behavior
around the area of Manners Mall,
Cuba Mall, and Courtney Place.
This just moved the problem to Te Aro Valley
and Newtown.
The purpose of the bill is to grant new powers to the
police to enable them to issue a notice that
an individual must leave an area for a
period of no longer than 24 hours.
Police already have a number of powers to address
antisocial behavior under current laws
or bylaws.
From a lived experience perspective,
the move-on orders provide several
concerns. So as Rachel mentioned
in her submission earlier-
It moves the person away from supports.
So those who are sleeping rough or begging will
tend to be around where
NGOs exist,
churches,
or members of the public
that support them.
In areas like
Wellington, if you get a move on
order in Cuba Mall, it will mean that you will
be unlikely to access Downtown
Community Ministry,
which provides support to homeless people,
provide bank accounts, and food.
On the issue of food,
providing a move on order
may prevent someone who is sleeping
rough from accessing food.
Several NGOs and churches
distribute donated food from
supermarkets, cafes, and function centers.
In Wellington, this is Kaibosh and
is a very effective process. So that is something
that for a period of 24 hours, they won't be able
to access.
And as I mentioned earlier, it removes them from any
additional help and support.
So the staff at NGOs and churches know
who is on the local streets around them,
and they will actually go for a walk and
check on individuals and making sure they are okay.
In terms of the public,
yes, I will acknowledge there are members
of the community who cause
a lot of disruption, but they are a small portion
of those who have to sleep rough or beg.
There are a number of people who, due to
circumstances beyond their control,
find themselves on the streets. I was one
of those at the age of 16.
Members of the public will sometimes just stop by
and have a chat and see if the person is
okay. Do they need a cup of
noodles or something small? So this
is potentially limiting
the support.
Further on, Section 8 requires the
individual to remain a certain distance
for a set time.
Many of those who may be affected by
a move on order have lower literacy skills
and are unlikely to own a watch.
They may not know when an order is to
expire because they don't have a watch or can't tell
the time. Or they may not know
where
the point is 500 meters away or a kilometer
away, unless it is clearly described to them
by the constable issuing the notice.
This has the potential for
unintentional breaches of
the move on order by accident.
Section 8C of this bill provides
police the power to detain an individual for
issuing and serving a move on order, but
also taking a person's biographical details.
Many of this community will have had
previous interactions with the police,
and they will have often been negative in
nature.
There is a real risk of an individual becoming
agitated
and the interaction escalated because of this.
I saw an example the other day where an
ambulance officer was providing first aid
to someone on the street, and they were
surrounded by six police officers.
So you can imagine, I think, what that individual
felt, and you would not expect, as a standard
member of public, if you needed intervention
by a paramedic, that there would be six police
officers surrounding you.
Section 8F states that if an
individual breaches the order
knowingly, recklessly, or without reasonable
excuse, they can be fined
$2,000 or three months in prison.
This penalizes the poor, as they are
unlikely to be able to
pay this, and the fine has the potential
to create a significant legal debt and act
as a further barrier to getting off the street and
increase the need to beg.
Fines can accumulate, causing further
financial and mental distress.
The judge does have the option of swapping a fine
out for a prison sentence.
But this creates further issues down the track, as
a criminal conviction is often a barrier to
housing and employment.
So I would hope that from a lived
experience point of view, that you can understand
some of the issues that this proposed bill faces.
Thank you.
Fantastic, Richard. Thank you very much for your submission.
Doesn't look like there's any questions for you, but we just want to say thank you
for coming before us this afternoon, and for your written submission as well.
Thank you very much.
Members, Julie's now unavailable to present her submission, so
we will go onto the next submitter, which is Kayla.
Doesn't-- Ah, okay. Doesn't look like we've got Kayla,
but we do have Jodi. Fantastic. Thank you, Jodi, for joining us this
afternoon. You've got five minutes. We've read your written submission.
Just leave a little bit of time at the end for questions.
Sure. Well, I don't know what I can add to all the submissions
I've been listening to today that have vehemently
opposed this bill. And as I put in my submission,
what is this government doing? How can you sleep at night?
I would really like to tautoko the
V Bloom's
submission, as well as Te Oro Whakawhanaungatanga,
or Tāmaki Makaurau, and the Hamilton
Epilepsy Society. Now, both V's and my father's
followed a similar path in their life,
and I just think there for the grace of God, go I.
I could've wound up homeless myself.
Thankfully, I went and lived with my mother after my parents
divorced. But her boyfriend went and gambled
away all our rent, and if it wasn't for our neighbors
living two houses down the road, who were about to move out of
their house,
we were able to
live there in our caravan until they vacated the house and we could take over
the rental.
Now,
I'm a teacher aide these days, and I just see the impact
that
all of these types of legislation
are impacting on our tamariki.
I'm
really
actually speechless. It's
like, how can you
sleep at night? How can you sit there and listen to all these
submissions
and not come up with a better plan?
You know,
the Children's Commissioner is not being reinstated.
She needs to be reinstated.
Can I just ask you,
why are MPs with their privileged
salaries,
why are some of them getting $1,000 a week accommodation
benefits when that money could be going to help the homeless?
Could you please answer me that?
Jodi, we're not generally in a position for members of the committee to
answer questions on it, but the question you have related to is a
decision made by the Independent Remuneration Authority.
It's not made by individual members of Parliament.
And there is a new Children's Commissioner. Yeah.
It's just that that current one hasn't been reappointed, but another one has been
appointed.
Well, that is a true relief, I can
tell you. But it's just really concerning that,
as the Children Commissioner said in her
submission, there are so many
recommendations made, and they just
don't seem to be
getting through to you guys at the top.
You guys have got all the power.
There's just so many people that are invisible but
are impacted by homelessness, that are impacted by
abuse,
poverty,
all kinds of issues. And
Minister Luxon just
showed his complete ignorance about that issue in Parliament
with not recognizing that there were any night
shelters.
But so many people have
submitted today. All I can do
is mihi to Tamatha Paul, who seems to
be one
politician who is actually doing something to
help the homeless
and the vulnerable people in Wellington.
In my submission,
it doesn't take
too much to be kind
to
people who are begging on the street.
Even in Motueka, where I live, I've sat down with--
We have two homeless people in our town at the moment,
and
I'm a type one diabetic. I always have a banana in my
bag. It doesn't take
much to just kia ora. And every time I go to Wellington,
Auckland,
I always give
people begging
a gold coin or say, "Kia ora. How's it
going?"
That's what I can do because
I'm on a teacher aids wage.
Maybe you guys can just lift it up a little
with your wages.
Fund
all these countless
organizations that are doing their best
to support the homeless, that are supporting people who have
come out of...
The names escape me.
Sorry, guys, but-
It's okay, Jodi. We have gone-
You get my point.
We do. We do. And we have gone significantly over your time, so I'm sorry we don't
have any time for questions. But we do thank you for your submission
this afternoon and for your written submission to the committee as well.
Okay. Thank you.
Thanks, Jodi
Thank you for your time.
No problems.
Go-
All right. Come to our next submitter, which is Diane.
Hi, Diane.
We can't hear you, Diane.
Can you hear me now?
We can. Fantastic.
Slow but-
We've got you down for 10 minutes.
We have read your written submission and just leave some time for questions.
Sovereign
Nation of Muupokl. He kura hou ki oi CEO of Muupokl
Tribal Authority.
Thank you all for this opportunity to speak.
Our submission was small, but to the point of strongly
opposing the bill, and having
seen a number of other submissions online
today, we tautoko
the sentiments that have been expressed about the concern of
this
proposed amendment bill.
What we thought we would do is make some key points.
One is around
we see this as in the '60s and '70s,
our young people were collected from
situations of mainly poverty or other
circumstances,
collected off the street.
And now we see that play out in the prison
population that we face today. There is plenty of research that
shows that the actions undertaken in the '60s and
'70s are what we face in the prison population
playing out today. And we absolutely don't want to see that
perpetuated in any way.
We are a pre-settlement iwi, but we do actively
participate where we can and funding allows
in all manner of vulnerable housing solutions, both from
a social and hauora services point of view,
but also as a partner in community
solutions for housing.
Housing itself is one of the key
enablers for us not to even need this bill.
So we really want to see the investment go to the right place.
Currently, we see this as a response, and
an inappropriate one, to poverty and mental illness, where the
investment should be going, and not into this bill.
We agree with the analysis that says that it
allows children as young as 14 years old to be detained,
fined, or criminally charged for behaviors
associated with homelessness.
In tautoko a bit,
I'm not saying we have a huge and critical problem, but we certainly
do have our share of people and whanau
who are, because of their circumstances,
sleeping on the streets.
And
they're not doing that out of choice. That's the key thing.
And what this does is basically, to us, feels like, as
I say, criminalizing poverty and mental illness,
aside from the risk of this being perpetuating
historical issues.
We think anyway that
we have, and Horowhenua has a bit of a unique
perspective on this because as an iwi on our whenua,
we've seen a lot of state-oriented
interventions that have sought to,
whether it's Kimberly or it's Kohitahi
and Hokia Boys, we've seen a lot of
state institutions as the result of bills and acts
that have forced people into situations that
are
Penalizing them, as I say, for poverty and/or mental illness and
a range of other things, disconnection, identity.
So it's our preference to be part of the,
uh, see the investment going into
solutions. We remain ready, waiting, and
willing to be able to be part of the solution with our community,
um, and across our agency and partners, and that's where we'd wish to see,
uh, any investment, uh, and attention go.
Thank you so much for your time
being granted to us for this.
Thank you, Diane. We will-- I will just see.
We've got a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Uh, thank you, Chair, and thanks, Diane.
Your submission has a similar theme to the Law
Association of New Zealand submission, where it described this bill
as moving away from the traditional criminal law model, where police
powers generally respond to completed offending towards,
like, an intervention-based or anticipated conduct
model. And I was just wondering if you had anything to add on what
moving away from that traditional criminal law model might mean
for young people, and if there was anything around that aspect of
the bill that the committee should be considering.
Um,
that was an accident, if it, if it has a close
assimilation. But it may have happened because
our experience here with young people is exactly that.
Because of Horowhenua statistics and because of their
population demographics, we actually have a dedicated
rangatahi team.
And, um, the focus on programs and
mentoring, and alongside that, because we are an iwi
org, we are pre-settlement, but we do have Whanau Ora services.
The ability for us to take a whole of family or whanau
approach,
uh, is the key.
So, so we can create or enable-- Not create, because
we don't. Our whanau do that. We can work with and
enable individual circumstances of rangatahi,
but the true impactful change happens when we do two things:
work with whanau
and also work with the,
I guess, partners, agencies, schools that work
alongside our young people. And in a community
like Horowhenua, I think there's a reason we've often been chosen to be
the prototypes and pilots of so many things.
Um, but that's not hard to do if we are, if we are
able to line up that way. So we
favor being able to take a,
a one-on-one sort of mentoring within a whanau
context approach to our rangatahi.
Thanks, Diane. Appreciate that.
Fantastic, Diane. Thank you so much for your time this afternoon and for your
written submission to the committee as well.
Thank you very much.
Have a good evening. Thanks, Diane.
Thank you, Chair.
Okay, members, our next submitter is going to be Pippa, who is with us online.
Hey, Pippa. Thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
Um, we've read your written submission.
We've got you down for five minutes, if you can just leave some time at the end for
questions.
Tena koe, Chair. Kia ora koutou. Thank you for the opportunity to give an
oral submission. I'm going to be very brief,
um, because you've already heard ample evidence about why move on
orders are draconian and an, and an inappropriate tool
to address antisocial behavior, begging or homelessness.
You've heard how move on orders are likely to divert frontline officers
from core policing functions. You've heard the lived
experience of those who've ended up on the streets through no fault of
their own,
and the support they desperately need.
I'd really like to mihi to all of the submitters who've fronted up to
this process, which can feel very performative,
um, and those who are working on the front line of the housing and health
crisis and fighting to uphold fundamental rights.
I'm s- presenting as a former elected representative of
Auckland City Centre, and I just bring my perspective that
I really understand how important it is that the city
center feels safe, welcoming, and vi-vibrant for
everybody who lives there, comes in to visit, study, and
work.
And I'm sure the promoters of the bill, they want to look like they're taking
action, and that they're doing so in the interests of public
safety. However, move on orders are
just not the solution to systemic problems.
And as you've heard, move on orders will just compound
existing disparities and increase harm to the most
vulnerable.
Um, like poor houses and vagrancy laws, move on orders
should really be left in the 19th century because they really
have no place in a modern, caring society, and I think
you've really heard that from a whole variety of submitters.
So I just ask that the committee reflect on that evidence, reject the
bill in its entirety, and recommend solutions
like Housing First, that we know work,
and that will actually improve the lives of the most vulnerable
and will make our cities, town cen- cities and town centers
safe and welcoming for everyone. Nga mihi.
Fantastic, Pippa. Thank you. We've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thanks so much, Pippa, and just acknowledging your work in this area too
in central Auckland.
I just had a question around the powers that are already in
place. We've had quite a few submissions looking at existing police
powers, and one of the things that we looked at, I think on our first day of
submissions and discussed briefly with Richard Northey, was the bylaw that's
in place in Auckland City. I just wanted to give you the opportunity
to reflect on the other tools that we have at this stage
and whether move on orders are adding anything
to that toolkit in respect of
antisocial behavior because I think the points on begging and homelessness
have been well made in opposition.
Yeah. And I think that's a good point to
emphasize, that there are already a range of tools that can be used for the
offenses that occur. And I know that workers, say in
retail, they don't want to arrive at work and find someone
sleeping in their shop front or to feel
unsafe. And that's where the police are already
engaging in a very empathetic way.
And we've seen too that the Auckland Council has stepped up with compliance
wardens who are walking the street in the morning, and
that's really an effective approach where they get to know people, and
they're essentially doing
that work already to find places for people to go and getting to
know their names. And so that's just one of the
tools. There's a range of police solutions, bylaws, and
empathetic agencies that are already
operating on the streets. But what they need is resourcing and
funding.
Fantastic. Thank you very much, Pippa.
Really appreciate your submission this afternoon and the written one as well.
Thank you. Ka kite.
All right, our next submitter is going to be the community of St.
Luke, Remuera, and we're going to have them come up
now.
Good afternoon. Thank you both for joining us.
We have read your written submission.
We've got you down for 10 minutes, and if you just leave some time at the end for
questions. Over to you.
Thank you very much. I'm Alison Poulin, and this is Alexa
Johnston. We are here on behalf of the community of St.
Luke Presbyterian Church and a community center based
in Remuera in Auckland.
As people of faith, we believe in compassion and justice,
which leads us to always try our best to stand with
those who are marginalized in our society, focusing on acting in
ways that promote the common good rather than the
comfort of the rich.
Because of this, our church is a founding member of Te Ohu Tamakii,
which is
a community alliance of over 40 organizations seeking to give voice to some of
the most difficult problems our society faces.
I believe you heard from them today with Marlon Drake.
Thank you very much for the opportunity to submit on this proposed
legislation. I realize you are near the end of a very busy day,
and for this reason, we plan to make our comments brief.
Our belief is that this bill is
criminalizing poverty. As Christians, this appalls us.
Christ's approach to those who were poor and marginalized was to
try to help them by engaging with them and providing for their
needs, not pushing them away so they can't be seen.
The issues that cause homelessness in the first place are many and
varied, including addiction, mental health difficulties,
racism, unstable job markets, and reduction in state
housing.
We acknowledge the significant pressures on social services,
whose staff are trying to respond to increasing numbers of desperate people.
The move on orders, we believe, will not solve the problem of rough sleeping,
merely transfer it elsewhere.
Such orders will make it even harder to build the relationships of trust,
which are so critical for providing the help that is needed.
Over to Alexa.
Kia ora koutou. I'm Alexa Johnston.
As you've heard from Alison, at the community of St.
Luke and as members of Te Ohu Tamakii Community Alliance, we
are people of goodwill with serious concerns about justice and human
dignity and human rights in our community.
And homelessness is a complex issue, as Alison said, with many causes,
and it's a challenging problem for our society.
And we all know that challenging problems require serious thinking,
and this bill is not serious, and it's not thoughtful.
It's shortsighted, impractical, unworkable, bullying, and
cruel.
Its approach to the homelessness crisis has been widely criticized, and you've
heard many of them today, I'm sure, but groups like Karangahape Road Business
Association, the Police Association, numerous social service
agencies, and the government's own social support ministries.
They describe the proposed bill as lacking in serious intent to improve the
situation, unworkable, superficial, and ultimately
damaging to our communities.
And so we reject the current bill, and we endorse the solutions proposed by
Community Housing Aotearoa, who you've also heard from today.
As they say, "Housing and support will end homelessness.
Bullying and enforcement will not."
Drawing on international experience and research, CHA suggests a
six-point plan to effectively combat homelessness.
Kaupapa Maori-led housing solutions, which uphold mana motuhake
and effectively combat homelessness.
Housing first. The international research shows the most effective response is
permanent housing with wraparound support.
Transitional housing provides stability and connection while permanent
housing is found.
Assertive outreach builds trust and links people to housing and support services.
And local community-led support responses can best deliver
tailored, culturally responsive support.
And of course, homelessness prevention.
We need to ensure that no one is discharged from health, justice,
care, or protection systems into homelessness.
These humane and effective responses to Aotearoa's human catastrophe
require central and local government active support and
funding.
And so in conclusion, we join with thousands of citizens in Aotearoa who
are outraged by the actions proposed in this bill.
We will continue to organize around this issue, promoting humane and effective
actions from our government to end the tragic and shameful incidents of
homelessness in our country.
And I repeat, thoughtfulness, seriousness, and compassion for those in
need and distress should be the prime movers of our government at this time.
We look forward to seeing this bill set aside and better solutions
proposed and resourced.
Fantastic. We've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Ngā mihi kia kōrua. Thank you both for your very strong
written and oral submission.
I had a question. I know that this is not the basis of your opposition to the bill,
because especially as you outlined the
Christian beliefs that you have around how we treat others.
But as an organization that is based
centrally, although not in the central city in Auckland, do you have some
concerns around these move on orders simply
meaning that people in Auckland will move from the central city into
places like Remuera because they can't
be in the central city?
Well, so no. Actually, neither of us live in Remuera.
Our church is a progressive Presbyterian community which pulls people from all over
the place. So we say Remuera because it makes us sound more
I know, sorry. No, we don't. That's not an issue for us.
It's just it's an appalling idea to treat these people in this cruel way.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you both for joining us this afternoon.
That's all we've got with you, so thank you very much for your time and your
submission.
Thank you.
All right. Members, we come to Nicola, who is going to be submitting next.
Hey, Nicola, can you hear us okay?
We can't hear you. I'm sorry, Nicola.
Yeah, sorry, Nicola. You are our last submitter for the day, so I'm not quite
sure. We can't really break and come back to you. I'm sorry.
No worries. I'm really sorry about that.
We do have your written submission anyway, but I do apologize
that
sometimes technology plays this way.
But thank you anyway for your willingness to want to submit and be with us, and
have a good evening.
Okay, members, that brings us to the close of our consideration
of submissions today. We're going to move to our private Zoom link
now, please.